<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The harmony between the old and present non-conformists principles in relation to the terms of conformity, with respect both to the clergie, and the people : wherein a short history of the original of the English liturgy, and some reasons why several truly conscientious Christians cannot joyn with the church in it : humbly presented to publick consideration in order to the obtaining some necessary relaxation and indulgence : to which are added some letters that pass'd between the Lord Cecil, and Arch-bishop Whitgift.</title>
            <author>Lobb, Stephen, d. 1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 257 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48863</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2726</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23045</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12238696</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12238696</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56725</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48863)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56725)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 606:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The harmony between the old and present non-conformists principles in relation to the terms of conformity, with respect both to the clergie, and the people : wherein a short history of the original of the English liturgy, and some reasons why several truly conscientious Christians cannot joyn with the church in it : humbly presented to publick consideration in order to the obtaining some necessary relaxation and indulgence : to which are added some letters that pass'd between the Lord Cecil, and Arch-bishop Whitgift.</title>
                  <author>Lobb, Stephen, d. 1699.</author>
                  <author>Whitgift, John, 1530?-1604.</author>
                  <author>Burghley, William Cecil, Baron, 1520-1598.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Joseph Collier ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Liturgy.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56725:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HARMONY Between the Old and Preſent <hi>Non-Conformiſts</hi> PRINCIPLES, In Relation to the TERMS of Conformity, With Reſpect both to the CLERGIE, and the PEOPLE.</p>
            <p>Wherein A ſhort Hiſtory of the Original of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> LITURGY, and ſome Reaſons why ſeveral truly Conſcientious Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians cannot joyn with the Church in it.</p>
            <p>Humbly Preſented to Publick Conſideration in order to the obtaining ſome neceſſary Relaxation and Indulgence.</p>
            <p>To which are added ſome Letters that paſs'd between the Lord <hi>Cecil,</hi> and Arch-Biſhop <hi>Whitgift.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>The Fault is on both ſides, and on neither ſide. For the Godly wiſe on both ſides bear with each other, and concenter in the main. But then there be ſelfiſh, peeviſh Spirits, on both ſides ſome, and theſe make the Quarrel.</p> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Greenham</hi>'s Anſwer to the Lord <hi>Cecil</hi>'s Queſtion, Who is the Faulty Cauſer of the Diviſion in the Church?</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed and are to be ſold by <hi>Joſeph Collier</hi> on <hi>London-Bridge,</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:56725:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56725:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Right Reverend</hi> Edward <hi>Lord Biſhop of</hi> Cork <hi>and</hi> Roſs <hi>in</hi> Ireland.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>ON a peruſal of your late Treatiſe, Entituled, <hi>The Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Peace Maker,</hi> I find your Lordſhip ſo very much diſpoſ'd to purſue Charity, Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, the only neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary mean left us for the preſervation of the Reformed Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that though I am a perfect ſtranger to you, I cannot chooſe but make, and hope that you will Candidly receive this preſent Dedication.</p>
                     <p>
                        <q>There is now (as your Lordſhip expreſſes it <hi>p. 29.)</hi> an argument for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, which muſt be heard, and is uncontroulable; <hi>We muſt Unite or be deſtroyed.</hi> At all times Chriſtian duty obliges us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: now <hi>neceſſity</hi> or <hi>ſelf-preſervation</hi> too, or more parties may bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance one, when any ſingle other cannot. [Thus 'tis evident we muſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite.] The ſtrength of the Proteſtant Cauſe, both here, at home, and throughout Chriſtendom lies in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of Proteſtants, and the glory, purity and power of Chriſtianity in this world, ſtand or falls with Proteſtantiſm.</q> But the only queſtion is upon what Termes muſt the Church of <hi>England</hi> come over to the Diſſenters, or the Diſſenters go over to the Church.</p>
                     <p>The right ſtating the true Termes of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion is a work of extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary difficulty, a work that requires the heads and hearts of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, the moſt judicious and Holy men on earth to contribute all they can towards it. Government in the Church must be ſecur'd, tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences reliev'd; Where there is no government, all things will run in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to confuſion, where there is no relief for tender Conſciences, there can be no union. The government of a National Church muſt be National, and ſuch as is moſt exactly ſuited to the civil conſtitution of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ou, The former muſt not interferr with the later. But of this, though your Lordſhip ſpeakes nothing, yet may your Lordſhip ſee ſomething (God permitting it) in good time that ſome Diſſenters have to offer towards the healing our breaches, and that alſo in a way conſiſtent with an eſtabliſhment of ſuch a National Church government, as agrees with the antient conſtitution of this Kingdom: That which your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip's wiſdom hath inſiſted on, is a point of moment and importance, namely, the <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> concerning which you propoſe <hi>mutual conceſſions</hi> and <hi>approaches,</hi> as the only probable uniting ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient. <q>Now if <hi>complyance</hi> be likelyeſt to do the buſineſs, (you ſay, let us relax a little on both hands in the fear of God, and fall
<pb facs="tcp:56725:3"/>
upon it; Let us Candidly conſult what good Conſcience, what pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence will bear towards an accommodation.</q> (To this you add <hi>Page 118. 119.)</hi> 
                        <q>I do not conceive the alteration of an expreſſion, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps here and there of an whole Prayer or two, by Law, or the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing (ſtill by Law) with ſome ceremony <hi>in Law,</hi> for the ſake of ſome unſatisfied, but otherwiſe <hi>regular Chriſtians</hi> (who are not ſuppos'd of the Cathedral Body) I ſay, I do not conceive ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion or relaxation as this, would break the harmony and beauty of our worſhip, or diſturb the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion or Peace of our Church. I will therefore freely publiſh my thoughts to be, that whither we Conſider the Nature of the thing it ſelf, or with regard to the Apoſtle's Rule. <hi>Rom. 15. 1, 2. Not to pleaſe our ſelves, but every one of us to pleaſe his Neighbour for his good to Edification.</hi> In either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard I ſay, there are ſome <hi>Collects,</hi> and perhaps <hi>Rubricks</hi> too, which with all Duty and Submiſſion I humbly conceive may be alter'd for the better. And farther that in ſome Seaſons, and in ſome private places.—If the Obligation to a Ceremony or two were taken off, the benefit which would hence redound to the Church would be very Conſiderable.—And I ſeem to my ſelf herein to follow the ſenſe and guidance of our Church, for even at preſent the Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Ceremonies does not appear to me to extend it ſelf to all places and ſeaſons. There are alſo divers other points, which when once the deſign of a fair Accommodation ſhall be on foot, will be fit to be mentioned, and indeed will both of Courſe offer themſelves, and be I judge, as eaſily granted; ſuch as the <hi>Liberty</hi> of exchanging <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criphal</hi> Leſſons for <hi>Canonical</hi> ones, any Amendment of ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, as can be prov'd, in the <hi>Calendar,</hi> The <hi>Uſe</hi> of the moſt <hi>Correct Tranſlation</hi> of the <hi>Pſalms.</hi> A better Metrical Verſion al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and perhaps <hi>ſome like matters,</hi> which we may account ſmall, ſome <hi>Diffenters</hi> do not.</q>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>May the expedient you propoſe be attended unto, the deſired <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion would ſoon be obtained, for thereby all thoſe <hi>Arguments</hi> mentioned in the enſuing Treatiſe, which preſs hard on the Conſciences of ſome Diſſenters, concerning the preſent Terms of Communion, would be anſwered, their Conſciences relieved, and they be of the ſame exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Communion with the Church of <hi>England.</hi> I do therefore humbly preſume to beſeech your Lordſhip to do your utmoſt for the furthering this peaceable, and uniting Deſign, for certainly you have hit on
<pb facs="tcp:56725:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
what, if cloſely followed, will reconcile us, and as your Lordſhip will expreſs it, <hi>this is the only probable expedient,</hi> for 'tis an undoubted Truth, That there are among the Diſſenters a conſiderable Number, who are under the moſt powerful, and plain Convictions of Conſcience about the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawfulneſs of the preſent <hi>Liturgy</hi> as Ordered by the <hi>Canon,</hi> and <hi>Rubrick</hi> to be uſed, and of the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> that they cannot but by ſinning againſt God to the wounding of their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, <hi>conform.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That the World may be aſſured of this much, and ſee how neceſſary ſome Relaxations are in Order unto <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion. I have ſhewn what are the Sentiments of ſome of the moſt Judicious and more moderate Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, why 'tis yet they conform not to the <hi>Terms of Lay-Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> impos'd by the Church, and why 'tis they <hi>erect ſeperate Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations.</hi> Some are ſo fully Convinced of the unlawfulneſs of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Liturgy, and Ceremonies, that they refuſe to Conform, becauſe they think their Conformity to be <hi>ſinful,</hi> but other do not ſo much inſiſt on the <hi>ſinfulneſs,</hi> as on the <hi>Inexpediency</hi> of their Conformity. They cannot Conform without <hi>Scandal.</hi> By <hi>Scandal</hi> they mean (as your Lordſhip doth) with the Scripture generally) <hi>The drawing,</hi> or <hi>encouraging others to do what they are not in Conſcience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd they may do.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>There is a real Diſpoſition, yea, longing Deſires among the <hi>Non-Conformiſts</hi> towards a Proteſtant <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, and it rejoyceth their very Souls to find ſome ſuch as your Lordſhip among the dignified Ciergie, and do bleſs God for you. There are ſome ſuch alſo in <hi>England,</hi> who, tho' they Conform, do it <hi>not blindfold,</hi> nor upon <hi>Corrupt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements.</hi> We believe there are many of you, <hi>who can in the fear of God, profeſs you have again, and again conſidered the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Laws,</hi> and <hi>according to your Duty, as you believe, you have been, and are obedient, not only for Wrath, but alſo for Conſcience ſake,</hi> and that you are <hi>Sound Proteſtants,</hi> and as great an Eye-Sore to the Papiſt, as any among the Diſſenters. However we are as Confident, That there are others, who are pretendedly at leaſt great zealots for Conformity, and yet Aimrather at an <hi>Union</hi> between the <hi>Church of</hi> England, and <hi>the Church of</hi> Rome, who conſequently hate a Proteſtant Diſſenter much more than they do a Papiſt, not being aſham'd to profeſs <hi>They would</hi> rather be <hi>Papiſts, than Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:56725:4"/>
There are many ſuch, who delight not only to miſrepreſent the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter, as your Lordſhip will perceive by the <hi>Reverend Mr. Baxter's</hi> reply to your Poſtſcript, but moreover, to <hi>Unchurch all the Foreign Reformed Churches,</hi> who have not an <hi>Epiſcopal Ordination,</hi> Thus Mr. <hi>Conold</hi> in his <hi>Notion of Schiſm</hi> Dedicated to <hi>Anthony Lord Biſhop of</hi> Norwich, <hi>p. 14.</hi> aſſerts, <q>That he who is out of this Line of <hi>Apoſtolick Succeſſion,</hi> and exerciſes any Miniſterial Office without the Commiſſion of <hi>Epiſcopal Ordination</hi> is but a <hi>Lay-Impoſter,</hi> and a <hi>Schiſmatick</hi> from the Catholick Church,</q> and <hi>(p. 43.)</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Foreign</hi> Proteſtant Churches, adds, <q>But if any of them have a Miniſtry which have no other Orders than their own <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation, or popular Election, I know not how to Acquit them from being Shiſmaticks from the Catholick Church.</q> But yet though he is ſo <hi>ſevere</hi> in Cenſuring the Foreign Proteſtant Churches as Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks from the Catholick Church, he is as <hi>Merciful</hi> to Foreign Papiſts, for in his <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Reader.</hi> 
                        <q>As for thoſe of your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion [vid. the Popiſh] who live under the Laws of the <hi>Romiſh Dominions,</hi> I have a great Charity for them (ſays he) for they can plead Submiſſion to their own <hi>Superiors,</hi> and I am apt to believe, that plea may be very conſiderable, when they come to appear before the <hi>Prince of Peace</hi> and the <hi>God of</hi> Order.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>There having been ſome ſuch in the Church of <hi>England</hi> ever ſince the firſt Reformation, they have impeded all Eſſayes for a Proteſtant <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, and have done their utmoſt rather to Accommodate the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences between <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s and <hi>Rome,</hi> whereby Inſtead of Relaxations and Abatements towards Diſſenters. The Church of <hi>England</hi> has made the Terms of Communion the more difficult and uneaſie unto us, to the hightning and increaſing the Diviſions, and at this very day will be at the ſame work, wherein, unleſs timely prevented, they may ſucceed. We beſeech your Lordſhip therefore to animate your Brethren, who are hearty to the Proteſtant Intereſt to Conſider with juſt regards the tender Conſciences of Diſſenting Proteſtants, and to appear in making a brisk Oppoſition to thoſe, who under pretence of making the Church of <hi>England</hi> the more Grand, and <hi>Auguſt</hi> deſigns her Ruine by bringing her into her Antient Slavery to the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>'Tis to be wiſhed a Bill <hi>Comprehenſive</hi> of all Sound Proteſtants might paſs in Order to the uniting us, But if that cannot be, a Bill leſſer Comprehenſive<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with an <hi>Indulgence</hi> will very much contribute to
<pb facs="tcp:56725:4"/>
the Churches peace, and the ſtrengthning the Proteſtant Intereſt. To which end, That the Advice your Lordſhip gives <hi>p. 62. to the end,</hi> may be regarded by all, is the Prayer of him who highly values your Lordſhips great Learning, your Chriſtian Temper, and Moderation, and who is</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your Humble Servant.</signed>
                        <date>April. 1. 1682.</date>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>The Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge 7. l. 11. <hi>dele who.</hi> p. 9. l. 2. <hi>After</hi> then <hi>add, my work is.</hi> l. 18. <hi>dele For.</hi> l. 35. <hi>for they</hi> r. <hi>the Diſſenters,</hi> p. 19. l. 22. <hi>for if</hi> r. <hi>of.</hi> p. 20. l. 23. <hi>After</hi> then <hi>add the Biſhops of.</hi> p. 21. l. 32. <hi>for Families</hi> r. <hi>Faculties.</hi> p. 23. l. 7. <hi>after</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection add <hi>has offer'd:</hi> p. 26. l. ult. r. <hi>of.</hi> p. 28. l. 10. <hi>dele of</hi> p. 32. l. 18. r. <hi>it has.</hi> p. 33. l. 10. <hi>d. and.</hi> l. 28. r. <hi>Proctors,</hi> p. 34. l. 11. r. <hi>Scultingius.</hi> p. 35. l. 15. r. Intelligencers. p. 40. l. 1. r. <hi>pages.</hi> p. 41. l. ult. <hi>add That is ſeveral Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Veſtments.</hi> p. 42. l. 9. <hi>after</hi> affairs <hi>add than in Civil.</hi> p. 44. l. 6. <hi>after drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs add does.</hi> p. 48. l. 5. r. <hi>Superstitious.</hi> p. 55. l. 13. r. Prince. p. 59. l. 19. r. <hi>Parity.</hi> p. 60. l. 10. r. <hi>to.</hi> l. ult. r. 2. p 71. l. 27. r. <hi>Rites.</hi> l. 38. <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> that <hi>add are.</hi> l. ult. r. <hi>why.</hi> p. 72. l. ult. r. <hi>Wild.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:56725:5"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>THE deſign of the enſuing Treatiſe is only to ſhew, <hi>how neceſſary</hi> 'tis, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> make the Terms of Communion with her ſomewhat more <hi>eaſie.</hi> For 'tis certain, that whatever ſome ſuggeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the fancy, humour and obſtinacy of Diſſenters; He who is the ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of hearts doth know, that they are <hi>Conſcientious</hi> in their Non-conformity, Could they with a good Conſcience conform, they would, but ſeeing they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, (as appears by what is inſiſted on in this Treatiſe) what muſt they do? They muſt not ſin and offend God to pleaſe men.</p>
            <p>'Tis not altogether improbable but that a <hi>Conformiſt</hi> in his peruſal of the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments in the following diſcourſe, may be ſupply'd with an anſwer ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to himſelf, and many others, notwithſtanding which, the Diſſenters may ſtill feel more conviction in thoſe arguments for their Non-conformity, than in any reply made to 'em, and therefore cannot Conſcientiouſly conform.</p>
            <p>Hitherto the Diſſenters have been reproach'd as a people, who cauſe diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Church about <hi>Trifles,</hi> who though they won't now Conform, if there were a Bill of Comprehenſion on no eaſier Termes than a complying with the uſe of the Liturgy, they would generally do it: I have therefore upon a ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and deliberate weighing all things, thought it meet at this ſeaſon (when a late book of a ſingular brother calls aloud for it,) to give an impartial account of the Diſſenters ſentiments, which are more general concerning Conformity, having done it impartially, rather indeed like an <hi>Historian</hi> than a <hi>Logician.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The great thing I abide by, and judge my ſelf oblig'd to defend is. 1. That <hi>there are arguments powerfull enough</hi> in <hi>the judgments of ſome, to faſten plain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victious on 'em, concerning the</hi> unlawfulneſs <hi>or</hi> inexpediency <hi>of the uſe of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Ordinary Lord's dayes Service;</hi> Though I may not be convinc'd by them, yet others may. 2. <hi>That ſo long as any Diſſenters are thus fully convinc'd of the</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulneſs <hi>or</hi> inexpediency <hi>of the Liturgy,</hi> they <hi>must not act contrary to the plain conviction of their</hi> Conſcience <hi>and Conform;</hi> If then there be any peace in the Church, it muſt be either by a familiar, ſweet and plain diſcovery of their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, or by a relaxing ſomewhat the rigor of the Terms of Communion. The <hi>Forms</hi> by many years experience we find impoſſible, and therefore as the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Cork</hi> and <hi>Roſs</hi> expreſſes it, <hi>the only probable expedient for Union left us is</hi> the <hi>later.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the following <hi>Hiſtory</hi> I muſt ſay, that I have confin'd my ſelf to urge thoſe arguments of the Old Non-conformiſts, which are againſt thoſe parts of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy now in being, and I have done it without paſſion or partiality. My great care hath been to propoſe with indifference <hi>their</hi> judgment, to the end the Reader, conſidering it with the ſame equal mind as 'tis written, may be the better enabled to paſs a Candid Cenſure on the whole.</p>
            <p>I have not been curious in the choice of words, for my deſign is only the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the <hi>vulgar,</hi> to whoſe capacity I have in the moſt familiar manner I could, adjuſted the following diſcourſe: That the God of Heaven will enable us all to follow peace with all men, and <hi>Holineſs</hi> (for we muſt not ſo far purſue peace, as to do any unholy thing in order thereunto) ought to be our dayly Prayer to the God of Heaven.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>April</hi> 3. 82.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56725:5"/>
            <head>An Account of the Non-Conformiſts Principles, concerning the Terms both of the Clergy, and Lay-Conformity.</head>
            <p>SINCE the 24th of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1662, there have been ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a <hi>Non-Conformiſt,</hi> even among the Miniſters, and People of <hi>England,</hi> who, though they have diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent apprehenſions concerning the <hi>Terms of Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> do yet all agree in their not ſubmitting unto all that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by the <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity.</hi> There are ſome among the Miniſters, who can Conſcientiouſly comply withall that is enjoyn'd the people, and there are others, that cannot.</p>
            <p>That the Reader may with the greater clearneſs underſtand, wherein the principal grounds of Non-Conformity conſiſt, I will with the greateſt impartiality attempt the giving a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular account of the Principles of thoſe, who are now moſt commonly known by the name of Diſſenters. Not that I deſign to inſiſt on all thoſe principles, they profeſs to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace, as they are ſound Chriſtians, and good Proteſtants, but only to ſhew, what their Judgment is, as they are <hi>Diſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> from the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. There being a great difference between the <hi>Terms</hi> of Conformity impoſed on the <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and thoſe enjoyn'd the <hi>People,</hi> there are ſome among the Non-Conforming Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, who can ſubmit unto the impoſitions laid on the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but not unto what is exacted from the Miniſters. They can hear, yea read the <hi>ordinary Lord's days Service,</hi> and joyn in the Communion of the Church, but yet cannot <hi>Aſſent,</hi> and <hi>Conſent to every thing contained in the</hi> 39 <hi>Articles, Book</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:56725:6"/>
of <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> and <hi>Homilies already extant,</hi> and <hi>ſuch as ſhall hereafter be ſet forth, becauſe</hi> they are fully convinc'd, that there are ſeveral things contain'd in thoſe Books, which are not <hi>agreable</hi> unto the Word of God, and becauſe, they cannot divine what may be inſerted in the Book of <hi>Homilies,</hi> hereafter to be publiſhed, and are loath to ſubſcribe to they know not what. Theſe have ſo great an advantage againſt the Conformiſts, that Dr. <hi>Stilling fleet,</hi> when he firſt entred on the controverſies about the Terms of the peoples Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Church, wav'd that of the Miniſters Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity. As theſe are Non-conformiſts, ſo in their writings they triumph over the Conformiſts; But then as they do or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily ſeparate from the Communion of the Church, and erect orderly Congregations for the Adminiſtrations of all Ordinances, they have not that advantage which other Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts have; For ſay the Conformiſts unto 'em, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you look on the terms of Lay-Communion to be lawfull, and to ſhew ſo much, you do <hi>occaſionally</hi> hold Communion with us, your Communion ought to be <hi>fixed</hi> and <hi>ordinary,</hi> and that becauſe the conſideration of the Curches peace, and the authority of our Governours in the enjoyning what is confeſſedly lawfull, ſhould oblige your Conſciences.</p>
            <p>There are ſeveral things replyed. Firſt, The Miniſters, being conſecrated unto God in that Holy Function of the Miniſtry, dare not look back, they commit Sacriledge ſhould they withdraw themſelves from the Miniſtry, for wo unto them if they preach not. Secondly, The great neceſſity there is of their preaching, in order to the reforming the people; Moreover, they add, that they do not ſeparate from the Church, they do but preach as Lecturers, or Curates un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Pariſh Miniſters.</p>
            <p>In this controverſie, I'll not engage my ſelf, for my buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is principally deſign'd to give a right ſtate of the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, and, ſo far as I can, to offer ſomewhat in the Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts defence, which as to this particular, ſhall be only to clear them from that reproach which is caſt on them, about
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56725:6"/>
their going to Church, to Divine Service, and the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and yet do not conform as Miniſters. The anſwer is eaſie, <hi>viz.</hi> There is much more than theſe things required of them; <hi>Viz. Subſcriptions</hi> as enjoyn'd by the Act of Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, beſides the abjuring the Covenant, to the which ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, who have nothing to offer againſt the ordinary Lord's days Service, and the other Terms of Lay-Communion, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not yield their Conſciences.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There are other Non-conforming Miniſters, who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conſcientiouſly conform either unto the <hi>Terms</hi> impoſ'd on the <hi>Miniſter</hi> or <hi>People.</hi> Of theſe there are two ſorts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>(1.) Some, who look on the particular forms of Prayer, impoſed on all to be <hi>Lawfull,</hi> but not <hi>Expedient.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>(2.) Others who conſider <hi>this</hi> particular form of Prayer to be <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawfull.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Of the firſt opinion are ſeveral <hi>Preſbyterians,</hi> if not ſome Congregational Divines. For the clearer underſtanding their Sentiments, we muſt conſider.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there is a difference between the lawfulneſs of ſet forms of Prayer in <hi>Theſi,</hi> and in <hi>Hypotheſi;</hi> A form of Prayer in general may be lawfull, but <hi>this,</hi> or the <hi>other</hi> ſet form in particular, ſinfull. In the Popiſh Maſs Book there are ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral forms of Prayer, which are by ſound Proteſtants eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſinfull, not becauſe they are <hi>forms,</hi> ſo much as becauſe they are <hi>ſuch</hi> forms. There are very few, beſides ſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents and Anabaptiſts, who judge all forms of Prayer, becauſe they are forms, to be Unlawfull.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is alſo a difference between the <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> of a form, and its <hi>expediency.</hi> A Stinted Liturgy may in ſome caſes be both lawfull and expedient, and in other, though in it felf lawfull, yet highly inexpedient. For ought I can ſay to the contrary, a ſet form of preaching is as lawfull as a ſet form of Prayer; and 'tis manifeſt, that there was a time in the beginning of <hi>Edward the 6ths.</hi> Reign, that the making <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> for the Miniſters, was as convenient as the making <hi>Prayers</hi> for them, ſuch was the ignorance, peeviſhneſs and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56725:7"/>
contentiouſneſs of thoſe in Holy Orders; That a ſtinted form was as neeeſſary to be uſ'd in preaching as 'twas in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for which reaſon as an <hi>Engliſh Liturgy</hi> was drawn up for the Miniſters help in prayer, a <hi>Book of Homilies</hi> was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd to be read inſtead of preaching, unto both which, at firſt, all ſuch as had not a Licenſe were equally oblig'd. But though a ſtinted form of preaching be in it ſelf lawfull, doth it therefore follow that 'tis always expedient? The like may be ſaid of a form of prayer.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That about things lawfull, that is, about ſuch things as are in their own nature <hi>indifferent,</hi> enquiry muſt be made after their expediency or inexpediency <hi>pro hic,</hi> &amp; <hi>nunc.</hi> For many things which are in <hi>Theſi</hi> lawfull, are yet in <hi>Hypotheſi,</hi> becauſe of their inexpediency ſinfull. To eat fleſh is in it ſelf lawfull, but to eat fleſh offer'd unto Idols when another acquaints thee with it, is inexpedient, and therefore ſinfull. There are many things that are lawfull, which becauſe they edifie not, but offend, and grieve ſuch for whom Chriſt dyed are inexpedient, yea as ſo circumſtantiated, are unlawfull, and cannot without ſins be complyed with.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epiſtles to the <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> doth ſomewhat amply treat of this point, where he ſayes, that though all things are lawfull, yet all things are not expedient, that is, as the Apoſtle himſelf explains it, all things edifie not; All things, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> all indifferent things are lawfull, but not at all times, in every circumſtance for God's glory, and therefore not expedient. In the exerciſe of our liberty about things indifferent, if we will follow the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> we muſt take heed that we do nothing that affords grief, or proves a ſtumbling block to thoſe for whom Chriſt dyed, but muſt endeavour that all things be to the Glory of God, and the edification of Souls. This is evident from <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>If then the <hi>Ordinary Lord's dayes Service</hi> be in it ſelf law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and indifferent, yet if it's uſe be a grief and a ſtumbling block to thoſe for whom Chriſt dyed, no way conducive
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56725:7"/>
to God's glory, nor the peoples edification, its uſe is ſo very inexpedient as to become unlawfull, yea ſinfull, unto ſuch as know ſo much, the which inexpediency remains, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding any Humane Law to the contrary. For when the caſe is as here ſtated, the word of God ſhews it to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expedient, and therefore cannot be altered by any law of man.</p>
            <p>That the Lord's dayes Service, though in it ſelf lawfull, is in its uſe inexpedient. Some may argue thus, namely, It becomes all good Chriſtians to mind the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> of thoſe Churches, where they live, and unto this we ought to have a ſpecial regard in the exerciſe of our liberty about things indifferent. There is a manifeſt diviſion among Proteſtants in this Kingdom, the which hath prov'd very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious unto the Proteſtant Religion, and if encreaſed, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be much more miſchievous, and therefore all men muſt take heed, that in the uſe of their liberty they do not what neceſſarily tends to the multiplying diviſions. If we cannot Unite the Conformiſt and Non-conformiſt, we muſt do all, that <hi>lawfully</hi> we can, to fix an Union between Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt and Conformiſt, yea, and between Non-conformiſt and Non-conformiſt; This every judicious and ſober Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian will I preſume grant, from which conceſſion, 'tis thus argued, even from the ſuppoſition of the lawfulneſs of the Lord's day, Service againſt the expediency of its uſe <hi>pro hic, &amp; nunc.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If a Non conformiſt's uſing this ſervice dothnot contribute any thing towards an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with the Conformiſt, but tends to the <hi>dividing</hi> the Non-conformiſt, though the ſervice be in it ſelf lawfull, yet its uſe is not expedient.</p>
            <p>But a Non-conformiſts uſing this Service doth not contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute any thing towards an Union with the Conformiſt, [As Mr. <hi>Read's</hi> experience does evince, for ſayes he in his caſe, <hi>Though we yield as far as we can in things lawfull, there is no <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, no Peace nor Agreement to be had with ſuch men,]</hi> but tends to the dividing of the Non-conformiſts, as is moſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56725:8"/>
manifeſt to any that will but deliberately conſider the general practice of the Diſſenting Brethren. Therefore the uſe of the Lord's dayes Service <hi>pro hic</hi> &amp; <hi>nunc</hi> highly inexpedient, and not to be done.</p>
            <p>The multiplying diviſions among good Proteſtants cannot be for God's glory, nor for the edification of the people, but has been, and ſtill is a ſtumbling block unto ſome, and great grief unto others for whom Chriſt dyed, and therefore a man ſhould rather ſuffer, than uſe it. 'Tis quaeryed by ſome, whether or no the generality of Non-conformiſts do eſteem the uſe of the ordinary Lord's dayes Service expedient? In anſwer unto which, I may ſafely aſſert, <hi>that the generality of the Non-Conformiſts do at leaſt conſider the Conforming unto the Lord's dayes Service ſo very inexpedient, that they cannot Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiouſly comply with it;</hi> This is manifeſt from their avow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Practiſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Their Principle is, that in matters of Religion, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is in it ſelf lawfull and <hi>pro hic,</hi> &amp; <hi>nunc</hi> expedient, is their Duty; The expediency of a lawfull thing makes it Duty. It has therefore been the Conſcientious endeavour of Non-conformiſts to find out the expediency of thoſe things which are lawfull, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> whether the uſe thereof is for God's glory, and the edification of the people, and they judge themſelves bound in Conſcience to do whatever lawfully they may, to the end God may be glorified, and the edification of immortal ſouls advanced.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Practice</hi> of the Non-conformiſts hath been by this Rule, as they dare not do what is to God's diſhonour, ſo they are afraid to omit what will be for God's glory, and for edification. Their being turn'd out of their places to the impoveriſhing the families of ſome, the great prejudice of all, does evince they cannot venture on the doing what is to God's diſhonour. Their greivous ſufferings on the account of their publique meetings do as manifeſtly demonſtrate, that they are afraid to omit what is for God's glory, and the edification of the people.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:56725:8"/>
To thefe conſiderations add, that if theſe Conſcientious Non-conformiſts had been convinced, that the uſe of the ordinary Lord's dayes Service had been both lawfull and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, that is, had been for Gods glory, and the people's good, would they have lived ſo many a year in the neglect and omiſſion of ſo excellent a duty? What, do they make conſcience of one duty, but no conſcience of another? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I cannot believe it.</p>
            <p>For this reaſon I think my ſelf oblig'd to conclude, that the true reaſon why the generality of the Non-conforming Miniſters, who do not uſe this Service, is becauſe they think it <hi>inexpedient,</hi> they believe it is not for Gods glory, nor for edification, they fear that ſhould they uſe it, they ſhould diſhonour God, and be a ſcandal and grief to many for whom Chriſt dyed. But,</p>
            <p n="2">II. There are others, who conſider the particular forms of worſhip, appointed in the Liturgy for the ordinary Lords dayes ſervice, to be unlawfull, of this opinion are ſome <hi>Preſbyterians,</hi> the <hi>Congregational generally,</hi> and the <hi>Anabaptiſt.</hi> Here I'll give the ſenſe of the moderater ſort of thoſe, who look on the preſent Liturgy, as what cannot by them be uſed without ſin; The which I'll do without an engaging my ſelf ſo far in their defence, as to eſpouſe their quarrel.</p>
            <p>As for my part, I think moderation becomes all Chriſtians, eſpecially Engliſh Proteſtants, in a day wherein they are in danger of being deſtroyed by the common enemy, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. This is not a time to fall out with one another, and quarrel about leſſer things, for now the great and weighty matters of our Religion are in hazard, there muſt be an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Chriſtian charity towards each other. Let every man give that liberty to the conſcience of another, which he expects ſhould be given his own, for while the World en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures, there will be as different apprehenſions about leſſer matters, as there are different complections among men, and therefore there muſt be mutual forbearance, or there will be no peace among us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:56725:9"/>
Methinks it lookes ill, when men aſſume to themſelves an unaccountable infallibility, the which is attended with a proportionable ſeverity, in impoſing their own ſentiments on others. This is not only common among the Papiſts, but alſo to be obſerved too much among all ſorts of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, whether Epiſcopal, Presbyterian, Independent or Anabaptiſt, and is, I verily believe, one great reaſon of thoſe violent Diſſentions that are among us, every one thinks, that ſuch as diſſent from them, do ſo without any ſolid rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and therefore not to be tolerated. Thus ſome of the Conforming Clergy eſteem the Non-conformiſts diſſent from them, to be both unreaſonable and intolerable, and ſome Diſſenters, it may be, are even with the Epiſcopal in thoſe cenſures they paſs on them, and among the Non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, ſome, who only deſire that the ſubſcriptions and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurings of Covenants be remov'd, are willing enough that the Liturgy be eſtabliſhed with but a few amendments, the which may be done by a <hi>Comprehenſive Bill,</hi> that hath nothing of <hi>Indulgence</hi> in it.</p>
            <p>But really how weak ſoever the greateſt part of the Non-conformiſts are, 'tis too manifeſt, that they think that there are other <hi>Blocks</hi> which lye in their way to Conformity, than <hi>ſubſcriptions</hi> and <hi>abjurings,</hi> whoſe Conſciences ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, and who ſtand as much in need of an <hi>Indulgence,</hi> as others do of a <hi>Comprehenſion.</hi> If the Bill of comprehenſion ſhould be comprehenſive enough to take me in, I think my ſelf oblig'd to do my utmoſt that ſuch Conſcientious perſons, who through weakneſs cannot do as much as my ſelf, be at leaſt indulg'd.</p>
            <p>Conſcience is a tender thing, and is really the immediate directer of our actions, againſt the plain convictions of which we muſt not go. No Authority is ſufficient to oblige any man to act againſt the plain convictions of conſcience; For which reaſon, ſeeing the Diſſenters are fully convinc'd in Conſcience, that they cannot lawfully conform to the preſent Terms of Lay-Communion, there muſt be either ſome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56725:9"/>
of the Termes, or ſome muſt ſuffer for Conſcience ſake, whence then to ſhew the neceſſity of altering ſome things, even for a comprehenſion, and the indulging in other things for the eaſe of tender Conſciences. I'll give the Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er an <hi>Hiſtorical Account</hi> of ſome of their reaſonings againſt the <hi>Termes</hi> of <hi>Lay-Communion,</hi> the which I will produce on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to this end, namely to ſhew, that the reaſons are ſuch as may lay convictions on the Conſciences of good and honeſt; if not learned men. Though men of great learning may be able to anſwer them, yet if they be ſuch as are unanſwerable in the judgmenr of the Diſſenters, 'tis ſufficient for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for which I produce them. Thoſe arguments may be ſtrong in the <hi>judgment</hi> of ſome, which are not ſo in the <hi>opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> of others. My province then is only to propoſe, not to defend the arguments that are cogent in moving ſome Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to conclude, that as <hi>Lay-men,</hi> they cannot conform un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the impoſed Termes of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For to the compleat Communion of Lay-men, there is required a conformity, not only to the <hi>ordinary Lord's dayes Service,</hi> but moreover unto their <hi>Modes of Adminiſtring the Sacraments.</hi> But that unto this they cannot conform, I will eſſay particularly to evince, by ſhewing more generally, why they can't conform to the Terms impos'd on the people, and then more particularly why they can't ſubmit unto the <hi>Rubrick</hi> about baptizing their children, nor Communicate with them in the Lord's Supper, and in fine give ſeveral rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, why others can't with a ſafe Conſcience attend on the Reading of the ordinary Lord's dayes Service.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Why ſome cannot Conſcientiouſly comply with the Termes of Communion, impoſed by the Church on the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>More generally;</hi> Becauſe there are ſo many things which the Church of <hi>England</hi> acknowledges to be in their own nature indifferent, that are made ſo neceſſary apart of Religion, as to be Termes of Communion with them. They take the Word of God contained in the writings of the Old
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56725:10"/>
and New Teſtament to be the only Rule of the whole, and of every part of their Religion, whence what is enjoyned them, as ſo neceſſary a part of Religion, as to be made a Term of Communion, they cannot conform thereunto, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be agreeable to the Word of God. A <hi>Term</hi> of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Communion is a very neceſſary part of Chriſt's Religion,</hi> the non-embracing which deprives a perſon of the benefit and advantage of the Sacraments, and therefore they muſt be no other, than what our Lord Chriſt has in his Word made ſo. If any man, or ſociety of men aſſume unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a power concerning matters of Religion, which Chriſt never gave them, they think they cannot be faithfull unto Chriſt, if they ſubject themſelves unto them in their exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of ſuch an irregularly aſſumed power. Chriſt Jeſus is the Sole Lord of his Church, and Law-giver in it, and therefore the alone Author of the whole of Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for which reaſon, they cannot receive any ſuch additions as are made meerly by men, as parts, much leſs as <hi>neceſſary</hi> parts of Chriſtian Religion, they know that there are ſome who ſay, the <hi>Impoſition may be ſinfull, when a compliance therewith is a duty;</hi> But this in matters of Religion, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the preſent caſe they do not underſtand, becauſe when lawfull Authority commands any thing <hi>ſinfully,</hi> the great reaſon why 'tis ſinfull is, becauſe 'tis in other manner than according to the Word of God, but if the command be not according to God's Word, how can their obedience be ſo? All obedience is to a command, and ſuch is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion between the command and the obedience, that we muſt conſider the obedience to be as is the command; If the command be out of the Lord, and ſinfull, the obedience thereunto cannot be in the Lord, and a duty. If the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand be not <hi>for the Lord,</hi> but againſt him, the obedience cannot be for the Lord. But that our obedience muſt be <hi>in,</hi> and <hi>for the Lord,</hi> is acknowledged by the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there are many things in their own nature, according
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56725:10"/>
to the confeſſion of the Church oſ <hi>England indifferent,</hi> which yet are made ſo neceſſary a part of Chriſtian Religion as to be enjoyned as <hi>Termes</hi> of Chriſtian Communion. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever conſcientiouſly refuſes to be preſent at their publique Prayers, or to kneel at the Sacrament, is, by the <hi>27th. Canon,</hi> deprived of the Sacrament, yea, and though the Miniſter, who ſhall <hi>wittingly</hi> adminiſter the ſame to notorious offenders, and perjur'd villains incurres not for ſuch a default, the <hi>pain of Suſpenſion;</hi> Yet no Miniſter when he celebrateth the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, ſhall <hi>wittingly Adminiſter</hi> the ſame to any but to ſuch as <hi>kneel,</hi> under pain of <hi>Suſpenſion,</hi> nor under the like pain to any that refuſe <hi>to be preſent at Publique Prayers, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Orders of the Church of</hi> England. Thus not only a form oſ Prayer, but <hi>this particular</hi> form of Prayer, in which form there are many things, with which theſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters cannot comply, are made ſo neceſſary a part of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that if they conform not unto them, they are denyed the Lord's Supper, and what Miniſter ſoever admits ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the communion is lyable unto a ſuſpenſion, a greater pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment than is threatned againſt thoſe Miniſters, who ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſuch as commit the horrible ſin of perjury. Moreover though they are convinc'd in conſcience they ſin if they kneel, yet they cannot be admitted unto the Lord's Supper unleſs they kneel,</p>
            <p>Let us put the beſt ſenſe on theſe things, and 'tis this; As the notorious offender and perjur'd villain cannot be admitted to the Sacrament, becauſe he complyes not with <hi>God's Terms,</hi> the Holyeſt man on earth cannot be admitted, unleſs he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies with <hi>Man's Termes.</hi> But what is this leſs than ſetting up mans poſts with Gods, or a ſetting as high (if not a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er) value on the precepts of men, as on the commands of God? But ſeeing our Lord Chriſt has purchaſed a liberty for them, whereby they may be admitted to the Sacrament on eaſier Termes than Man will permit, they muſt abide by this liberty in doing which they do, but diſcharge their duty in aſſerting the Lord Jeſus Chriſt to be the <hi>Sole Author</hi> of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56725:11"/>
the whole of Chriſtian Religion, and of all the Termes of Chriſtian Communion. But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. To be more particular in ſhewing why they cannot joyn with the Church in the <hi>Sacraments;</hi> In doing which I'll contract my ſelf in giving you no other than what I find in the <hi>Altar of Damaſcus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Of <hi>Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I'll only offer a very little that is inſiſted on in my Author, and therefore will paſs by that paſſage in the Second Prayer before Baptiſm, [where the <hi>Remiſſion of ſins is defired by Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Regeneration;</hi> As if the pardon of ſin conſiſted rather in the Sanctification of the ſoul, than the diſſolving the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to puniſhment:] and conſider the <hi>Interrogatories</hi> which are theſe, <q>
                  <hi>Doſt thou forſake the Devil, and all his works.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Dost thou believe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Wilt thou be Baptized in this Faith?</hi> The Child hath not Underſtanding, nor Faith, nor deſire of Baptiſm; And how be it the child had Faith, can the God-father tell abſolutely, and in particular, that <hi>this</hi> Child whom he preſenteth, doth Believe, deſire Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, or forſake the Devil? It is a fooliſh thing, and great mockery of God's ſervice, to demand that of Infants, which was at the firſt demanded of ſuch as were come to years of diſcretion, and were converted from <hi>Gentiliſm.</hi> The children of Faithfull Parents are within the Covenant of Grace, whereupon it is that they are made partakers of the Seal of the Covenant; The Covenant being made with the Parents in their Faith, and not the Faith of the child, the Parents ſhould give confeſſion of their own Faith, and not of the Faith of the child, which is not: becauſe their own Faith is the condition of the Covenant upon their part, whereupon God promiſeth to be their God, and the God of their Seed. Whereupon alſo it followeth, that the <hi>Father</hi> of the child ſhould preſent the child, and give confeſſion, and <hi>not another,</hi> becauſe the Covenant is made with him, and his Seed, and the child is his Seed, not the Seed of another, whom we call <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father;</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:56725:11"/>
The <hi>Natural Father</hi> is the proper God-father. Others may be <hi>Witneſſes</hi> of Baptiſm, but that the Father ſhould, or can reſign this duty to another, I deny.—After that the child is dipped, [or ſprinkled] and <hi>Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, the Priest maketh a Croſs upon the child's Forehead;</hi> Saying, <hi>We receive this child into the Congregation of Chriſt's Flock, and do ſign with the ſign of the Croſs, in token that hereafter he ſhall not be aſhamed to confeſs the faith of Chriſt Crucified, and Manfully to fight under his Banner againſt Sin, the World,</hi> and <hi>the Devil,</hi> and <hi>to continue Chriſt's Faithfull Souldier and Servant unto his Lifes end.</hi> He ſaith not we <hi>have received,</hi> but we <hi>do receive,</hi> as if the child were not received by <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> but by <hi>Groſſing,</hi> or as if the child were again received by Croſſing, which was before receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Baptiſm. This ſigning with the croſs is no decent geſture, it is rather like a jugglers geſture, than a geſture of decency and comelineſs; It muſt then be uſed as a <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical</hi> and <hi>Significant</hi> Rite. But we have no ſuch ſign ſet down in the Word of God, as to make two Croſs Lines in the Air with our fingers, to repreſent the croſs of a Tree, or to ſignifie unto us, that we ſhould not be aſhamed of the Croſs of Chriſt. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thou <hi>ſhalt make unto thy ſelf no Image,</hi> that is any <hi>Repreſentation forged in thy own brain to be ſet up in the Worſhip of God.</hi> Admit once the Aerial Croſs in Baptiſm, ye cannot refuſe to ſet up the <hi>material Croſs,</hi> and the <hi>Rood in the Kirck,</hi> nor the <hi>Wooden</hi> or <hi>Stone Croſſes</hi> in the High-way; For all may ſignifie the ſame thing, that the Croſs on the forehead; And by this reaſon every one may wear a Silver Croſs upon his forehead alſo. Further, not only other ſignificant croſſes material may be brought in upon this ground, but alſo the reſt of the beggarly ceremonies of Baptiſm, to deface, and deform the purity, plainneſs and ſimplicity of Chriſt's inſtitution. As to put ſalt into the mouth of the child, to anoint with Oyl the breaſt and ſhoulders, and the top of the head with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56725:12"/>
Holy Criſm, and to put a burning Taper into his hands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for theſe Toyes had their own glorious ſignification, as well as the Croſs. Laſtly, What doth it ſignifie, but that which is already ſignified in baptiſm. The ſame va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and courage, and conſtant profeſſion, and fighting un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Chriſt's banner, is a part of that Grace which is ſealed by baptiſm. But beſides that it is a <hi>ſignificant</hi> toy, it is alſo eſteemed <hi>effective,</hi> for they ſay, that the infant by it is dedicated to the ſervice of him that dyed on the croſs. Who did ſanctifie this ſign for ſuch an uſe? Are men able to do it? It was made alſo a conſecrator of Water, Bread and Wine, and all other Holy things in time of Popery, for the which corruption we ought to abhorr it. Again we <hi>Sign this child in token, that he ſhall continue Chriſt's faithfull Souldier to his Lives end;</hi> Theſe words [ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to his lives end,] compared with the like in the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> of the 22 <hi>Sunday</hi> after Trinity [God ſhall continue the work in you to the end] ſhew unto us, that we uſe the croſs for a <hi>pledge to give aſſurance to the child</hi> to continue in grace to the end, which if it be ſo, then it ſerveth to work faith, and is uſed <hi>effectually,</hi> ſaith <hi>Parker. Hooker</hi> ſaith, that there cannot be a more <hi>forceable means to avoid that which may deſervedly procure ſhame.</hi> If it be in ſome ſort a <hi>means</hi> to ſecure from confuſion Everlaſting, then it is in ſome ſort <hi>effective of Grace.</hi> In a word, ſuppoſe there were no ſinfull uſe of it for the preſent, the horrible abuſe of it in times by-paſt, and the danger and peril of theſe ſame abuſes are ſufficient to remove it out of this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sacrament, where it is ſet up in ſuch honourable State, beſide the Lord's own Altar.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Of <hi>the Lord's Supper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I'll not mention all is ſaid of this, I'll only apply my ſelf to what is ſaid of <hi>Kneeling,</hi> which geſture, though not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Chriſts example, nor the nature of the Ordinance, is impoſed as a <hi>neceſſary</hi> condition of our <hi>Right in</hi> the Lord's Supper; whatever right Faith and Repentance may give <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:56725:12"/>
this Ordinance, no <hi>jus in re,</hi> no right in it is acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to any among us, but ſuch as <hi>Kneel,</hi> whereby Kneeling is made by the Church of <hi>England</hi> a <hi>neceſſary</hi> Term, and yet look'd on but as indifferent, as if a man had been inveſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a power of making a thing in it ſelf indifferent, to become a neceſſary part of Chriſts Religion; But to give you what I find in the <hi>Altar of Damaſcus;</hi> Where 'tis ſaid. <q>That without any farther, he and they <hi>[viz.</hi> Miniſter and People] Communicate <hi>Kneeling</hi> after the Popiſh manner, that is, with a <hi>geſture of Adoration,</hi> when they are behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſigns, taking, eating, drinking, and inwardly in their minds ſhould be meditating on the ſignification, and the fruit, and benefit which they reap by Chriſt Crucified, and conſequently cannot without diſtraction of mind from this employment of the Soul, and Meditation, pray a ſet, and continued prayer to God, or cannot meditate and be employed in the preſent action without diſtraction of mind from the prayer, and therefore either they pray <hi>irreverent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> which they will not grant, or do Communicate this <hi>Geſture of Adoration</hi> to <hi>the other imployments of the Soul,</hi> and of the outward ſenſes and members of the body, about the objects preſented, which they muſt grant, and ſo <hi>nill</hi> they, <hi>will</hi> they, they muſt be forced to confeſs, that they commit idolatry. <hi>Kneeling is no decent geſture for a Table,</hi> for commodity, they ſay, maketh decency, but this geſture is confeſſed not to be commodious, as ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting is; It is then enjoyned for another reaſon. to wit for <hi>Reverence,</hi> but to kneel for Reverence and Religious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects is ever Adoration in the higheſt degree. To kneel for reverence, that is, to adore, is not enjoyned here for prayer, neither may prayer lawfully be enjoyned in time of another action, and part of God's worſhip to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the ſame perſon. And ſuppoſe it were enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the ſhort prayer uttered by their prieſt, yet are not the outward ſenſes, and inward faculties employed princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally on that prayer, but upon another action, principally
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56725:13"/>
and directly intended in the inſtitution, whereas the other is only ſuper-added by man. Let them frame their <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons</hi> and <hi>Acts</hi> as they pleaſe, and ſuppoſe, that they kneel for reverence of the Sacrament, common ſenſe may teach us, that it is done for that reſpect, either totally or prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally; but let it be in the leaſt part, yet that leaſt part is idolatry. Beſide the idolatry of this geſture, it cannot ſtand with the right manner of celebration, and rites of the inſtitution. For when they kneel for adoration they cannot carry the cup from hand to hand, nor divide the elements among themſelves, as Chriſt hath commanded. In many places the people are raiſed from their kneeling to come about the Table there to receive kneeling, and then are directed to their places again, ſaith the <hi>Author of the Survey.</hi> The prieſt giveth the Bread and the Wine, to every one ſeverally, out of his own hands. When the cup is to be carryed from one to another, the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant is too prophane (in their opinion) to reach it, the Prieſts Holy hand muſt take it from one, and give it to the other: but Chriſt willed his Diſciples to <hi>divide it among themſelves,</hi> and it was carryed from hand to hand indeed, after the manner of the laſt paſchal cup. When Chriſt therefore gave the Bread and the Wine, he ſaid in the plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral number, <hi>take ye, eat ye,</hi> &amp;c. The Engliſh prieſt ſpeaketh in the ſingular number, when he giveth the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, he annexeth not Chriſts words containing a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable promiſe, and uttered in an <hi>Enunciative</hi> form, but other words invented by man, and in form of a prayer, converting one part of God's worſhip into another, or elſe confounding them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>By this 'tis manifeſt that many Miniſters may conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oufly refuſe to conform to the Termes impoſed on the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. They can no more ſatisfie their conſciences in comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Termes of <hi>Lay-Communion,</hi> than others can with thoſe of the Miniſters Conformity.</p>
            <p>Moreover.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:56725:13"/>
II. As they cannot hold Communion with the Church in the <hi>Holy Sacraments,</hi> and conſequently not comply with what is required of the people in order thereunto, ſo neither can they with a ſafe Conſcience joyn in the <hi>ordinary Lord's dayes Service.</hi> They cannot conſcientiouſly <hi>approve</hi> of many things in that ſervice, unto which they muſt give their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation if they conform thereunto.</p>
            <p>Whoever conforms doth thereby ſhew his approbation of what he conforms unto. To what a man conforms, to that he manifeſts his good liking, why is it that ſome can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conform unto the By-Offices, but becauſe they do not approve of them, and why do any conform to the <hi>ordinary Lord's dayes Service,</hi> but becauſe they approve of it, which is as much as if it had been ſaid, Conformity is an Overt Act of Approbation, 'tis in practice an Approving the thing.</p>
            <p>But ſome ſcrupulous Diſſenters cannot conform unto the <hi>ordinary Lord's dayes Service</hi> without conforming to ſeveral things to which they refuſe the giving their approbation. <hi>By</hi> the <hi>ordinary Lord's dayes Service</hi> they underſtand, all that Office that is according to the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> and <hi>Canon of the Church, appoynted to be</hi> read <hi>Ordinarily on the Lord's day,</hi> or to ſpeak in the Common Prayer Dialect, that Service that is appointed to be read ordinarily on Sundayes, againſt the uſe of which they do more generally argue thus.</p>
            <p n="1">I. If they muſt conform to the ordinary Lord's dayes Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, it muſt be to all according to the Rubrick and Canon, or only to ſome part. But,</p>
            <p>If the <hi>latter</hi> it will not ſatisfie the Church, for by refuſing to be preſent at any part thereof, they are to be denyed the Lord's Supper, and if when call'd to ſhew their reaſon of ſuch their refuſal, they ſpeak any thing againſt either the Service it ſelf, or any Ceremonies, or Rites in uſe, they are by an <hi>Ipſo facto Excommunication</hi> Excommunicated accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>4th.</hi> and <hi>6th. Canons,</hi> whereby to ſome it ſeems apparent, that unleſs their Conformity be full and compleat
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56725:14"/>
they are as lyable to the diſpleaſure and cenſure of the Church, as if they had not at all conform'd. The Miniſter muſt read all required, and the people muſt joyn with him in it, or be expoſ'd to the ſevere laſh of Eccleſiaſtical Fulmina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but this many a Diſſenter cannot do, neither doth eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Conformable Miniſter in this reſpect actually conform to the Canon.</p>
            <p>'Tis true every Miniſter according to the import of the ſecond <hi>Article,</hi> unto which he that ſubſcribes is oblig'd to uſe the form in the ſaid book preſcribed in Prayer, and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Sacraments, and <hi>no other;</hi> The which was expreſly enjoyn'd all Miniſters, <hi>primo Eliz.</hi> Where 'tis ſaid, <hi>That all and ſingular Miniſters—in any Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Church,</hi> or <hi>other place within the Realm of England—ſhall be bounden to ſay and uſe—all their Common and Open Prayer in ſuch order and form as is mentioned in the ſaid Book,</hi> and <hi>none other,</hi> or otherwiſe, that is, ſayes Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> neither before nor after Sermon, no other prayer, unleſs the bidding of prayer with the alone uſe of the <hi>Lord's Prayer,</hi> is allowed by the <hi>Canon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That this is the ſenſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> how contrary ſoever the practice of her Sons generally is, will appear with conviction to ſuch as ſoberly conſider, that the weightyeſt arguments which are produc'd to prove the uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of a publique Liturgy, are fetch'd from ſuch <hi>Topicks,</hi> as neceſſarily inferr the unlawfulneſs of a publique praying <hi>ex tempore,</hi> or by a form of a private Miniſters Compoſing. One great Argument is given us by Mr. <hi>Hutton,</hi> in the words of the Counſell of <hi>Melevis,</hi> which is, <q>that a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Liturgy approv'd of either by a Council or Synod, muſt be uſed leaſt any thing peradventure be otherwiſe fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med contrary unto Faith, either by ignorance, or for want of ſtudy, or due meditation, or as others add, leaſt thoſe Miniſters who pray <hi>ex tempore,</hi> or uſe a ſet form of their own compoſing, ſhould be <hi>Immethodical</hi> in their Prayers, uſing <hi>Tautologies,</hi> or having in 'em <hi>Nonſenſe,</hi> and ſeveral un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comely
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56725:14"/>
ſlips;</q> beſide 'tis added, that we muſt uſe a publique Liturgy, that the prayers of the ſeveral Congregations within this Realm, may be ſent up unto God in the ſame words, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All which is againſt the uſe of all <hi>free Prayer,</hi> or Prayers Compos'd by the Miniſter himſelf, for which reaſon many are of an opinion, that the Liturgy was deſign'd to be inſtead of all other prayer, the which ſeems to be the meaning of the <hi>14th. Canon,</hi> where 'tis expreſt, that <hi>there muſt be an uſing the Liturgy without either diminiſhing in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of Preaching, or any other reſpect, or adding any thing either in the</hi> matter, or form <hi>thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that many among the Diſſenters cannot ſatisfie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in abiding by a form of prayer, thus erected to the publique diſuſe of the gift of prayer is very certain, ſee Dr. <hi>Collins</hi> on this Subject. Though there are ſome circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces wherein a form of prayer is lawfull, namely, when the perſon whoſe duty 'tis to pray in publique has not a gift, in that caſe to uſe a form is much better than not to pray at all, which is enough to ſhew that the uſing a form of prayer is not in it ſelf unlawfull, ſeeing if it had been ſo, it could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be a duty; However to ſet up a form in oppoſition to the publique uſe, if ſpiritual or free prayer is in the opinion of ſome, not only a practice unknown to the Church for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral hundred years, but moreover contrary to the preſent diſpenſation of the Spirit.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They aſſert that the impoſing a publique Liturgy thus, is a practice that was unknown to the Church for ſeveral hundred years. The Reverend and Judicious Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in his <hi>Search for the Engliſh Schiſmatick,</hi> aſſerts; <q>That no One Liturgy was impoſed on any National Church, or any Patriarchal for many hundred years after the Apoſtles dayes (yea and after <hi>Conſtantine,)</hi> but every Biſhop or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor was the chooſer of his words and practice, and as others, a publique Liturgy was not Univerſally impos'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till Antichriſt did ariſe, by the power of whoſe might <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gories Liturgy</hi> in contempt of that of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> was impos'd
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56725:15"/>
on the Churches, which Liturgy was not received from the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> nor in many years after, but ſome part had its riſe from Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the Firſt, another from <hi>Celeſtin, &amp;c.</hi>
               </q> as <hi>Platina</hi> in the lives of <hi>Sixtus, Celeſtin,</hi> and <hi>Gregory</hi> does aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert. Furthermore <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelf does acknowledge, that the Biſhops of particular Churches ever had allowed 'em a power of making Offices for their own Churches, which point of <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is confirmed by uncontroulable evidences in this our own Country, where untill the time of the Reformation, there was great diverſity in ſaying and ſinging in Churches, ſome following <hi>Salisbury</hi> uſe, and ſome <hi>Hereford,</hi> ſome the <hi>uſe of Bangor,</hi> and ſome that of <hi>York,</hi> and others the uſe of <hi>Lincoln;</hi> All which were ſuppreſſed by <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th. in order to the carrying on a farther Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, in the Room of which Offices, one only was ſet up as what did moſt effectually anſwer the great deſign of our worthy Reformers, which was the promoting a thorough Reformation with as much ſpeed as the badneſs of thoſe times would bear it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As 'tis thus evident that there was no publique form of prayer impos'd on any particular Church the firſt 300 years, nor Univerſally till Antichriſts appearing in the World, and that even then particular Churches enjoy'd the liberty of forming Offices for their own particular Churches, in like manner the erecting any one publique form, in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the publique uſe of the <hi>Gift of Prayer</hi> is ſo contrary to the Goſpel diſpenſation, which is the diſpenſation of the Spirit, that the Divines of the Church of <hi>England</hi> cannot but by their practice diſcover their diſlike of ſuch impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. They do not therefore adhere ſo firmly unto theſe forms, but that before Sermon, they uſe ſome of their own Compoſing, which is a ſufficient demonſtration, that pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>extempore,</hi> or the publique uſe of a prayer Compos'd by a Miniſter in private, is neither unlawfull nor inexpedient, and that the Arguments produc'd from the abſurdities of ſuch a practice, to prove the uſefulneſs of a publique Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56725:15"/>
are not cogent enough to command their aſſent, the which cannot but countenance and juſtifie the Diſſent of the Non-Conformiſts, as they refuſe to conform unto the Liturgy as 'tis enjoyn'd, as the only form of prayer to be us'd in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique.</p>
            <p n="2">II. But to be more particular, there are many among the Diſſenters who are furniſh'd with ſuch Arguments, as the <hi>Reader</hi> may find in the <hi>Abridgment of that book,</hi> which the Miniſters of <hi>Lincoln</hi> Dioceſs deliver'd to the King, <hi>Anno</hi> 1605. as alſo in a <hi>part of</hi> the <hi>Regiſter,</hi> and among the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for <hi>Refuſal of Subſcription,</hi> exhibited to <hi>Cotton Biſhop of Exeter</hi> by the <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> and <hi>Corniſh Miniſtry,</hi> and in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other diſcourſes, as in <hi>Bayly's Parallel of the Liturgy,</hi> with the <hi>Maſs-book, Ames</hi> his <hi>freſh ſuit againſt Ceremonies, &amp;c.</hi> The which have fix'd ſuch ſtrong convictions on the Conſciences of ſome Diſſenters concerning the unlawfulneſs of the preſent Liturgy, that they cannot ſafely joyn with any in the uſe of it. Though ſome, who have not receiv'd ſuch powerfull impreſſions from the weight of thoſe Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, can read the Common Prayer, and joyn with ſuch as do, to the end they may ſave themſelves from the ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Penal Lawes, yet other Diſſenters will rather ſubmit themſelves to the greateſt extremities, than venture to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour God by doing what they are convinc'd is a ſin.</p>
            <p>That the Reader may be mov'd to entertain ſome charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thoughts concerning ſuch perſons, and that the common objection that is laid in againſt their Non-Conformity, which is <hi>Humour</hi> and <hi>Fancy,</hi> and a <hi>Peeviſh Obſtinacy,</hi> may be fully anſwered. I'll give an Hiſtorical Account of ſome of thoſe Arguments which do ſo fully convince ſome Diſſenters, that they cannot without laying an unnatural violence on their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, conform.</p>
            <div n="1" type="argument">
               <head>
                  <hi>Argument</hi> I.</head>
               <p n="1">I. They are perſwaded that according to the Rubrick,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56725:16"/>
the ſame honour is put on the <hi>Apocryphal Books,</hi> which is due alone to the <hi>Sacred Scriptures.</hi> For they are appointed to be read as a part of the Old Teſtament, without any note of difference from the Canonical.</p>
               <p>In a diſcourſe before the Common Prayer concerning the Service of the Church, 'tis aſſerted that <hi>nothing is ordained to be read, but the very Pure word of God, the Holy Scriptures, or that</hi> which is agreable to the ſame, beſide this after the order, how the <hi>Pſalter</hi> is to be read, 'tis ſaid in the Title, <hi>how the reſt of Holy Scripture</hi> is to be read, under which Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſeveral orders are to be found. Namely, 1. The Old Teſtament is appointed for the firſt Leſſons at Morning and Evening Prayer, ſo as the moſt part thereof will be read every year once, and in the 3d. order 'tis ſaid that to know what Leſſons ſhall be read every day, look for the day of the Month in the <hi>Kalendar</hi> following, and there ye ſhall find the Chapters that ſhall be read for the Leſſons both at Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Evening Prayer, and in the <hi>Rubrick</hi> after the Pſalms are read 'tis order'd, that then ſhall be read diſtinctly with an audible voice, the <hi>Firſt Leſſon</hi> taken out of <hi>the Old Teſtament,</hi> as it is appointed in the <hi>Kalendar,</hi> whereby 'tis evident that what is appointed in the <hi>Kalendar</hi> to be read, for the Firſt Leſſon, is conſider'd as a part of the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, the pure word of God; But the <hi>Apocryphal books</hi> are in the <hi>Kalendar</hi> appointed to be read for Firſt Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for almoſt Two Months together, even from the latter end of <hi>September</hi> untill <hi>November 24th,</hi> beſide the Holy dayes, on which theſe books are appointed to be read. To which add that this is done to the conſtant neglect of reading a great part of the Sacred Scriptures, namely the <hi>two books of Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles. Solomons Song,</hi> and a great <hi>part of the Revelations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That 'tis the appointment of the Church to read the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryphal books</hi> as a part of the Holy Scriptures, is farther con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd by Archbiſhop <hi>Bancroft,</hi> in the conference held at <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> where (as the <hi>abridgment</hi> has it,) he tax'd <hi>Jerom</hi> for calling theſe books <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> and ſaid he was the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56725:16"/>
firſt that gave them that name, and called his objections againſt them, the <hi>old Cavills of the Jews;</hi> And the Biſhops of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> affirm'd at the ſame time, that they muſt needs be held, <hi>Canonici ad informandos mores.</hi> Canonical for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of manners. To theſe I'll add, what Mr. <hi>Hutton</hi> in his anſwer unto the reaſons of the Miniſters of <hi>Devon</hi> and <hi>Cornwall</hi> to this very objection. <q>They, are ſaith he, called Holy Scriptures in a ſignification at large, becauſe the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject they entreat of, is God, his Love, Power, our San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification and Obedience to him. And they may be held <hi>Canonical,</hi> wholſom Doctrines being thence deduced, though not ſimply of themſelves, yet wherein they agree with the Canon, as alſo becauſe they may ſerve as they alwayes heretofore have done, for a <hi>rule to direct and order our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation aright.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>In this anſwer, though he ſeems without the approbation of the Rubrick, to make a difference between the Sacred Scriptures, and the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> books, yet at length falls in with the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> aſſerting, <hi>that they are a Canon</hi> or <hi>Rule to direct our Converſation aright.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in oppoſition hereunto, 'tis generally by ſound Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants aſſerted. 1. That the <hi>Apocryphal</hi> books are not a part of the Holy Scriptures, the pure word of God. 2. That there are ſeveral things appointed to be read, which are not agreable to the word of God, nor can be defended by any ſound Proteſtant.</p>
               <p>To make this point the more clear, I'll give the <hi>Reader</hi> an account of what is reply'd to the diſtinction of the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> about the <hi>Canon of Faith,</hi> and <hi>Manners,</hi> and then offer what arguments have been urg'd againſt this prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the Church.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond part of the <hi>defence of the reaſons of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonſhire</hi> and <hi>Corniſh Miniſters,</hi> 'tis thus reply'd to the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid diſtinction. <q>But that we may farther ſee how heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and unſound this diſtinction of <hi>Canonical for manners,</hi> but not for <hi>Faith</hi> is, let us obſerve how they here make a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56725:17"/>
diſtinction of faith and manners where none is, for all Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of God's word are (in this reſpect) Doctrines of faith, whether they concern matters of believing, or of other Converſation of life, wherefore the Apoſtle hath coupled them together in that place to <hi>Timothy,</hi> ſaying, all Scripture given by inſpiration of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhewing us thereby, that upon one, and the ſame divine Revelation, our knowledge and practice both muſt be grounded. And I would entreat theſe men that give us this diſtinction, to tell us whether it be not a point of faith, <hi>That we muſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip one God, and him after his own manner, reverencing his Name, and keeping his Sabbaths, &amp;c.</hi> And whether it be not a point of faith, <hi>That we muſt honour our Parents and Superiors, that we muſt not Kill, commit Adultery, Steal, Slander, Covet;</hi> And whether our Conſciences be not bound in theſe things by the <hi>Divine Teſtimony,</hi> as well as in any point of our underſtanding? ſurely (unleſs our Divinity faileth) <hi>all the word of God</hi> is the <hi>object of Faith,</hi> that as well which directeth to <hi>manners,</hi> as that which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealeth myſteries unto us. There is (I confeſs) a diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on between <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Manners,</hi> when we come to ſort and ſever the things contained in the Word, into the kinds of duties impoſed, but when we conſider them in the Rule and Principle of the word it ſelf, from which the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is certainly inform'd and bound, there is no difference, but they are all of faith alike: even as the ſame ſap, which in the branches diſtinct unto leaves and bloſſomes, was in the Root but one; whence it followes that nothing can be properly <hi>Canonical unto manners,</hi> but the ſame was firſt <hi>Canonical unto faith:</hi> for we therefore ſtand undoubtedly perſwaded that thus we ought to do, becauſe we firſt <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi> that God himſelf would have us to do ſo, and hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd it to us as his will.</q>
               </p>
               <p>By this it ſeems evident that the diſtinction between <hi>Canon of faith</hi> and of <hi>manners</hi> as us'd by the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> is idle and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent, and that therefore notwithſtanding all has been
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56725:17"/>
ſaid by Mr. <hi>Hutton,</hi> it remains as an undoubted truth, that the <hi>Service Book doth conſider the Apocripha as Canonical, as a part of the Holy Scriptures, the pure Word of God,</hi> which is no more than what may be inferred from their confounding the <hi>Apocriphal</hi> with the <q>
                     <hi>Canonical</hi> books, as may be ſeen in their great <hi>Bible</hi> Authorized to be read, where dividing the books of the Old Teſtament into <hi>Legal, Hiſtorical, Sapiential</hi> and <hi>Prophetical;</hi> In the <hi>Hiſtorical</hi> they place 19 <hi>books,</hi> amongſt which they reckon the <hi>third and fourth books of Eſdras,</hi> the <hi>books of Tobith</hi> and <hi>Judith,</hi> the <hi>two books of Maccabees,</hi> and the reſt of the Chapters of <hi>Eſther,</hi> making the book of <hi>Eſther</hi> to conſiſt of 16 Chapters, and then to be part of that book. In the <hi>Sapiential</hi> they place 5 books, whereof they reckon the <hi>books of Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> for two, calling the book of Wiſdom the <hi>Wiſdom of Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</hi> In the Prophetical they place 18 books, of which they reckon <hi>Baruch</hi> the Prophet, and <hi>Suſanna, Bell and the Dragon,</hi> making the ſame all one with <hi>Daniel,</hi> conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of 14 Chapters; What can be more clear than this, ſayes the Defender of the Reaſons? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Where to (ſayes the ſame Author) if we add the <hi>book of Homilies,</hi> how it divers times calleth theſe Apocriphal Books <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> in the ſame ſenſe wherein the Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament are ſo called, ſaying in the alledging <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bith</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſticus, the Holy Ghoſt ſpeaketh ſo in the Scriptures,</hi> thereby giving the ſame Authority and Title with <hi>Zechary, Luke</hi> 1. and the Author to the <hi>Hebrews Ch.</hi> 3. 7. give to the Holy Prophets, in their writing of places out of the Old Teſtament.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus 'tis evident; That according to the Service Book, and the Sentiments of ſome great Biſhops, the great Bible and Book of Homilies, the Apocripha is conſider'd as a part of the Holy Scriptures. The which truth abides in its ſtrength, notwithſtanding what is argued from the <hi>Book</hi> of <hi>Articles,</hi> where 'tis ſufficiently manifeſt, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cripha are no part of the Holy Scriptures, for this doth but
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56725:18"/>
diſcover the contradiction there is between the book of Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles and the Service book, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereby the Non-Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts are but ſupply'd with an unanſwerable argument againſt ſubſcription, which I'll give in the words of the <hi>Devonſhire</hi> Miniſters: <hi>viz. That to ſubſcribe to the Service Book is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to our Subſcription to the Book of Articles, the</hi> 6 <hi>Article whereof under the name of Holy Scriptures, underſtanding on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Canonical Books of the Old and New Teſtament, there mentioned, whereof the Apocrypha Books are none,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they conclude <hi>they cannot ſafely ſubſcribe, becauſe they ſhall ſubſcribe to two books, one contrary to another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This being ſo clear, namely, that the <hi>Apochripha</hi> Books, are appointed to be read as a part of the Holy Scriptures, and as the Canon and Rule of manners, I'll proceed to ſhew what has been objected againſt it; Not that I'll trouble the Reader with all, but onely with two or three particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Hereby their error, who account theſe Books Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Scripture is confirm'd; <q>This was (ſayes the <hi>Lincoln Abridgment)</hi> the only reaſon, that moved the third Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill of <hi>Carthage</hi> to decree, that they ſhould be held Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical, becauſe they had received from the Fathers, that they were to be read in the Church. And <hi>Bellarmine</hi> makes this one of his beſt reaſons to prove that the authority of theſe books is Divine and Canonical, becauſe they are now, and have been of old, read by the Church in the publique Aſſemblies; ſo do the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in that Book they have lately Publiſhed, called the <hi>Three Converſions of England;</hi> And <hi>Gregory Martin</hi> reaſoneth thus; "Their own Service book (ſaith he) appointeth theſe books of <hi>Toby</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> to be read for <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> as the other. Do they read in their Churches Apocryphal and Superſtitious Books for Holy Scriptures?</q> ſo clear it is that the very Papiſts are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd in their error by this practiſe of the Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The reading theſe books, though but as the <hi>Canon</hi> and <hi>Rule manners</hi> tends ſo very much to the corrupting the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56725:18"/>
of men in ſome things, that the Diſſenters can in no way approve of it.</p>
               <p>In the defence of the <hi>Devonſhire</hi> and <hi>Corniſh Miniſters</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, 'tis thus argued. <q>If the Apocriphal Books be Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical as teaching manners, then whatſoever point of manners thoſe books do commend unto us, either by <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept</hi> or <hi>allowed Example,</hi> we not only <hi>may</hi> but <hi>muſt</hi> obſerve it for Conſcience ſake, as a divine Rule or Canon.</q>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis true hereby a late Order, which was that the wicked Diſſenters, if poor receive not Almes, will be defended, for 'tis but according to the command in <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> 12. 5. where 'tis expreſly ſaid; <hi>Give not to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly, hold back thy bread,</hi> and <hi>give it not unto him: leaſt he over-maſter thee thereby.</hi> But how agreable this Precept is unto the pure word of God, or the light of nature, let a common capacity judge, but though this practice is enjoyn'd to the defence of that but now mention'd order, yet there are other allowed, and highly approv'd practiſes, which are moſt odious in the apprehenſion of the Diſſenter, and are really abhor'd by all but bloody Papiſts. For <hi>Judiths</hi> tricking up her ſelf on purpoſe to tempt and enſnare the heart of <hi>Holofernes</hi> to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, her compaſſing an Irreligious Governour by fraud, by lies, by oaths and proteſtations in the name of God, to the end ſhe might the more aſſuredly murder him, is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an allowed, but a practice highly approv'd of by the book of <hi>Judith,</hi> that is appointed to be read in <hi>October.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> though now return'd from the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Captivity, yet to the very time <hi>Holofernes</hi> was murdered by <hi>Judith,</hi> they remained under the Government of the <hi>Emperour.</hi> The Emperour though an Idolater, yet their Lawfull Governour, whoſe Government they ſhould not have ſhaked off by frauds, by lies, equivocations, and other ſinfull practices, which yet <hi>Judith</hi> did to the gaining the greateſt applauſe and commendation; The which is read in the Church as the Rule of manners, whereas in truth, 'tis meet only for the countenancing the unjuſtifiable treaſons
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56725:19"/>
of the Papiſts, to which purpoſe it has been improv'd by <hi>Saunders de ſchiſmate,</hi> who <q>inciting the Engliſh Ladies, profeſſing the Popiſh Religion to murder <hi>Queen Elizabeth,</hi> and all her Favourers, calling her <hi>Holofernes,</hi> the <hi>Heretical Prince,</hi> did prove from this example of <hi>Judith,</hi> that they might do it, without any the leaſt ſtain or blot to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This is urg'd in the defence of the reaſon of the <hi>Devon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> and <hi>Corniſh</hi> Miniſters, from whence I would query, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a perſon fully convinc'd of that, if the book of <hi>Judith</hi> muſt be read as the <hi>Rule of manners,</hi> this allowed practice of <hi>Judith muſt</hi> be in the like caſe imitated, ought not rather to abandon the reading or hearing of theſe books, then preſume to enter on the practiſes of murdering by lies, deceits. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I verily believe, that the Non-Conformiſts rather than that they would imitate <hi>Judith</hi> in theſe things, would rather be expoſ'd to the worſt of miſeries, whereby they would more effectually demonſtrate to the World the Loyalty of their Principles, than by their Conformity.</p>
               <p>There are ſeveral other things that muſt be practiſed; if the Apocriphal Books be embrac'd as the <hi>Rule of manners,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which the Diſſenters cannot conform. But deſigning to be ſhort, I will at this time wave the conſidering them, and proceed to ſhew the ſenſe, ſome of the Old Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Proteſtants had of theſe books, as I find it in the <hi>Abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <q>The Old Church of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dr. Whitaker)</hi> never vouchſafed the Apocriphal Books ſo much honour as to read 'em publiquely, which alſo the Learned hold to be a good preſident for us to follow—The <hi>Council of Hippo</hi> (ſayes Biſhop <hi>Jewell)</hi> ſpeaking of the Canonical Scriptures, decreed that beſides them nothing might be read in the Church. The Council held at <hi>Laodicea</hi> decreed, on the Sabbath we may not read any books, that be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Canon, but only <hi>the</hi> Canonical books of the Old and New Teſtament. To the like effect <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſpeaks,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56725:19"/>
(ſayes the ſame <hi>Jewell,)</hi> and as Biſhop <hi>Jewell,</hi> ſo Biſhop <hi>Horn,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Pilkinton</hi> aſſerts, the <hi>French Church by the conſtitutions of Lewes and Charles,</hi> were againſt the reading of the Apocrypha.</q> Whoever will diligently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare what Proteſtant writers offer againſt Apocryphal books, with the books themſelves will find ſo many idle ſtories and fables, ſo many errors and ill preſidents in it, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but conclude with <hi>Dr. Sutcliff.</hi> 
                  <q>That it is impudence in the Papiſts, that they match <hi>Apocryphal books</hi> and Legends, with the Scriptures, or at leaſt read them in the Churches, together with the Scriptures.</q>
               </p>
               <p>From the whole hath been ſaid on this particular, I inferr that 'tis but charity to conclude that ſome Diſſenters may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſuch ſtrong convictions concerning the unlawfulneſs of conforming to this part of the Liturgy, that their Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity may be more juſtly eſteemed the product of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, than the Off-ſpring of obſtinacy, and an unreaſonable Humour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="argument">
               <head>
                  <hi>Argument</hi> II.</head>
               <p n="2">II. Some Diſſenters cannot Conſcientiouſly approve of the Tranſlation of the Pſalmes, which is read at the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Lord's dayes ſervice, becauſe 'tis not only imperfect, but moreover in ſome places ſenſeleſs and abſurd, and in other places falſe, directly contradicting our laſt Tranſlation of the Pſalmes in the Bible.</p>
               <p>The Tranſlation now us'd is the ſame ſet forth in the times of ignorance, when the light of the truth did but begin to dawn in <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th. dayes, and is</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Imperfect,</hi> becauſe among many other omiſſions, all the Titles, though a part of the original and very uſefull, are left out.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Senſleſs and abſurd, for <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58. 9. where our Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation has it thus, <hi>viz.</hi> before your pots can feel the Thorns, he ſhall take them away with a Whirl-wind, both <hi>living,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:56725:20"/>
and in his wrath.</hi> In the Service Book Tranſlation 'tis, or ever your pots be made hot with Thorns, ſo let indignation vex them, as <hi>a thing that is raw.</hi> So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. 6. He ſhall come down like <hi>rain upon the mowen graſs.</hi> This in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer is Tranſlated thus, he ſhall come down like the <hi>rain into a fleece of Wool.</hi> This our Old Proteſtant divines look'd upon as a corruption in the Papiſts, not to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, but can it be leſs ſo when done by the ſons of the Church of <hi>England, Fulk, Withers, Bulkley, Whitaker,</hi> and others have blamed the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> Tranſlation, becauſe 'tis in many places ſenſeleſs and abſurd, for which reaſon ſeeing the Tranſlation of the Pſalmes in the Service Book, is as ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in ſome things, as that of the Rhemiſts is in other, 'tis as much to be blamed, and as little to be approv'd.</p>
               <p>But this is not all, for this Tranſlation in <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th, is not only <hi>imperfect, abſurd</hi> and <hi>ſenſeleſs,</hi> but moreover in ſome places contrary to the original, not only in the opinion of Diſſenters, but alſo in the judgment of thoſe who were the Authours of the beſt Tranſlation that ever was in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The Pſalter has it in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17. 4. Thus, becauſe of mens works that are done <hi>againſt the words</hi> of thy lips: I have kept me from the wayes of the deſtroyer, but more agreeably to the Original, our Tranſlation is thus, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the works of men, <hi>by the words</hi> of thy lips I have kept me from the paths of the deſtroyer, whereby 'tis apparent, that not mens works that are done againſt the words of God's lips kept <hi>David</hi> right, but concerning mens works, <hi>David</hi> was kept from the paths of the deſtroyer, <hi>by the words of God's lips.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. In <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. 26. The <hi>Pſalter</hi> ſayes, <hi>that with the frow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard,</hi> thou ſhalt <hi>learn frowardneſs,</hi> but according to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, 'tis as our laſt tranſlation in the Bible has it, <hi>with the froward thou ſhalt ſhew thy ſelf froward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. In the <hi>Pſalter Pſal.</hi> 68. 6. 'tis thus, he is the God that maketh men <hi>to be of one mind in an houſe,</hi> whereas according
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56725:20"/>
to the Hebrew, 'tis <hi>God ſetteth the ſolitary in Families.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. In the <hi>Pſalter, Pſal.</hi> 107. 40. Though he ſuffer them to be evil intreated through Tyrants, but according to the Hebrew in our Bibles; He poureth contempt upon Princes. But,</p>
               <p n="5">5. In <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105. 28. The <hi>Pſalter</hi> ſayes, <hi>And they were not obedient unto his word,</hi> but the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> And <hi>they rebelled not againſt his word,</hi> or were <hi>not diſobedient to his word.</hi> And in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106. 30. The <hi>Pſalter</hi> has it; Then ſtood up <hi>Phineas</hi> and <hi>Prayed,</hi> and ſo the Plague ceaſed; But our Bibles, then ſtood up <hi>Phinehas</hi> and <hi>executed judgment,</hi> and the Plague ceaſed, which is not only moſt agreeable to the <hi>Hebrew</hi> in this place, but moreover to the Hiſtory in <hi>number</hi> 25. 7, 8.</p>
               <p>Such as conform to the ordinary Lord's dayes Service, muſt not only ſhew their approbation to the many idle Stories in the Apocryphal books, and give 'em that countenance that alone pertains to the pure word of God; but beſides muſt lay aſide the Tranſlation that is moſt exactly agreeable to the Original, and uſe one that is not only imperfect, abſurd and ſenſeleſs, but in ſome things ſo contrary to the Original. But ſome Diſſenters think that their Conformity in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect cannot but prove pernicious to the Chriſtian Religion, as it caſts a reproach not only on the laſt and beſt tranſlation, but even on the Original it ſelf; They know how jealous God is about his word, unto which no additions, diminuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or alterations can be made, but to the provoking the moſt high, and the wounding their Conſciences, and therefore are afraid to conform.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="argument">
               <head>
                  <hi>Argument</hi> III.</head>
               <p n="3">III. The third Argument doth more immediately concern the very <hi>Service</hi> it ſelf, unto which the Diſſenters refuſe to Conform, becauſe of that <hi>ſimilitude, likeneſs</hi> and <hi>agreement</hi> there is between it and the formes of Prayer, which the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> uſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:56725:21"/>
That the <hi>Reader</hi> may be the more fully acquainted with the true State of this controverſie, about the agreeableneſs there is between the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and <hi>Roman Service</hi> Books, and what 'tis the Diſſenters aim at by their inſiſting ſo very much on it, I muſt ſhew.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What they ſay concerning the agreableneſs that is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be between theſe Service Books.</p>
               <p n="2">2. How this came to paſs; What occaſion'd our adhering ſo cloſely to the Popiſh Service Book even when we forſook their Communion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Reaſonings of ſome Diſſenters from that agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs is ſuppos'd to be between theſe two books againſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Service.</p>
               <p>Firſt, What they ſay concerning the <hi>agreableneſs</hi> that is ſuppos'd to be between theſe two Service books.</p>
               <p>The Diſſenters do out of <hi>King Edward's Letter</hi> unto the <hi>Devonſhire</hi> and <hi>Corniſh Rebels</hi> give this following account of it, namely. <q>As for the Service in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue thus manifeſt reaſons for it, and yet perchance it ſeemeth to you a <hi>new Service,</hi> and indeed is <hi>none other but the old;</hi> the ſelf ſame words in Engliſh, which were in Latine. The differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is, that you our Subjects ſhould underſtand in Engliſh, that which before was ſpoke in Latine. If the Service of the Church was good in Latine, it remaineth good in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, for nothing is alter'd, but to ſpeak with knowledge, that which was ſpoke with ignorance.</q> Furthermore theſe Diſſenters add, as I find in their <hi>Anatomy of the Service Book.</hi> 
                  <q>That every piece and parcel of the Liturgy, word for word is out of theſe Popiſh peices, namely the <hi>Breviary</hi> out of which the <hi>Common Prayers</hi> are taken, the <hi>Ritual,</hi> or <hi>book of Rites,</hi> out of which the <hi>Adminiſtration of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, Burial, Matrimony, viſitation of the ſick</hi> are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. The <hi>Maſs-book,</hi> out of which the conſecration of the Lord's Supper, Collects, Epiſtles and Goſpels, are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: As for the book of ordination of Arch-biſhops, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Miniſters, that is out of the <hi>Roman Pontifical.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:56725:21"/>
Theſe things being ſo, whoever pleads for the Engliſh Service book, doth ſo far defend the Romiſh Maſs-book, not that 'tis a defence of the whole Romiſh Service, for in the <hi>Anatomy</hi> of the Service Book 'tis acknowledged, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing in the Maſs-book is not in our Liturgy, though all that is in our Liturgy is word for word in the Maſs-book. But ſo far as our Liturgy is defended, ſo far that part of the Romiſh Service is defended, for which reaſon, the greateſt Champions, who among our Church men have moſt zealouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly written in defence of the Liturgy, and have been conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd by the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> as men; who have done great Service to the Roman Religion. Thus <hi>Whitgift</hi> and <hi>Hooker,</hi> have had their applauſes from the Romaniſts</p>
               <p>'Tis not unworthy obſervation to find <hi>Arch-Biſhop Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gift</hi> reproaching <hi>Cartwright,</hi> and the Diſſenters as a people eminently ſerviceable to the Papiſt, and Dean <hi>Stilling fleet</hi> to give the utmoſt countenance he could thereunto, whereas the truth is, that that on which <hi>Whitgift</hi> grounds his cenſure, will not bear it, and though none of <hi>Dean Stilling fleet</hi>'s ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries have taken any notice of it, that I can find, yet <hi>Whitgift</hi> himſelf is the man, who has had from the Jeſuites great thankes for what he has written againſt Diſſenters, in defence of the Engliſh Service and Diſcipline.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Whitgifts Cenſure</hi> concerning the Diſſentes ſubſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency to Popiſh deſignes is groundleſs, being rather the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of his indiſcreet paſſions, than of ſound arguings, is evident, in that the great reaſon given to ſhew that the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters are the Papiſts promoters, is becauſe they aſſert that the Papiſts ought not to be compel'd to receive the Supper of the Lord, ſo long as they continue in their <hi>Popery,</hi> that is, they ought not to <hi>act contrary to their Conſcience,</hi> nor <hi>diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> with Almighty God, by profeſſing themſelves to be Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, even when they are really, and in heart Papiſts; whether this be to gratifie the Papiſt let the impartial Reader judge.</p>
               <p>But that <hi>Whitgift</hi> has gratify'd the Papiſt in his writings
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:56725:22"/>
againſt Diſſenters; I'll evince by producing what the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Parker</hi> in his <hi>Eccleſiaſtical policy, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>chap.</hi> 33. inſiſts on, in anſwer to this objection of <hi>Whitgift, Bancroft,</hi> and others, where he ſhews how <hi>William Reignolds</hi> the Jeſuit aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, that <hi>John Whitgift</hi> in his diſcourſe againſt <hi>Cartwright,</hi> has defended the <hi>Catholick</hi> Cauſe, and accordingly the ſaid <hi>Reignolds</hi> in the preface againſt <hi>Whitaker,</hi> makes great uſe of <hi>Whitgift,</hi> and in the book it ſelf, he ſends <hi>Mr. Whitaker</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Dr. Whitgift,</hi> for a ſupply of reaſons for the confirming their notion about putting of our caps, and making curteſie at the hearing the Name of Jeſus. <hi>Scultinyns</hi> and <hi>Stapleton</hi> give the ſame Character both of the writings of <hi>Whitgift</hi> and <hi>Bancroft</hi> againſt the Puritanes, even as <hi>Gretzer</hi> the Jeſuit triumphs in <hi>Saravias</hi> and <hi>Sutcliff's</hi> defence of the Epiſcopal Authority in Civils.</p>
               <p>And as <hi>Whitgift,</hi> even ſo <hi>Hooker,</hi> for the ſervice done the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> by what they have writ in defence of the worſhip and diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> hath had the praiſes of the <hi>Romaniſts.</hi> This Mr. <hi>Walton</hi> in the life of <hi>Hooker</hi> has obſerv'd, which is no more than what <hi>Dr. King,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter</hi> was acquainted with, as he himſelf ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes in a letter to honeſt <hi>Iſaac.</hi> 
                  <q>I am glad you mention (ſayes the Biſhop) <hi>how much value Robert Stapleton, Pope Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> the 8th, and other eminent men of the Romiſh perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion have put upon this book, having been told the ſame in my youth by perſons of worth, that have travelled <hi>Italy.</hi>
                  </q> And what doth this diſcover leſs than that ſuch is the <hi>agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> between the <hi>Service</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and that of <hi>Rome,</hi> that whoever pleads for the one, defends the other.</p>
               <p>Furthermore in the <hi>Anatomy of the Service Book,</hi> we are furniſhed with an Hiſtorical Account of the Papiſts appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving our Liturgy. <q>There be, ſayes the Author thereof, abundance of inſtances for the Papiſts approving our Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, witneſs <hi>Mortons Appeal, Pope Pius</hi> the 4th, and <hi>Gregory</hi> the 13th. offered to <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi> to confirm the Engliſh
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:56725:22"/>
Liturgy; Witneſs <hi>Dr. Abbot</hi> then Prelate of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and <hi>Mr. Cambden</hi> in the life of <hi>Queen Elizabeth,</hi> who ſayes the common fame went for truth, that the <hi>Pope</hi> promiſed to confirm out of his own authority the Engliſh Liturgy, provided her Majeſty ſhould rank her ſelf with the Roman Church: To thefe I adjoyn <hi>Dr. Boyes,</hi> who was a bitter expoſitor of the Engliſh Liturgy, as <hi>Heiga</hi> by the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of <hi>Dowayes</hi> appointment was of the Maſs, after he hath whetted his teeth upon the Schiſmaticks in his Epiſtle to <hi>Bancroft,</hi> he produceth the letter of <hi>Pope Pius,</hi> for the approbation of the Service Book, and notes alſo the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of approbation from <hi>Briſtow,</hi> in his motives, <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi> being interdicted by the Popes Bull. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary <hi>Walſingham</hi> wrought ſo, that he procured two In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligences to be ſent from the Pope, as it were in ſecret in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>England,</hi> to whom the Secretary appointed a State <hi>Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligencer</hi> to be their Guide, who ſhew'd them <hi>London,</hi> and <hi>Canterbury ſervice</hi> in all the pomp of it, which the popiſh <hi>Intelligencers</hi> viewing and conſidering well, with much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration they wondred, that their <hi>Lord the Pope</hi> was ſo ill adviſed, or at leaſt ill informed as to interdict a Prince, whoſe <hi>Service</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> ſo <hi>Symobiliz'd</hi> with his own, and therefore returning to <hi>Rome</hi> they poſſeſt the Pope, that they ſaw no <hi>Service, Ceremonies</hi> or <hi>Orders</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> but they might very well ſerve in <hi>Rome,</hi> whereupon the Bull was recalled, to this alſo Doctor <hi>Carrier,</hi> conſid. <hi>p.</hi> 45. a dangerous ſeducing Jeſuit gives ample evidences; The <hi>Common Prayer book,</hi> (ſaith he) and the Catechiſm contained in it, held no point of Doctrine expreſly contrary to Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, that is, as he explaineth himſelf contrary to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Service,</hi> &amp;c.</q> Much more might be ſpoke to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but I wave it, judging that what hath been already of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd is ſufficient to evince, that there is, at leaſt in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of many, a very great <hi>agreableneſs between the two ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice books.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:56725:23"/>
2. What is it <hi>that occaſion'd the Church of Englands adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to ſo great a part of the Romiſh Service Book,</hi> even when <hi>ſhe forſook the Communion of that Church?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whoever conſiders the State of the Church in <hi>Edward the ſixth</hi> his time, will find that <hi>Cranmer</hi> and others diſcover'd a propenſion to drive on the Reformation much farther than they did, but were hindred by the iniquity of the times. Thus <hi>Bullinger,</hi> as I find it in a difcourſe of the troubles of <hi>Franckford,</hi> reports to Mr. <hi>Williams, Whittingham, Gilby</hi> and others, that <hi>Cranmer</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> had drawn up a book of Prayers an hundred times more perfect than this we now have, but the ſame could not take place, for that <hi>Cranmer</hi> was matched with a wicked Clergy and Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with other enemies.</p>
               <p>There were alſo reaſons of a like nature that might hinder the furtherance of the reformation in <hi>Queen Elizabeths</hi> dayes, for even then the <hi>ignorance</hi> of the vulgar accompanied with a proportionable hatred to true Religion was very great; Whence 'tis that <hi>Cambden</hi> aſſures us, <q>that the change of Religion was not ſuddenly made, but by <hi>little</hi> and <hi>little, by degrees,</hi> for the Roman Religion continued in the ſame State it was firſt, a full Month, and more after the death of <hi>Queen Mary.</hi> The 27th of <hi>December</hi> it was tolerated to have the <hi>Epiſtles</hi> and <hi>Goſpels,</hi> the <hi>Ten Commandments,</hi> the <hi>Symbole,</hi> the <hi>Litany,</hi> and the <hi>Lords Prayer</hi> in the vulgar Tongue. The 22 <hi>of March</hi> the Parliament being Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, the order of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth was re-eſtabliſhed, and by act of the ſame, the whole uſe of Lord's Supper, granted under both kinds. The <hi>24th. of June</hi> by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of that which concern'd the Uniformity of Publique Prayers, and Adminiſtration of the Sacraments. The Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Maſs was aboliſhed, and the Liturgy in the Engliſh Tongue more and more Eſtabliſhed. In the Month of <hi>July,</hi> the Oath of Allegiance was propoſed to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and other perſons, and in <hi>Auguſt,</hi> Images were thrown out of the Temples and Churches, and broken, and burn'd.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:56725:23"/>
Furthermore, as the illneſs of the times did impeed a <hi>ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> Reformation, in like manner the moderate temper, and favourable diſpoſition the <hi>Queen</hi> had to ſome part of Popery, was ſuch as hindred a <hi>full</hi> Reformation; whereupon it was not ſo far carryed on by this Queen, as 'twas ſometime before by her Brother <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth.</p>
               <p>That Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> had a natural propenſion to favour ſome part of Popery, is not only manifeſt from her (I hope) <hi>Conſcientious</hi> conforming ſo far in <hi>Queen Maries</hi> dayes, as to hear Divine Service according to the rule in the Romiſh Church, and her oft going to confeſſion, and afterwards when ſhe came to the Throne, her chooſing to be Crown'd by a <hi>Popiſh Biſhop,</hi> according to the order of the <hi>Roman Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifical,</hi> which had ſo much in it of the Ceremonies and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that 'tis thought very probable, the Proteſtant Biſhops would not act in it, but with great alterations, and that therefore ſhe deſired 'em not to be ingaged in it. But beſide this, Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> gives us the ſame Character I have ſuggeſted, for ſayes he in his Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Reformation, <q>
                     <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi> receiving ſome impreſſions in her Fathers Reign in <hi>favour,</hi> of ſuch Old Rites as he had ſtill retain'd, and in her own Nature loving State, and ſome Magnificence in Religion, as well as in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing elſe, ſhe thought, that in her Brother's Reign they had ſtript it too much of External Ornaments, and had made their Doctrine too narrow in ſome points, therefore ſhe intended to have ſome things explained in more general Termes, that ſo all parties might be comprehended by them. She inclin'd to keep up Images in Churches, and to have the manner of Chriſt's preſence in the Sacrament left in ſome general words, that thoſe who believed the Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral preſence might not be driven away from the Church by too nice an explanation of it.</q> So far Dr. <hi>Burnet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In purſuance of theſe reſolves, the Queen attempts the accommodating matters of Religion ſo unto the Romiſh Clergy, as to take 'em into the Communion of the Church
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:56725:24"/>
of <hi>England,</hi> the which end, as Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> affirmes, ſhe ſo effectually compaſſ'd, that for ſeveral years the <hi>Papiſts</hi> continued in the Communion of the Church, and when they did forſake it, it was not becauſe they approved not of our Liturgy, but upon political conſiderations, and becauſe the Councill of <hi>Trent</hi> had commanded it, and <hi>Pope Pius</hi> the 5th. had Excommunicated the Queen, and diſcharg'd her Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects from their Allegiance, and made the going or not go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Church a ſign diſtinctive, to difference a Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick from an Engliſh Proteſtant.</p>
               <p>I'll give you the words of Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> they are in his Hiſtory of Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> 
                  <q>There paſt another Act for recommending and impoſing the book of Common Prayer, and Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, according to ſuch alteration and corrections as were made therein by thoſe who were appointed to reviſe it, as before is ſaid. In the purſuance of which ſervice, there was great care taken for expunging all ſuch paſſages in it, as might give any <hi>ſcandal or offence to the Popiſh party,</hi> or be urg'd by them in excuſe for their not coming to Church, and joyning with the reſt of the Congregation in God's publique worſhip. In the Litany firſt made and publiſhed by King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight, and afterwards continued in the two Liturgies of King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the ſixth, there was a <hi>Prayer to be deliver'd from the Tyranny, and all the deteſtable enormities of the Biſhops of Rome,</hi> which was thought fit to be expung'd, as giving matter of ſcandal, and diſaffection to all that party, or that otherwiſe wiſh'd well to that Religion. In the Firſt Liturgy of <hi>King Edward,</hi> the Sacrament of the <hi>Lord's</hi> Body was deliver'd with this benediction, that is to ſay, <hi>the body of our Lord Jeſus Christ, which was given for the preſervation of thy Body and Soul, to Life Everlaſting; The blood of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. which being thought by <hi>Calvin</hi> and his Diſciples to give ſome countenance to the groſs and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal preſence of Chriſt in the Sacrament, which paſſeth by the name of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> in the School of <hi>Rome,</hi> was
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:56725:24"/>
alter'd into this form, into the ſecond Liturgy, that is to ſay, <hi>take and eat this in remembrance that Chriſt dyed for thee, and feed on him, in thy heart by faith with Thanksgiving; Take and drink this.</hi> &amp;c. But the <hi>Reviſers</hi> of the book joyn'd both formes together, leaſt under colour of rejecting a <hi>carnal,</hi> they might be thought alſo to deny ſuch a <hi>real pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence</hi> as was defended in the writings of the antient fathers. Upon which ground they expung'd alſo a whole <hi>Rubrick</hi> at the end of the Communion Service, by which it was decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that kneeling at the participation of the Sacrament, was required for no other reaſon, than for the ſignification of the humble and gratefull acknowledging of the benefits of Chriſt given therein unto the worthy Receiver. And to avoid that prophanation and diſorder which otherwiſe might have enſued, and not for giving any adoration to the Sacramental Bread and Wine, there bodily received, or <hi>in regard of any real and eſſential preſence of Chriſt's Body and Blood. And to come up cloſer to the Church of Rome,</hi> it was ordered by the <hi>Queens injunctions</hi> that the <hi>Sacramental Bread</hi> (which the book required onely to be made of the fineſt Flower) ſhould be made <hi>round, in faſhion of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers uſed in the time of Queen Mary.</hi> She alſo order'd that the <hi>Lord's Table</hi> ſhould be placed where the <hi>Altar</hi> ſtood, that the <hi>accuſtomed</hi> reverence <hi>ſhould be made at the name of Jeſus, Muſick retained in the Church,</hi> and all <hi>the old feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals obſerv'd,</hi> with <hi>their ſeveral Eves;</hi> By which comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, and the expunging of the paſſages before remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, the book was made <hi>ſo paſſable amongſt the Papiſts,</hi> that for ten years they generally repair'd to their Pariſh Churches, without doubt or ſcruple, as is affirm'd not only by Sir <hi>Edward Cook</hi> in his Speech againſt <hi>Garnet,</hi> and his charge given at the Aſſizes held at <hi>Norwich,</hi> but alſo by the <hi>Queen</hi> her ſelf, in a Letter to Sir <hi>Francis Walſingham,</hi> then being her Reſident, or <hi>Leiger Embaſſador</hi> in the Court of <hi>France,</hi> the ſame confeſſed by <hi>Sanders</hi> alſo in his book <hi>de Schiſmate.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:56725:25"/>
To this <hi>Heylin</hi> within a few years following adds. <q>And now we may behold the face of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as it was firſt ſetled and eſtabliſhed under <hi>Queen Elizabeth.</hi> The Government of the Church by Archbiſhops and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops;—The Liturgy conform to the primitive patterns, and all the Rites and Ceremonies therein preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, accommodated to the honour of God, and encreafe of piety. The Feſtivals preſerved in their <hi>former Dignity,</hi> obſerv'd with all their diſtinct Offices peculiar to them, and celebrated with a Religious Concourſe of all ſorts of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the weekly Faſts, the <hi>Holy</hi> time of Lent, the Embring weeks, together with the Faſt of the Rogation, ſeverely kept by a forbearance of all kind of fleſh, <hi>not now by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the Statute,</hi> as in the time of King <hi>Edward,</hi> but as <hi>appoynted by the Church in her publique Calendar,</hi> before the book of Common Prayer, the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper celebrated in <hi>moſt reverend manner,</hi> the Holy Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeated in the place of the Altar, the people making their due reverence at their firſt entrance into the Church, <hi>kneeling</hi> at the Communion, the confeſſion and the publique prayers, <hi>ſtanding</hi> up at the Creed, the Goſpels and the <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Patri,</hi> and uſing the accuſtomed reverence at the name of Jeſus; Muſick retain'd in all ſuch Churches in which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion had been made for the maintenance of it, or where the people could be trained up at leaſt to plain Song; All which particulars were either Eſtabliſhed by the Lawes, or commanded by the <hi>Queens</hi> injunctions, or otherwiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by virtue of ſome antient uſages, not by Law pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited. Nor is it much to be admired that ſuch a general Conformity to thoſe <hi>antient uſages</hi> was conſtantly obſerv'd in all Cathedrals, and the moſt part of the Pariſh Churches, conſidering how well they were preſidented by the Court it ſelf, in which the Liturgy was Officiated every day, both morning and evening, not only in the publick Chappel, but the private Cloſet, celebrated in the Chappell with Organs, and other Muſical Inſtrments, and the moſt excellent voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:56725:25"/>
of men and children, that could be got in all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. The Gentlemen and Children in their Surplices, and the Prieſts in Copes as oft as they attended the Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice at the <hi>Holy Altar.</hi> The <hi>Altar furniſhed with rich Plate, two fair Gilt Candleſticks with Tapers</hi> in them, and a <hi>Maſſy Crucifix</hi> of Silver in the midſt thereof, which laſt remained there for ſome years, till it was broke in peices by <hi>Pach,</hi> the fool (no wiſer man daring to undertake ſuch a deſperate Service) at the ſollicitation of Sir <hi>Francis Knolles,</hi> the <hi>Queens</hi> near Kinſman by the <hi>Caries,</hi> and one who open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeared in favour of the Schiſm at <hi>Franckford.</hi> The <hi>antient ceremonies accuſtomably</hi> obſerv'd by the Knights of the Garter, in their <hi>Adoration</hi> towards the Altar, <hi>aboliſhed</hi> by King <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th, and reviv'd by Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> were by this <hi>Queen</hi> retain'd as formerly in her Fathers time—for which ſhe received both thankes and honour from her very enemies, <hi>[i. e.</hi> the Papiſts] as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by <hi>Harding's</hi> Epiſtle Dedicatory before his anſwer to the Apology, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> So far <hi>Heylin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus from what the ſons of the Church, <hi>Cambden, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi> and <hi>Heylin</hi> have affirm'd, 'tis apparent that <hi>Queen Eliz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abeth</hi> had a natural propenſion to favour the Papiſts, and that this was diſcover'd by her making the Termes of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion much more eaſie to the Papiſts than in King <hi>Edward</hi>'s time, whereby they became the more difficult and arduous to the Proteſtant Diſſenter. I'll only add one obſervation of the <hi>Jeſuit Reignold</hi> againſt <hi>Whitaker,</hi> whereby the <hi>Reader</hi> may perceive, not only that the Papiſts take notice how the <hi>practice</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi> contradicts their <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick,</hi> but alſo that in the <hi>Rubrick</hi> concerning Apparel, which is now to be found in the Communion Book, even the beginning before morning prayer, 'tis order'd; <hi>That the Miniſter at the time of Communion,</hi> and <hi>at all other times in his Miniſtration, ſhall uſe ſuch Ornaments in the Church, as were in uſe by Authority of Parliament, in the ſecond year of the Reign of King</hi> Edward <hi>the 6th.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:56725:26"/>
But Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was not the <hi>only</hi> cauſe of driving back the Reformation, but the <hi>Clergy</hi> themſelves had an hand in it, which was ſufficiently diſcover'd, when they perceiv'd that her Majeſties <hi>Council</hi> began to entertain more favourable thoughts of Proteſtant Diſſenters, who continued their cries for a further Reformation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cambden</hi> aſſures us, that about the year 1583, <q>The Queen (who held it for a <hi>maxime</hi> that ſhe ought not to be more remiſs in <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Affaires,) advancing <hi>Whitgift</hi> from the Sea of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> to that of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> above <hi>all</hi> commanded him to re-eſtabliſh the Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that as then lay diſmembred by the conniven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Prelates, the obſtinacy of Innovators, and by the <hi>power of ſome great ones,</hi> whilſt ſome Miniſters—uſing to their own fantaſie new Rites of Services in their private Houſes, utterly condemning the Liturgy, and the appointed manner of Adminiſtring the Sacrament, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in many things contrary to the Scriptures, and therefore many refus'd to go to Church.—To aboliſh which things, and to reduce 'em in Unity, <hi>Whitgift</hi> propounded Three Articles to the Miniſters, by them to be ſubſcribed. But (adds <hi>Cambden)</hi> 'tis incredible what controverſies and diſputations aroſe upon this—What troubles and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries <hi>Whitgift</hi> ſuffer'd of <hi>certain noble men.</hi>
                  </q> So far <hi>Camb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But whoever might be ſo happy as to be throughly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with a juſt, impartial and particular Hiſtory of thoſe times would ſuddenly ſee, that the true cauſe of all <hi>Whitgifts</hi> troubles was his intemperate perſecuting Godly and Conſcientious men, who rather like a <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſitor</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd a multitude of Articles to enſnare, than as a good <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor</hi> to reduce his erring Brethren to the truth; For even when he was moſt violent in letting out his rage on the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious Diſſenter, even then the wicked, the ungodly and prophane Prieſts knew not what it was to be proſecuted for their debaucheries. Neither can it be truly ſaid that the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:56725:26"/>
                  <hi>Earl of Leiceſter</hi> was the only great perſon, that reſented the ill proceedings of this Biſhop, but even the Lord <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer Cecill,</hi> and her Majeſties <hi>Councill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis ſad to conſider with what ſeverity <hi>Whitgift</hi> treated the Couſcientious Diſſenter, and with what mildneſs the drunkard, glutton, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The which was ſo palpable, that ſome zealous Conformiſts, ſince that time have judg'd it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to eſſay the putting ſome colour on it, as <hi>Iſaac Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> in the life of <hi>Hooker,</hi> moſt Satyrically repreſents the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſt to be much more vile than the drunkard or glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, even when he could not impeach 'em as being guilty of any ſuch enormities. But that ſomewhat might be ſaid to expoſe the Diſſenter, and defend the Biſhops, an encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is made on the divine prerogative and vain man, who cannot but with much difficulty look into his own heart, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to ſee into the ſecrets of the Diſſenter, where he finds ſo many <hi>Spiritual wickedneſſes</hi> that lye hid to lodge, that he muſt be warm in diſcovering his abhorrence to ſuch Villanies, judging not according to the <hi>outward appearance,</hi> but like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the all-knowing God, according to the <hi>heart.</hi> I'll give you Mr. <hi>Walton's</hi> own words, who ſpeaking of the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts, ſayes. <q>Of this party there were many that were poſſeſt with an high degree of <hi>Spiritual wickedneſs;</hi> I mean with an <hi>innate reſtleſs radical pride</hi> and malice, I mean not thoſe <hi>leſſer</hi> ſins, that are more <hi>viſible,</hi> and more properly Carnal, and ſins againſt a mans ſelf, as gluttony and drunkenneſs, and the like, (from which good Lord deliver us) but ſins of an <hi>higher nature,</hi> becauſe more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to the nature of God, which is <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Mercy,</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> and more like the Devil, (who is not a glutton, nor can be drunk, and yet is a Devil:) thoſe wickedneſſes of malice and revenge, and oppoſition, and a <hi>complacence</hi> in making and beholding confuſions.—Men whom <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Self-conceit</hi> had made to over-value their own Wiſdom, and become pertinacious, and to hold <hi>fooliſh</hi> and <hi>unmannerly diſputes againſt thoſe men,</hi> which they ought to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:56725:27"/>
reverence, and thoſe Lawes which they ought to obey.</q> As if diſputing freely with the Biſhop, and not giving him the deſir'd reſpects by rendring obedience to his commands, even when they could not without ſinning againſt God, had been the Overt Act of that Pride, Malice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which makes men more vile than Gluttony and Drunkenneſs.</p>
               <p>But 'tis no part of my preſent province to comment on this notion, but only from it to inferr, that as the dignified Clergy did conſider the Non-Conformity of the Diſſenter to be a ſin moſt odious, much more high and great, than that of <hi>gluttony,</hi> even ſo 'tis eaſie to conclude, that what is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd in <hi>Hiſtory</hi> concerning the Biſhops treating the drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard with more candor than the Conſcientious Diſſenter, is very true; For which no ſtronger reaſon can be aſſign'd, than that the debauchees wickedneſs, not being ſo great an impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment to the accommodating the difference between the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and of <hi>Rome,</hi> as the Non-Conformity of the Diſſenter, the wickedneſs of the former might be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated, even when the <hi>Diſſent</hi> of the latter would not be born.</p>
               <p>That this is ſo, namely, that the <hi>Arch-biſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> in the reſpects they ſhew'd the ignorant, and ſcandalous among the Miniſtry, and the letting out their wrath on the <hi>intractible</hi> Diſſenter as they term'd it, was a plain evince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that they thereby aimed at the gratifying the Papiſt, will appear with conviction to ſuch as will be ſo juſt to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as to weigh impartially the import of thoſe <hi>Letters,</hi> are added to the end of this <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> where he will not only ſee into the reaſon, why the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> would by all means hide 'em from the Light, but moreover perceive the <hi>matter of fact,</hi> I have ſuggeſted to be very <hi>true.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That theſe <hi>Letters</hi> are nor ſpurious, nor feigned, but co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies from an <hi>Anthentick Original</hi> is well known to ſome zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Sons of the Church, who it may be will be ſurpriz'd to ſee that appear in face of the World, which doth ſo plainly diſcover what they deſire might be conceal'd.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:56725:27"/>
In theſe Letters, 'tis apparent, that when the proſecution was moſt brisk againſt Proteſtant Diſſenters, <hi>ſeveral</hi> among the <hi>dignified Clergy were very covetous,</hi> and <hi>ſcandalous in their Converſations. (Numb.</hi> 1.) Even <hi>thoſe who antecedently to their preferment, were well affected, when they came to the</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral Churches <hi>did ſo ſtrangely degenerate, that the</hi> Lord Treaſurer Cecil (Numb. 2.) <hi>did fear the places did alter the men; whence 'tis that her Majeſties</hi> Councill <hi>in their Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Biſhop of</hi> London <hi>and</hi> Canterbury, (Numb. 3.) <hi>did obſerve from the many complaints brought unto them, that the worſt of men met with no trouble, when Conſcientious and Learned Miniſters were greatly moleſted for their Non-Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that which doth moſt fully diſcover the <hi>temper,</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign</hi> of <hi>Whitgift,</hi> as one who acted rather like a <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> than a good Proteſtant, impoſing Articles that were of an enſnaring tendency, is what I find in the Letters of the <hi>Lord Cecil</hi> unto the <hi>Arch-biſhop,</hi> with <hi>Arch biſhops reply. Numb.</hi> 4. 5, 6. The which is more generally ſuggeſted in <hi>Cambden,</hi> who mentions the diſſatisfaction of <hi>ſeveral noble men,</hi> with the <hi>Biſhops</hi> proceedings, but more expreſly by a moderate writer in <hi>Queen Elizabeths,</hi> who (in his plea of the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent) doth in the name of the Non-Conformiſts ſpeak thus of the <hi>Lords of the</hi> Councill—<q>And this is not all, that bindes us to their honours: for in our private troubles about the Ceremonies and Subſcription, we the poor and faithfull Miniſters of Chriſt, whenſoever we have opened our cauſe, and humbled our ſelves unto them, we have found great <hi>juſtice</hi> and <hi>equity,</hi> and divers times <hi>great relief</hi> and <hi>eaſe</hi> from our troubles; No doubt they ſeeing our inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, that of meer Conſcience without any the leaſt incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to diſloyalty to our Sovereign, we did forbear to do thoſe things, they have tendered our cauſe, and lovingly effected, that we might not be too much over-burdened.</q> Moreover concerning the Biſhops they ſay; <q>What could we do leſs, or better, than to repair to the Reverend <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:56725:28"/>
for Counſell and Comfort, which for the ſpace of ten years, (or the moſt part thereof,) they did in ſome good meaſure afford unto us, till as I take it by the relation of ſome in the ſame broyles, the <hi>Papiſts had cunningly wreſted our good Fathers from us,</hi> that they could, and would do no further for us. Then yet complaining of our caſe, and opening our doubts unto them, we did as the Law afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that the cauſe ſhould be brought before the <hi>Ordinary,</hi> in all doubts about ceremonies of the Church Eſtabliſhed by Law: and finding not our ſelves reſolv'd by our ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, alas what could we do leſs, than quietly to ſuffer our ſelves (with great grief bewailing our flocks) to be ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, impriſoned and deprived. And this hath been the cauſe of all them, which have not uſed the Ceremonies ſo fully as ſome other of their Brethren.</q>
               </p>
               <p>By this 'tis evident, that as <hi>Queen Elizabeth's</hi> Education, natural temper, Intereſt of State, and I verily believe, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of Duty unto God inclin'd her to ſuch an eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitution,</hi> as might <hi>be moſt grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full unto the Papiſt,</hi> even ſo ſome of the <hi>Clergy</hi> (who by <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi> are called <hi>Melancthonians</hi> of whom <hi>Whitgift</hi> and <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croft</hi> were principal in their times,) did their utmoſt by inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo very much on the <hi>Ceremonies, Subſcription,</hi> &amp;c. to the ſame end the <hi>Queens</hi> Majeſty did, whereby to the great grief of many Sound Proteſtants, the <hi>Service of our Church</hi> was <hi>made to reſemble as much as poſſible, that of the Church of</hi> Rome. But,</p>
               <p n="3">3. I'll now conſider the reaſonings of ſome Proteſtant <hi>Diſſenters</hi> from this <hi>ſimilitude, likeneſs</hi> and <hi>agrement</hi> there is <hi>between theſe two ſervice books</hi> againſt the <hi>ordinary uſe of the Engliſh Liturgy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whoever will make a due enquiry into the Hiſtory of the Reformation, will find that in <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th, his dayes, <hi>Hooper</hi> Lord Biſhop elect for <hi>Glocester,</hi> ſcrupled the <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Veſtments,</hi> becauſe they had been invented cheifly for ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrating the Maſs with much pomp, and had been conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:56725:28"/>
for that effect. In <hi>Queen Maries</hi> time the exil'd Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants at <hi>Frankford,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Knox,</hi> and thoſe of his perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, refuſed to Miniſter the Communion by the book of <hi>England,</hi> for <hi>that there were ſome things in it placed only by warrant of man's Authority,</hi> or no <hi>ground of God's word for the ſame,</hi> and had <hi>alſo a long time very</hi> Superſtitiouſly <hi>in the</hi> Maſs <hi>been wickedly abuſed.</hi> See diſcourſe <hi>of the troubles</hi> at <hi>Franckford.</hi> Moreover in <hi>Queen Elizabeth's,</hi> and King <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>dayes,</hi> ſeveral manifeſted their diſlike of our <hi>Liturgy</hi> for this very reaſon, becauſe 'twas ſo <hi>like</hi> unto the <hi>Romiſh Service.</hi> I'll give ſome particular inſtances with thoſe rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons that were by 'em urg'd againſt a complyance with a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice Book, ſo like that of the <hi>Papiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In a part of the <hi>Regiſter</hi> you have the ſenſe of Mr. <hi>Edward Deering,</hi> who ſayes that; <q>The ſimilitude that this book has, with the form of Prayer which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> uſed; I think declineth from the equity of theſe Lawes, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7. 25. <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. 30. <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. 9. which things our fathers ſo much regarded in the Primitive Church, that their books are full of great complaints, againſt all ſimilitude to be had with the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> Yea the ſecond Councill of <hi>Bracca</hi> made a decree, that no Chriſtian ſhould have either Bay-Leaves, or Green Boughes in their houſes, becauſe the <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſo accuſtomed; And at this day all Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in <hi>France, Polonia, Helvetia, Scotland,</hi> and other places have changed that <hi>form of Prayer,</hi> which prudence of all ages, if we ſhall condemn, the rebuke of the Apoſtle, I think will touch us. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 36. <hi>Came the word of God out from you, or came it elſe to you only?</hi> Secondarily, we have the <hi>Pſalmes, Venite, Benedictus, Magnificat, nunc di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittis,</hi> uſual in our Miniſtry, of which we can give no good reaſon. Nor I ſee no cauſe why we ſhould more leave out the <hi>Ave Maria.</hi> And becauſe of parting the Scriptures again into the Epiſtles and Goſpels (which was not heard of before the dayes of Popery,) I dare not avow that this is that reverent handling of the Scripture, and the right di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:56725:29"/>
of the word of truth, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> requireth 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 15.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But the <hi>Abridgment</hi> is much more full on this Subject, ſhewing what are the many Scriptural Arguments againſt all complyances with the Superſtitions, the which is farther con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd, not only from the <hi>Fathers,</hi> the <hi>Tranſmarine Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Divines,</hi> but alſo by <hi>our own</hi> Old Proteſtant <hi>Doctors</hi> of the <hi>Church of England.</hi> Take it as in the <hi>Abridgment,</hi> where 'tis aſſerted, that 'tis contrary to the word of God, to uſe ſuch ceremonies in the worſhip of God, as man has deviſed, if they be notoriouſly known to have been of old, and ſtill to be abuſed unto <hi>Idolatry</hi> or <hi>Superſtition,</hi> by the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> eſpecially if the ſame be now of no <hi>neceſſary</hi> uſe in the Church; Where note, that the Ceremonial part of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Service that is like unto that of the Romiſh, is what has been abuſed by the <hi>Papiſts</hi> to Idolatry or Superſtition, but yet are not ſo neceſſary to Divine Worſhip, but that the worſhip may be compleat, decent and orderly without em but to their reaſons, this may appear ſay they.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <q>By the Second Commandment which forbids all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation unto ſpiritual fornication, as the 7th. doth unto that which is Carnal.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <q>By the Commandment and direction God hath given us in his word to ſeparate our ſelves from Idolaters, and be as unlike to them as may be, eſpecially in their Religious Obſervations and Ceremonies, to aboliſh not only all Idols, but alſo all the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> and <hi>Inſtruments of Idolatry,</hi> and that ſo as we may beſt ſhew our utmoſt deteſtation to them, and root out the very memory of them, to caſt away even ſuch things as had a good Original, and uſe (if they be not ſtill neceſſary, or commanded of God) when once they are known to have been defiled by Idolatry, or abuſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <q>By the equity and reaſons of theſe Commandments which we find ſet down in Holy Scripture, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. The <hi>deteſtation which the Lord</hi> our God (being a jealous God)
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:56725:29"/>
beareth unto <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and all the Inſtruments and Tokens thereof, as unto Spiritual Whoredom. 2. That we cannot be ſaid ſincerely to have repented of the Idolatry or Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whereby we or our Fore-fathers have provoked the Lord, unleſs we be aſhamed of, and caſt away with deteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> and <hi>Monuments of it.</hi> 3. That we ſhall be in danger to be corrupted in the Subſtance of Religion, and purity of Doctrine, and even to fall back again unto idolatry, if we conform our ſelves to Idolaters in their Ceremonies, and retain the Monuments of their Superſtition, yea if we ſhew not all deteſtation unto them. 4. That our holding of Conformity with Idolaters in their Ceremonies (wherein they repoſe the greateſt part of their Religion,) will be a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial mean to harden them in their Superſtition. 5. That ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Pope</hi> is reveiled to be that great <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and his Idolatry troubleth the Church, at this day more than any other, and our people converſe more with Papiſts than with any other Idolaters, there is more danger in the retaining of the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> and Relicks of Popery, than of any other Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry whatſoever.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <q>By the judgment of the <hi>Godly Learned</hi> of all <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Ages,</hi> who have conſtantly taught and given Teſtimony to this Truth, that <hi>Chriſtians are bound to caſt off the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> and <hi>Religious Cuſtomes</hi> of <hi>Pagans, Jewes, Idolaters</hi> and <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and carefully to ſhun all Conformity with them therein.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>In the Councell of <hi>Nice</hi> it was decreed, that Chriſtians might not keep the Feaſt of Eaſter at that time, nor in that manner as the Jewes did: Let us (ſay they) in nothing agree with that moſt deteſtable rout of the Jewes.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>And in another Councill, that none ſhould faſt on the Lord's day, becauſe the <hi>Manichees</hi> had taken up that day to faſt on, which alſo <hi>Augustine</hi> alledgeth and approveth of in another That ſuch Altars as were ſet up in the Country, and High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, in memory of the Martyrs, ſhould be aboliſhed, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they were pretended to be ſet by Revelations or Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and that ſolemn requeſt ſhould be made to the <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,</hi> that all Reliques and Monuments of Idolatry might
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:56725:30"/>
be utterly deſtroyed. And this decree we find cited by <hi>Dr. Fulk.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>In another <hi>Councill</hi> it was decreed, that none of the Clergy ſhould forbear or make ſcruple to eat Fleſh, that they might ſhew themſelves to differ from the <hi>Priſcillianiſts.</hi> In <hi>another,</hi> that Chriſtians ſhould not deck their houſes with Bay leaves, and Green Boughs, becauſe the <hi>Pagans</hi> did uſe ſo to do. That they ſhould not reſt from their labours thoſe dayes that the <hi>Pagans</hi> did, and that they ſhould not keep the firſt day of every Month as they did. In another, that Chriſtians ſhould not celebrate Feaſts on the Birth dayes of Martyrs, becauſe that was the manner of the Heathen. <hi>Tertullian</hi> is large and vehement in this point, as (ſaith he) we may give nothing to the ſervice of an Idol; So may we borrow nothing from the ſervice of an Idol; If it be againſt Religion to ſit at Table in an Idols Temple, what is it to be ſeen in the habit of an Idol. Again, no habit or apparel is eſteemed Lawfull amongſt us, that hath been dedicated or appointed to ſo unlawfull an Act. Thou that art a Chriſtian muſt hate thoſe things, the Authors and Inventors whereof, thou canſt not chooſe but hate. In another place he affirmeth, that Chriſtians might not waſh their hands, nor lay aſide their Cloakes before Prayer, nor ſit upon their Beds after Prayer, becauſe the Heathen uſed ſo to do. <hi>Melchiades</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> decreed, that no Chriſtians ſhould faſt on the Lord's day, or on the Friday, becauſe it was a known cuſtom of the <hi>Pagans</hi> to faſt on thoſe dayes. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> taught <hi>Monica,</hi> the Mother of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> as <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> himſelf reporteth it, which is alſo alleadged by Biſhop <hi>Jewel,</hi> to leave bringing of Wine and Cakes to the Church, as ſhe was wont to do, becauſe ſhe might not Lawfully give ſuch a ſhew of Conformity with the <hi>Gentiles. Auguſtine</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf alſo preſcribing a direction how to winn the <hi>Pagans,</hi> hath theſe words, if you ask how the <hi>Pagans</hi> may be won, how they may be enlightned, how they may be called to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation? leave all their Solemnities, forſake their Toyes. <hi>Gregory</hi> (as we find him cited by Biſhop <hi>Jewel)</hi> alleadgeth and approveth of a decree of the Councell of <hi>Toledo,</hi> which forbade the Ceremony of <hi>thrice dipping in Baptiſm,</hi> becauſe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:56725:30"/>
it was the cuſtom of certain <hi>Hereticks. Leo</hi> adviſeth all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to ſhun the viperous conference of Hereticks, and that in nothing they would be <hi>like</hi> unto them, who in name only are Chriſtians. The judgment of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> appeareth in a Letter, written from a general Aſſembly held at <hi>Edenborough</hi> 1566. unto the Biſhops of <hi>England.</hi> In which (beſides many other ſentences to this purpoſe,) thus they write; If <hi>Surplice, Corner Cap</hi> and <hi>Tippet,</hi> have been badges of <hi>Idolaters</hi> in the very Act of Idolatry, what have the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Chriſtian Liberty, and the open Rebukers of Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition to do with the dregs of the Romiſh Beaſt. And more plainly in the confeſſion of their Faith, whereunto his right excellent <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with others of the cheif ſtates of that Kingdom, did ſolemnly ſwear and ſubſcribe, where we find theſe words. <hi>[We deteſt all</hi> the Ceremonies <hi>and falſe Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of</hi> the <hi>Roman Antichrist,</hi> added to <hi>the miniſtration of the true Sacraments; We detest all his vain Allegories, Rites, Signes</hi> and <hi>Traditions brought into the Church without the Word of God.]</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>—Thus</hi> have ſuch as have been chief <hi>Pillars</hi> in our own Church, judg'd of the <hi>Monuments of Idolatry,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d all Conformity with Papiſts in their Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi> (that Holy Martyr) would not conſent to a Canon that was to be made in King <hi>Edward</hi>'s dayes for the Clergies Uniformity, in <hi>Cap, Tippet,</hi> and the reſt of the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel, unleſs it might be decreed that the Papiſts for a <hi>differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> between them and others, might be conſtrained to wear upon their ſleeves a <hi>Challice</hi> with an <hi>Hoſt</hi> upon it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Our late <hi>Queens</hi> injunctions require, that all Monuments of Idolatry and Superſtition be ſo utterly extinguiſhed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, that there may remain no memory of them either in our Churches or Houſes. And the Book of <hi>Canons</hi> made <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Dom.</hi> 1571. <hi>That no man wear the grey Amice, or any other garment defiled with the like Superſtition.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> in one place approveth the judgment of <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian,</hi> and the Fathers of that Age: who forbade Chriſtians to wear Garlands of Bay, not for that (ſaith he) the thing was ill of it ſelf, but for that they would not ſeem to follow Idolaters. It had ſome appearance of evil. And in another
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:56725:31"/>
place, ſpeaking of ſundry of the Popiſh Ceremonies, <hi>you have</hi> (ſaith he, ſpeaking to the Papiſts,) <hi>ſo miſuſed theſe things, or rather ſo defiled and bewrayed them with your Superſtitions, that we can no longer continue them without breach of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Biſhop <hi>Pilkinton</hi> miſliked, that in our Liturgy we are ſo <hi>like</hi> the Papiſts; In <hi>Marriage</hi> (ſaith he) and many other things beſides, we are but too like unto them; That is our fault ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, that we differ not more from them, in all our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Biſhop <hi>Weſtphaling</hi> (in his Treatiſe of Reformation) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadgeth to this purpoſe, and alloweth this ſentence of <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,</hi> whoſoever (be he Jew or Gentile,) that ſhall obſerve the Ceremonies of the Jewes, not only he that doth it unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly, but even he that doth it to any other intent, tumbleth himſelf into the Bottomleſs pit of the Devil.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Biſhop <hi>Bilſon</hi> (defending the Reformed Churches againſt a ſlander of the Papiſts,) reporteth thus of them, as approving and allowing them in it; The Reformed Churches (ſaith he) are ſo far from admitting the full doſe of your Hereſies, that by no means they can digeſt one dram of your Ceremonies.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Dr. <hi>Humfrey</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Conſtantines</hi> zeal in forbidding all Conformity with the Jewes, affirmeth; That all men ought to imitate him therein, and refuſe to conform them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the enemies of God in any of their Ceremonies. And in another place he profeſſeth plainly both his deſire and hope of the utter aboliſhing of the Ceremonies, and of all the Monuments of Popiſh Superſtition that yet remain in our Church.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Dr. <hi>Fulk</hi> in one place ſaith; If any man miſlike our form of Service, as not differing ſufficiently from yours, he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his greater zeal in deteſtation of your Idolatry and Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy. And in another; We abhorr (ſaith he) whatſoever hath but a <hi>ſhew</hi> of Popery. In another place he gives this for a reaſon, why our Miniſters uſe to ſtand at the North-ſide of the Table at the Communion, that we might ſhew our ſelves thereby unlike to the Papiſts,</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:56725:31"/>
                  <q>Dr. <hi>Andrews</hi> now <hi>Dean</hi> of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> hath this Speech in his Catechiſm, if it be true that is in <hi>Jude</hi> 23. that we muſt hate the very Garment that the fleſh had ſpotted, ſurely, becauſe the Idol is as unclean and abominable, no leſs abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable muſt that Garment be, that it hath ſpotted.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Dr. <hi>Sutcliffe</hi> maketh this one of his principal Arguments againſt the Papiſts; that they have derived moſt of their Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies and Cuſtoms from the <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Pagans.</hi> See alſo a moſt plain and pregnant Teſtimony of Mr. <hi>Greenham</hi> for this our firſt Argument in the laſt Edition of his Workes. But above all others that ever were read, <hi>Marbury</hi> is moſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory and bitter in this point. And as all theſe Divines agree with us in this our firſt Argument againſt the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, ſo do they and others alſo, in the reaſons we have brought out of the Scriptures to confirm it by.</q> For they hold.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <q>That thoſe Lawes, that we have alleadged out of the Old Teſtament againſt the Monuments of Idolatry, do bind us as much as they did the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and from them they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude as we have done, that all Reliques of Popiſh and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh Superſtition, are to be baniſhed out of the Church of of Chriſt; Of this judgment are <hi>Calvin, Martyr, Grineus, Wolphius, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus, Macabeus, Zanchius, Simterus, Zepperus,</hi> our own Book of Homilies;</q> Dr. <hi>Fulk</hi> and others.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <q>That <hi>Ezekiah, Joſiah,</hi> and the reſt of the Godly Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> which ſhewed moſt zeal in aboliſhing thoſe things which had been abuſed to Idolatry, did no more than they were bound by the Law of God to do, and that from their example the Argument holds ſtrong againſt the Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Idolatry now, becauſe all Chriſtians are bound to imitate their zeal therein. Of this judgment was <hi>Auguſtine, Calvin, Martyr, Wolphius, Lavater, Zanchius, Zadeel,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Jewel,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Bilſon,</hi> Dr. <hi>Fulk,</hi> Dr. <hi>Rainold, Dr. Andrewes,</hi> Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> and others.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <q>That the retaining of the Popiſh Ceremonies will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be a means to indanger the doctrine that we profeſs, and to bring the people back again to Popery. This was the judgment of the divines of <hi>Saxony,</hi> and of them of <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> of <hi>Luther, Oecolampadius, Calvin, Bucer, Martyr,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:56725:32"/>
Wolphius, Chemnitius, Pezelius, Zanchius, Dr. Andrews, Mr. Greenham,</hi> and others.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <q>That the retaining of the Ceremonies of Idolaters will cauſe them to inſult over our Religion, as if it could not ſtand without help from them, and ſo <hi>harden</hi> them in their liking of their own Idolatry. This reaſon hath been uſed againſt Conformity with the Jewes, by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and by all the fathers in the firſt Councell of <hi>Nice,</hi> and againſt Conformity with the Papiſts, by <hi>Brentius, Muſculus,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> and others.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Fourthly, we are confirmed in this our perſwaſion that it is unlawfull to retain the ceremonies of the Papiſts, by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the great hurt they have done, and do daily in the Church.</q> For we find.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>That ſome of the learnedſt of our Engliſh Papiſts (namely <hi>Martial, Briſtow,</hi> and he that penned that Petition for the Papiſts, which <hi>Dr. Sutcliffe</hi> and <hi>Mr. Powel</hi> have anſwered,) have by this Argument juſtified their Church and Religion, that <hi>we have borrowed our</hi> ceremonies <hi>from them,</hi> yea ſome of them (as <hi>Harding, Martial,</hi> and he that wrote the <hi>Apologe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Epiſtle</hi> for our <hi>Engliſh Papiſts,)</hi> have profeſſed, that this was to them an evident Argument, that Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did in her conſcience like well of their Religion, becauſe ſhe liked and maintained their ceremonies, and the ſuperſtitious multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, do uſually defend the bleſſing of themſelves with <hi>croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their Breaſts</hi> and Foreheads, by our Croſſing our children in Baptiſm.</q> So far the <hi>Abridgment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which I'll not make many an addition, becauſe I think that the reaſonings of thoſe Reverend Divines, thoſe great Doctors and Biſhops of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are ſo weighty and important, that an impartial <hi>Reader</hi> cannot but conclude: that though the influence this Argument may have on ſome be inconſiderable, yet it may be ſtrong and very cogent in the judgment of others, in order to the obliging 'em to refuſe to joyn with the Church in the uſe of the <hi>Engliſh Service:</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally at <hi>ſuch a time</hi> as this, wherein <hi>we are under the fearfull ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of</hi> Popery.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:56725:32"/>
If ever a Popiſh Succeſſor ſhould enter the Engliſh Throne, we may eaſily ſuppoſe, he'll do his utmoſt for the re-introducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his own Religion amongſt us, the which <hi>now</hi> cannot be done with more eaſe and ſpeed, than the firſt eſtabliſhing the Proteſtant Religion in this Kingdom has been. For, as the generality of the people were for Popery <hi>then,</hi> they are <hi>now</hi> as much againſt it, and therefore as the firſt Reformers <hi>ſuited</hi> the progreſs of the Reformation to the temper of the vulgar, ſo muſt the Papiſt <hi>now,</hi> and as King <hi>Edward</hi> argued for the Engliſh <hi>Liturgy,</hi> from its agreableneſs with the <hi>Romiſh;</hi> So <hi>now</hi> the Papiſts will argue on behalf of the Romiſh Service, from its agreableneſs with our Engliſh, and ſay, if 'twere good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an Heretical Under, why ſhall it be leſs ſo under a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick King, then (they may ſay) you have with the approbation of his Holyneſs the <hi>Pope,</hi> what formerly you had by the good liking of the Heretick only.</p>
               <p>'Tis not improbable that at firſt the <hi>Pope</hi> will be content, we ſhall uſe the ſame Liturgy we now have, with very little alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and to gain <hi>England</hi> under his Tyranny, will conſent to what Pope <hi>Pius</hi> would have done in Queen <hi>Elizabeth's</hi> days, and a late Pope in <hi>Laud's</hi> time: and then by little and little add unto the Liturgy, ſometime a few Prayers, and again for the greater Solemnity, Decency and Order in the Adminiſtration of Baptiſm, may add to the ſign of the Croſs, that of <hi>Salt</hi> and <hi>Spittle,</hi> and <hi>Lights,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Seeing then this may be ſo, there are many among the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters,</hi> who are afraid to comply with the uſe of the Engliſh Liturgy, leaſt by their practice they give an unanſwerable ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage <hi>to their</hi> implacable enemy the <hi>Papiſt.</hi> They are aware of the deſign, they are ſenſible how the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> have been practiſing on the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and what uſe they'l make of their not driving on the Reformation much farther, and therefore <hi>now,</hi> in <hi>this day</hi> do think, they ſhall highly provoke the Lord to jealouſie, ſhould they give countenance to the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice Book,</hi> which may be ſo eaſily improved to the advancing the ſuperſtition of the Roman Catholick.</p>
               <p>But if after all it be ſaid by any, that theſe things are <hi>Light-points,</hi> and not ſo much to be inſiſted on, no other anſwer ſhall
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:56725:33"/>
be given, but that of the Reverend <hi>Mr. Dering</hi> in his reply to an objection of a like nature, as 'tis in a <hi>part of the Regiſter.</hi> 
                  <q>If I ſeem curious, or ſtand upon light points, (beſide that in the worſhip of God there is nothing light,) ſo the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of man is exceeding tender, that it will neither be troubled nor touch'd in the leaſt tittle, contrary to the perſwaſion of truth The weight of ſin is not in <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of <hi>matter,</hi> but in the Majeſty of God, that is offended, and be the thing <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo little,</hi> yet the breach of his Commandment deſerveth death. This faith we have learn'd of him, that is the wiſdom of the father, and our only Prophet, that is, whoever ſhall break one of theſe <hi>leaſt</hi> Commandments, theſe words which are <hi>ſhall break one of the leaſt,</hi> have every one a greater weight than may be contemn'd of any man.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="argument">
               <head>
                  <hi>Argument</hi> IV.</head>
               <p>There is in this Service Book a ſtrange diſorder and confuſion unworthy the grandure and Majeſty of that God, unto whom we make our approach in Prayer. God is a great King, his Name is dreadfull even among the Heathen, he is great and greatly to be feared and reverenced even in the Aſſembly of his Saints. God is in Heaven, we on the Earth, and therefore as our words muſt be few, even ſo muſt they be utter'd in the graveſt, and moſt ſerious manner. God is a jealous God, and 'tis dangerous to trifle with him, when we come to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him; Yea God is a God of Order, and not of Confuſion, and therefore our Addreſſes ſhould be in the moſt Solemn Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               <p>This all will grant, but the queſtion is, <hi>whether there be any ſuch</hi> diſorder <hi>in the Common Prayer Book;</hi> For this has been formerly objected againſt the <hi>extempore</hi> and <hi>free Prayer</hi> of <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters,</hi> who are ſaid to enter raſhly into God's preſence, and pray after the moſt diſorderly manner conceivable, how then comes this to be urg'd (may ſome ſay) againſt that ſet form of Prayer, which has been with the greateſt deliberation of the Fathers of the Church Compos'd. I reply,</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:56725:33"/>
That the <hi>Reader</hi> may the more diſtinctly Comprehend what I have to offer on this Fourth head of Argument, I muſt beſeech him to conſider. 1. That I am not defending ſuch as will inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately Ruſh into the preſence of Almighty God, and prophane in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of honouring the name of God in Prayer. I durſt not plead for ſuch an Irreverent or uncomely practice. Neither 2. Do I deſign to offer any thing againſt thoſe, who will ſeriouſly medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on what they have to do, when they make their approaches unto the Throne of Grace. Premeditation on the matter to be prayed for, on the Method of the Addreſs, yea, and on the choice of Expreſſions, is ſo far from a Sin in my Judgment, that I verily believe it to be a duty. Neither, 3. Do I Object againſt the prudent and neceſſary Uſe of ſome ſet form of Prayer in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, for many may be endow'd with the Grace of Gods Spirit, who abound not with its Gifts, and 'tis not enough that a man has the Grace of Gods Spirit to enable him to be the Mouth of Others to God in Prayer, 'tis the <hi>Gift,</hi> that in this Caſe is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, the which ſome may not have who yet muſt pray in publick, or publick Worſhip muſt be totally omitted, in which Caſe the uſing a Form of Prayer is not only lawful, but highly expedient.</p>
               <p>Theſe things premiſed, the <hi>Reader</hi> may eaſily perceive who it is, for whom I do not Apologize, as well as that I am not arguing againſt the Divine Service Book, as it Contains a <hi>Form of Prayers,</hi> nor as it a form impoſed, which yet I approve not of, but as 'tis <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>form</hi> ſo <hi>diſorderly,</hi> and <hi>Confuſed</hi> a <hi>Form.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is inſiſted on in the <hi>Altar of Damaſcus,</hi> and in the <hi>Lincoln Abridgment.</hi> In the Altar it is thus expreſſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Then again their Prayers are ſhred into ſo many ſmall pieces, <hi>They pray in Two or Three Lines, and then after having read, ſome other things come, and pray as much more, and ſo to the Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth or Thirtieth time, with pauſes between.</hi> Prayers ſhould be continued together, not cut off, and interrupted, or cut in ſmall pieces. They do with their Prayers, as they do with their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpels and Epiſtles which they rent from their Contexts, which would ſerve for memory and greater Edification.</q> So ſar he. To whom I add, That if a <hi>Diſſenting Miniſter</hi> in Pulpit before his Sermon, when he addreſſes himſelf to God in Prayer, ſhould utter Three or Four Sentences in Prayer, and then go off to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, to the reading Two or Three Verſes in the Bible, and then to his Prayer, and then to Reading, would not the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:56725:34"/>
of the Church ſay, this Diſſenting Miniſter, by Confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reading and Prayer, offers up his Requeſts after a moſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly manner. But to the <hi>Abridgment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Abridgment 'tis urg'd, <q>That by this Book ſundry things, that bring great <hi>Diſorder</hi> and <hi>Confuſion</hi> unto the Worſhip of God are appointed As that the People ſhould ſay after the Miniſter whole Sentences of Prayer and Scripture, yea the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter one part of the Prayer, and the people another, and in ſundry parts of the Letany, the people make the Prayer, and the Miniſter only directs them what to pray for.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The Miniſter at ſome time muſt pray, and the People give the reaſon of the Prayer; for Inſtance. The Miniſter Prayes ſaying, <hi>Give peace in our days O Lord,</hi> and the people make their Anſwer, <hi>Becauſe there is no other that fighteth for us, but only thou O God,</hi> as if Almighty God <hi>alone</hi> had not been able to defend them in the time of War, whence they Pray unto God for the ſending Peace. But cannot that <hi>God,</hi> who ſendeth Peace by putting an end unto Wars, preſerve and protect in the day of Trouble. If he can, to what purpoſe is this Argument urg'd. Again an alteration is made in the State of this Affair. The Miniſter gives inſtruction, or rather as a beginner of the Prayer, mentions the <hi>Matter</hi> or <hi>Thing</hi> to be prayed for, and the people muſt proceed to the mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it a <hi>formal</hi> Prayer, whence 'tis, that whereas the Miniſter in the publick Aſſembly ſhould be the Mouth of the people unto God, The Miniſter being ſilent, the people altogether with a loud voice, a diſtracting Murmur are their own Mouth. Thus, <hi>From Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and all other deadly Sin,</hi> (as if ſome ſins were not Mortal, but Venial) <hi>and from all the Deceits of the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil,</hi> ſo far the Miniſter proceeds, and then make a ſtop, from whom the people take it adding <hi>Good Lord deliver us.</hi> Again, <hi>O Lamb of God, that taketh away the ſins of the World,</hi> ſays the Miniſter with the greateſt ſeeming fervour and affection, but yet in the midſt of the ſentence, his warm affection is ended, and the people proceed to ſay, <hi>Grant us thy peace O Lord.</hi> Again they muſt be as they were <hi>in Statu Quo,</hi> and the Miniſter prayes, <hi>O Lord let thy Mercy be ſhewed on us,</hi> to which Petition the people either add, <hi>their ſence,</hi> or <hi>Limitation,</hi> or <hi>Reaſon</hi> of the Prayer, <hi>as we put our Truſt in thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſide at ſome one meeting of the Aſſembly, the <hi>Pater-Noſter,</hi> or Lords Prayer is to be repeated Six or Eight ſeveral times, and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:56725:34"/>
the <hi>Gloria</hi> Patri Twelve, beſide the many <hi>Kyrie Eleeſons</hi> and <hi>Christe Eleeſons, Lord have mercy on us, Chriſt have mercy upon us,</hi> the <hi>Reſponces,</hi> the <hi>Verſicles, &amp;c.</hi> Alas how ridiculous would this be interpreted by the generality of thoſe who are now Sons of the Church, ſhould the Diſſenters have uſ'd ſuch a practice!</p>
               <p>This <hi>Argument</hi> receives ſtrength from what I find inſiſted on by by ſome of His <hi>Majeſties Commiſſioners</hi> in the <hi>Account of all the proceedings of the Commiſſioners of both perſwaſions,</hi> where 'tis thus Argued, Vid. <q>As we find that the Miniſter is the Mouth of the people to God in publick (which Scripture, and the neceſſity of Order do require,) So we are loath to Countenance the people's Invading of that Sacred Office, ſo far as they ſeem to us to do, By reading half the Pſalms and Hymnes. 2. By ſaying half the Prayers as the Miniſter doth the other half,—4. By being the only Petitioners in the far greateſt part of all the Letany by their <hi>[Good Lord deliver us]</hi> and <hi>[We beſeech thee to hear us good Lord.]</hi> While the Miniſter only reciteth the Matter of the Prayer, and maketh none of the requeſt at all; we fear leaſt by <hi>purity of reaſon,</hi> the people will claim the work of preaching and other parts of the Miniſterial Office. 3. And we mentioned, that which all our Ears are witneſſes of, that until half the Pſalms and Hymns, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are ſaid by ſuch of the people as can ſay them, the <hi>Murmur</hi> of their Voices in moſt Congregations is ſo unintell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible and Confuſed, as muſt hinder the Edification of <hi>all the reſt;</hi> for, who is edified by that which he cannot underſtand.</q> This you'l find page 29, but in page 60, we have account of the <hi>Rule,</hi> and <hi>Order of Prayer,</hi> with a full Demonſtration, That the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer</hi> is <hi>not agreeable unto any juſt Rule,</hi> or <hi>Order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>There are (ſay they) <hi>Two Rules</hi> of Prayer; <hi>One</hi> is the <hi>Nature of the things Compared</hi> (in Matter and Order) with <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Neceſſity;</hi> The <hi>Other</hi> is the <hi>Revealed Will of God in his word,</hi> in <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral</hi> the <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi> more <hi>Eſpecially</hi> the <hi>Lords Prayer:</hi> The Liturgy (for the greateſt part of the Prayers for <hi>dayly <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe)</hi> is <hi>Confuſed</hi> by whichſoever you meaſure it. You ſeem much to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the <hi>Lords Prayer</hi> by your frequent Uſe of it (or part of it) we beſeech you diſhonour it not <hi>practically,</hi> by denying it by Matter and Order, to be the <hi>only Ordinary and Perfect</hi> Rule; We know about particular Adminiſtrations, where it is but cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſelect Requeſts, that we are to put up, ſuited to the part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Subject and Occaſion, we cannot follow the whole Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:56725:35"/>
of the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> which containeth the heads of all the parts, where we are not to <hi>take in all</hi> the parts; we cannot <hi>take them in that Order.</hi> But that none of all your Prayers ſhould be form'd to that perfect Rule; that your <hi>Letany,</hi> which is your <hi>Comprehenſive</hi> Prayer, and that the Body of your dayly Prayers, (broken into ſeveral Collects) ſhould not (as ſet together) have any conſiderable reſpect unto <hi>that Order,</hi> nor yet to the Order, which reaſon and the Nature of the thing requireth (which is obſerved in all things elſe) and yet that you ſhould ſo Admire <hi>this,</hi> and be ſo tenacious of <hi>that</hi> which is conceived Prayer, you would call by worſe names than <hi>Confuſion,</hi> this ſheweth us the power of prejudice.</q>
               </p>
               <p>By this the Reader may perceive how much the <hi>Non-Conformiſts</hi> are for a <hi>decent Order,</hi> and <hi>Comely Method</hi> in <hi>Prayers,</hi> but the <hi>Conformiſt</hi> againſt it, and how much the Non-Conformiſt are for the right uſe of the Lords Prayer, even when the Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt are not at leaſt practically for it. Whence we may ſee how unreaſonable it is to make ſuch a Noiſe and Clamour, as if the Diſſenters rejected the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> or were againſt its uſe, whereas in truth the Diſſenters are much more for the <hi>Right uſe of the Lords Prayer,</hi> than the Conformiſts are.</p>
               <p>Whoever will underſtand the true State of this Controverſie, muſt conſider what the great deſign of the Diſciples in <hi>Aſking,</hi> and of Chriſt in granting their Requeſt about Prayer was, the which he can no ſooner with juſt deliberation, and impartially do, but will be ſatisfied, that the thing the Diſciples deſired was to be <hi>Taught how to Fray,</hi> Lord <hi>Teach us</hi> as <hi>John</hi> taught his Diſciples <hi>How to Pray,</hi> and they deſire to be taught, not that they preſcribe unto Jeſus Chriſt a Method in which he ſhould teach 'em, for that became not <hi>Diſciples,</hi> even <hi>Scholars,</hi> who are to Learn, but not to teach. This being the deſire of the Diſciples to be taught to pray, not to have a form of VVords to be Verbally and Sylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bically rehearſed, or repeated, but <hi>Rules</hi> or <hi>Preſidents</hi> for the <hi>directing 'em,</hi> how to pray. The anſwering of their Requeſt was the Deſign of Chriſt in giving 'em the Lords Prayer, which was principally intended for the <hi>Direction</hi> of the Diſciples, who were as <hi>Matthew</hi> expreſſeth it, Oblig'd by that Command <hi>when ye</hi> Pray, ſay, Our Father, ſo ſay after <hi>that manner,</hi> when you
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:56725:35"/>
pray, or whenever you pray. The Command is perpetual, Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging at all times of prayer ſo far, as the particular Occaſions of Prayer will admit, every Prayer we make muſt be according to this Command of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>But will any ſay, That the meaning is, when ever you pray, repeat the very <hi>words,</hi> and <hi>Syllables</hi> of the Lords Prayer; Let not one Prayer be made without the Repetition of this Prayer. If ſo, then, whereas now the <hi>Lords Prayer</hi> is repeated in the Church ſix or eight times ſome Mornings, it ſhould be ſo Twenty or Thirty, even at the end of every Collect, or other ſhort Prayer. This none will aſſert, which is enough to ſhew, that none do underſtand the words of <hi>Luke, [when you pray ſay]</hi> to be in this ſenſe, namely, <hi>when ever you pray, repeat</hi> theſe <hi>words</hi> and <hi>Syllables,</hi> for none do it, none of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> nor among the Papiſts. The true ſenſe then of thoſe words in <hi>Luke</hi> is more fully given us in <hi>Mathew,</hi> when you <hi>pray ſay after this manner,</hi> that is, The <hi>Lords Prayer</hi> is given as a <hi>Form,</hi> a <hi>Rule,</hi> a <hi>Directory</hi> of <hi>our Prayers,</hi> A Rule to be prayed by, which Rule is tranſgreſſed by ſuch, who when they pray, will cut their Prayers into many ſhreds and pieces. The Lord Chriſts Prayer was but <hi>One continued</hi> Prayer, all its parts moſt admirably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nected, he did not ſay, <hi>Our Father,</hi> and teach his Diſciples to add, <hi>Which art in Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is enough to evince that the <hi>Common Prayer</hi> Book is not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Rule of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and that although according to the <hi>Rubrick</hi> a part of the Lords Prayer is ſo frequently rehears'd in one Morning, as if the rehearſing ſeveral <hi>Pater noſters</hi> was <hi>ex opere Operato</hi> ſufficient to procure the pardon of Sin; yet the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> who do pray <hi>unto him,</hi> unto whom they are directed by the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> for <hi>ſuch things,</hi> as are more generally contain'd in it, keeping as near as they can to the ſame Method, do not only keep more cloſe to the command of Chriſt in <hi>Luke,</hi> but moreover ſet an higher value on the <hi>Lords Prayer</hi> than theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts, who, by keeping to the <hi>Rubrick,</hi> at moſt do make it but the end of ſome of their Prayers.</p>
               <p>But to return from this neceſſary Digreſſion, to what is farther inſiſted on by the aforeſaid. Commiſſioners, p. 62. 'Tis ſaid,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:56725:36"/>
                  <q>But if we may (according to the Common Prayer Book) begin and end, and ſeem to withdraw again, and make a Prayer of every Petition or two, and begin every ſuch Petition with God's name, and Chriſt's merits, as making up half the Form, or near; <hi>Nothing</hi> is an <hi>affected empty toſſing of God's name in Prayer,</hi> if this be not, we are perſwaded, if you ſhould hear a man in a known <hi>ex tempore</hi> Prayer do thus, it would ſeem ſtrange and harſh even to your ſelves.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This being ſo, there are ſome among the Diſſenters, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering how jealous God is in matters of his worſhip, how pure, and how holy, are afraid to draw near to God in this diſorderly and confuſed manner, when they have the opportunity of addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing themſelves to the Throne of Grace, in a way more agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his Holy and moſt Bleſſed Will; When they have a Male in their Flock, they are afraid to offer a corrupt thing, leaſt they thereby expoſe themſelves to that curſe in <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. 14. If they ſhould make their approaches in this diſorderly manner unto God, <hi>will he not ſay, offer it now unto thy Governours, will he be pleaſed with thee,</hi> or <hi>accept thy perſon?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="argument">
               <head>
                  <hi>Argument</hi> V.</head>
               <p>In the Abridgment, an Argument againſt the Ceremonies, to which thoſe who joyn with the Church of <hi>England</hi> muſt ſhew their approbation is fetch'd from the <hi>myſtical ſignificancy</hi> of <hi>'em</hi> thus; <q>All humane Ceremonies (ſay they) being appropriated to God's Service, if they be ordain'd to teach any Spiritual Duty by their myſtical ſignification, are unlawfull.</q>
               </p>
               <p>That this Argument may appear in its fuller ſtrength, 'twill be requiſite to conſider the nature of <hi>Religious Worſhip,</hi> as well as a <hi>Religious Ceremony,</hi> and to make ſome enquiry after the <hi>power,</hi> man has given him to <hi>appropriate Humane Ceremonies to God's wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. whoever will conſult the Learned of moſt perſwaſions, will find 'em to agree in the general about the nature of external wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and a Ceremony of Religion. Dr. <hi>Covel,</hi> a great aſſerter of the Engliſh Ceremonies in his <hi>modeſt and reaſonable examination</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. has very handſomely given the ſenſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>Bellarmine's words<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> as neer as an Engliſh Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can well be to a Latine Original. Whoever will but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:56725:36"/>
                  <hi>Bellarmine's</hi> 29th. <hi>Chapter de effectu Sacramentorum,</hi> with what Dr. <hi>Covel</hi> has in his 6 <hi>chap.</hi> will find the agreement to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt <hi>verbatim; Ceremonia</hi> (ſayes <hi>Bellarmine) eſt actus externus Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionis, qui non aliunde habet laudem, niſi quia fit ad Dei honorem;</hi> that is, as <hi>Covel,</hi> without making any mention of his Maſter <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine,</hi> Tranſlates it, <hi>ceremonies are all ſuch things as are the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Act of Religion, which have their commendation and allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from no other cauſe, but only that in God's worſhip, they are virtuous furtherances of his honour.</hi> Thus <hi>Covel,</hi> who borroweth his explications, as well as arguments from <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> in order to the making the ſtronger defence of Engliſh Ceremonies, is ſo bold as to take the whole ſubſtance thereof from him, without any conſiderable variation, whereby we may find that the Church of <hi>England</hi> agrees ſo far with the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in this matter, as to make a Ceremony of Religion to be. 1. <hi>An external Act expreſſive of inward worſhip. Actus externus interno reſpondens, qui eſt quaelibet externa actio, quae non aliunde eſt bona, niſi quia fit ad Deum colendum;</hi> That is, as <hi>Covel</hi> Tranſlates it, <hi>the External Act anſwering the</hi> internal, which is <hi>no otherwiſe good or commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than that it vertuouſly ſerveth to the inward worſhip of God,</hi> 'tis an outward ſign repreſenting the inward frame of the Spirit, as 'tis after God. 2. 'Tis alſo a <hi>virtuous furtherance</hi> of inward Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is to the honour of God; It is apt to <hi>ſtir up</hi> the dull mind of man to the remembrance of his duty to God, by ſome notable and ſpecial ſignification, whereby he might be <hi>edified.</hi> Ceremonies of Religion are means whereby the dull mind is ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up to the remembrance of duty, and whereby the Soul is edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>(i. e.)</hi> ſtrengthned and confirm'd in grace; Then is a man edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied when his graces are ſuſcitated, ſtirred up, ſtrengthen'd, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd or confirm'd.</p>
               <p>This deſcription of a Religious Ceremony is not only what <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> and <hi>Covel</hi> out of him give us, but alſo the ſame, to which a late Author in his <hi>verdict apon the Diſſenters Plea,</hi> gives his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation. <hi>Page</hi> 57. <q>That ſuch myſtical Ceremonies, or Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical repreſentations are not ſinfull, (ſayes he), I am fully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd, becauſe they are good for the uſe of edifying; For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is apt to <hi>inform</hi> me, and put me in mind of my duty, and to <hi>excite</hi> me to perform it; That is certainly for my edification, becauſe to <hi>inform, to admoniſh,</hi> and excite is to <hi>edifie,</hi> and that ſome myſtical Ceremonies are of this nature, is too notorious to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:56725:37"/>
be deny'd.</q> So far the <hi>Anſwer to Melius Inquirendum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame is aſſerted in the Diſcourſe that is prefix'd unto the <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> concerning the Service of the Church, where 'tis expreſt, <hi>That the Ceremonies are by ſome notable ſignification, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to ſtir up the dull minds of Men to the Remembrance of their Duty.</hi> Their uſe is for the exciting to Duty as well as for inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p>This is that they ſay concerning the Nature of a Ceremony, whereby it ſeemeth to ſome very evident, That there is a great Difference between a <hi>Religious Ceremony,</hi> and a <hi>neceſſary Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Religion.</hi> The <hi>former</hi> is a part of External Worſhip, the <hi>latter</hi> but an Appendix. Some <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> ſuch as time, and place, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are <hi>neceſſary</hi> unto, though no <hi>parts</hi> of Worſhip, but an <hi>humane Ceremonie,</hi> though not neceſſary unto, yet is made a part of Worſhip. We cannot worſhip God but in ſome time, and in ſome place, but can do ſo without any of theſe humane ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant Ceremonies, which yet are made a part of external Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which is but the expreſſing and ſetting forth of the Internal by outward ſigns, by which as by certain outward bodily Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows and Colours the <hi>Spiritual</hi> and Inward Worſhip of God is made <hi>viſible,</hi> and ſenſible to others, as the Learned <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes it.</p>
               <p>Much more might be ſaid by way of Explication, but this is enough to evince, that a Religious <hi>Ceremony</hi> is <hi>ſignificant of thoſe inward motions of the heart that are directed unto God,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently a part of External Worſhip; and more than a <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</hi> That the Ceremonies in Controverſie are of the ſame Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with ſome of thoſe in uſe among the <hi>Papists, Jew,</hi> and <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then;</hi> for which reaſon, who ever can juſtly appropriate the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Ceremonies to Gods Worſhip, may, for the ſame reaſon appropriate thoſe of the <hi>Papiſt, Jew,</hi> or <hi>Pagan,</hi> and, that there is too much of the <hi>Nature of a Sacrament</hi> aſſigned unto 'em, in that they are not only <hi>ſignificant,</hi> but moreover adapted for the <hi>ſtirring up the dull mind unto an edifying Remembrance of duty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſaid, of Religious Worſhip and Ceremonies. The next enquiry is concerning <hi>what power man has given him to appropriate</hi> humane Ceremonies <hi>unto Gods Worſhip.</hi> By <hi>humane Ceremonies</hi> the Diſſenters (If I miſtake 'em not) underſtand ſuch Ceremonies as are neither <hi>Natural,</hi> nor of <hi>Divine Inſtitution,</hi> but of <hi>Mans Invention</hi> only, By <hi>appropriating 'em to Gods Worſhip,</hi> they mean
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:56725:37"/>
an <hi>Ordaining,</hi> or an <hi>uſing them</hi> after a ſolemn and <hi>Religious</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>for Spiritual uſes,</hi> and <hi>ends,</hi> not for Civil or Temporal, but as outward Notes and Teſtimonies of thoſe things that make us Spiritual. The ordaining or Uſing 'em as ſignificant of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Grace, and for the ſuſcitating and ſtiring up thoſe graces thereby ſignified. The which is ſuppoſed to be done even when the Worſhip may be compleat and exactly agreeable to the word of God without them.</p>
               <p>This appropriating humane Ceremonies to Gods Worſhip is not only an Unaccountable adding unto Gods Worſhip, but a making that a part of Chriſts Religion, which God never made to be ſo, which is as unlawful in <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> as 'tis in the <hi>Papiſt.</hi> The <hi>Papiſts</hi> may as lawfully appropriate to Religion a <hi>Shaven Crown,</hi> a <hi>Monks habit, Spittle</hi> in Baptiſm, Holy Water, and all the Miſſal Rites (as <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> has it) as a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Magiſtrate can make a <hi>Surplice,</hi> a <hi>Cope,</hi> a <hi>Croſs</hi> in Baptiſm, Impoſition of hands in Confirmation, Ring in Marriage to be Ornaments of Religion and Holy Ceremonies, yea, as <hi>Bradſhaw.</hi> 
                  <q>Thoſe that may bring in, without ſpecial Warrant from God, <hi>Piping [vid.</hi> of the Organ, <hi>&amp;c.]</hi> into his Service, might as well bring in <hi>Danc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> alſo; thoſe that have Authority to joyn to the Sacrament of Baptiſm, the Sign of the Croſs have Authority alſo (no doubt) to joyn to the Sacrament of the Supper, Fleſh, Broth, Butter, or Cheeſe,</q> and worſe matters than thoſe, if they will [ſeeing they are equally capable of ſignificancy, and apt for the ſtirring up our dull minds to the Remembrance of many a neceſſary duty] Yea, <q>thoſe that have power to make peculiar forms of Religion and VVorſhip, have power to make and invent a Religion of their own.</q>
               </p>
               <p>There are two things, on which the Church men do ſeem to inſiſt very much.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>If the Ceremonies impoſed be in their own Nature indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</hi> And</item>
                  <item>2. Such <hi>as do teach good Doctrine,</hi> they may be lawfully im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. To this the <hi>Old Non-Conformiſts</hi> anſwer'd.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">I. That all things that are in themſelves matter indifferent, are <hi>not</hi> lawful to be done in Divine Service, tho' the Magiſtrate ſhould Command them, the which they judge will be very clear to ſuch as will but conſider what things are <q>indeed indifferent, or go under the Name and Title of indifferent things, that the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:56725:38"/>
Magiſtrate cannot lawfully command, nor the people lawfully obſerve 'em if Commanded.</q> 
                  <hi>e. g.</hi> Eating and Drinking, the <q>avoiding the Superfluities of Nature, Spinning and Carding, Killing of Oxen and Sheep, which of themſelves have in them neither vertue, nor vice, and are therefore indifferent Actions; and yet I think (ſaies <hi>Bradſhaw)</hi> none except profeſſed Atheiſts, but will hold it a foul Sin to do ſome of theſe Actions in any Aſſembly, much more in the ſolemn Worſhip of God, though the Magiſtrate ſhould Command the ſame even upon pain of Death. But if it be further conſidered, That Carding and Diceing, Masking and Dancing, For men to put on Womens Apparel, and VVomen Mens, Drinking to Healths, Ribaldry, Stage-Playes are things indifferent to be done upon the Lord's own day, [at leaſt it was eſteemed ſo when the Book for Plays was to be read] may a Miniſter of the Goſpel upon the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates Command do any of theſe in Divine VVorſhip?</q>
               </p>
               <p>By this we may ſee, That there is not ſo much Innocency in the <hi>meer Indifferency</hi> of an Action, that it ſhould on that Account be meet enough to be appropriated to Gods VVorſhip. Neither,</p>
               <p n="2">2. Can the ſignificancy of a Ceremony, or its aptneſs to edifie and ſtir up grace, be reaſon enough to appropriate a Ceremony to Gods Service, unleſs the playing a Game at Cards may be lawfully introduced into the ſolemn VVorſhip of God. For ſays a late Author, a Son of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in his <hi>Anſwer to Melius Inquirendum,</hi> pag. 57. <q>The other day as I remember, I ſaw a <hi>Pack</hi> of <hi>Cards,</hi> which according to this Account may very well be call'd a Pack of Sacraments, [that is as a <hi>Sacrament</hi> is Conſidered to be a <hi>Outward and viſible ſign of an inward and Spiritual Grace]</hi> for each <hi>Card</hi> had the <hi>Matter of a Sacrament,</hi> that is, an <hi>Outward,</hi> and <hi>Viſible ſign of ſome Inward, and Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Grace</hi> in the Martyr [Sir <hi>Edmund. Godfrey]</hi> (whoſe barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Murder they were deſign'd to repreſent;) and ſure the ingenious Contrivers of thoſe <hi>Cards</hi> intended ſome <hi>effect</hi> from them, to <hi>excite,</hi> to <hi>ſtir up,</hi> to <hi>encreaſe</hi> Grace and Devotion by the ſight of them, <hi>Viz.</hi> an utter abhorrence of Treaſon, and all Popiſh Principles, which lead to it, and muſt this poor <hi>pack of Cards</hi> be condemn'd to the Flames for the Ingenuity of the Author?</q> So far our Author. Who ſhould have ſaid and may not this <hi>pack of Cards,</hi> ſo like unto other humane ſignificant Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, or Sacramentals, be <hi>appropriated unto the ſolemn Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:56725:38"/>
of God,</hi> May not the Miniſter and People in the midſt of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn VVorſhip apply themſelves to thoſe Cards, ſeeing they in their play turning 'em frequently over, may be <hi>excited</hi> to an <hi>utter abhorrence</hi> of <hi>Treaſon,</hi> and whether any ſober Divine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> would ſo far approve of the appropriating this indifferent but ſignificant Ceremony, namely this pack of Cards to their ſolemn Religious VVorſhip, is not difficult to determine. To return to what Mr. <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> adds, who ſpeaking of the above mention'd Ceremonies, ſaies, <q>There is none of <hi>theſe</hi> but may have applyed unto them, by the VVit of Man, a Myſtical and Religious Senſe, even the <hi>filthieſt Actions,</hi> and things that are, may teach good Doctrine. The Holy Ghoſt reſembleth the Soul polluted with Sin to a <hi>Menſtruous Cloth,</hi> A man fallen again into Sin to a <hi>Sow wallowing</hi> in the Mire: Might therefore a filthy Sow, and ſuch unclean Clothes be brought into the Church, to be viſible Shadows, and repreſentations of ſuch things? Pray, what may not by this means be brought into Gods VVorſhip, and yet by this reaſon he defended to be a good Ceremony, if the Magiſtrates and Biſhops ſhould decree the ſame.—A Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter clothed with ſuch Apparel as thoſe that Act the Devils part in a play may teach this, That by Nature we are Limbs of Satan and Fire-brands of Hell: Bear-baiting may teach us how Chriſt was baited before the Tribunals of the Phariſees, or the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate between the Fleſh, and the Spirit.</q> 
                  <hi>But ſhall theſe be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore appropriated to God's Worſhip?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus, no good Argument may be fetch'd either from the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency,</hi> or <hi>ſignificancy</hi> of <hi>Ceremonies</hi> for their lawfulneſs in God's worſhip, though commanded by the Magiſtrate. For not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the utmoſt can be ſaid from either of theſe <hi>Topicks,</hi> there will not (as Diſſenters think) be enough to ballance what is offer'd againſt the lawfulneſs of the Ceremonies, or of a comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with 'em in God's Worſhip; On the which I have the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſiſted, becauſe the hot Sons of the Church, by adheering over zealouſly to <hi>ſignificant Ceremonies</hi> which are conſidered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their being in their own nature indifferent, as very harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, do but open the way to the letting in an over-running flood of <hi>Popiſh Ceremonies,</hi> againſt which the <hi>Zealots</hi> for Ceremonies have nothing to offer, becauſe the Ceremonies they impoſe, are in their own nature indifferent and very ſignificant, inſtructive of good Doctrine, ſtirring up the peoples dull minds to their duty,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:56725:39"/>
and enjoyned by publick Authority, but of this more in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons againſt the appropriating humane ſignificant Ceremonies to the worſhip of God; The which I'll give the Reader out of the <hi>Abridgment,</hi> the Authors of which aſſert them to be <hi>unlawfull,</hi> becauſe;</p>
               <p n="1">1. <q>The Second Commandment forbids us to make to our ſelves the <hi>likeneſs</hi> of any thing whatſoever, for Religious uſe. And ſo is this Commandment underſtood by <hi>Bucer, Virell,</hi> Dr. <hi>Fulk,</hi> and others.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <q>Chriſt is the only Teacher of his Church, and appointer of all means, whereby we ſhould be taught, and admoniſhed of any Holy Duty, and whatſoever he hath thought good to teach his Church, and the means whereby he hath perfectly ſet down in the Holy Scriptures, ſo that to acknowledge any other means of teaching, and Admoniſhing us of our duty, than ſuch as he hath appointed, is to receive another Teacher into the Church beſides him, and to confeſs ſome imperfection in thoſe Means he hath ordained to teach us by. Our Saviour by this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (amongſt others) Condemns the Jewiſh purifyings and and Juſtifieth himſelf and his Diſciples in refuſing that Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, becauſe (being the precept of men) it was taught and uſed as a Doctrine by way of ſignification to teach what inward puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhould be in them, and how they ought to be cleanſed from the pollutions of the Heathen. And ſo we find this place inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted by <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> (whoſe Judgment alſo is alleadged and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by Dr. <hi>Whitaker)</hi> the Church of <hi>Wittemberge Calvin, Virell, Zeipperus,</hi> Dr. <hi>Fulke,</hi> Dr. <hi>Reinolds</hi> and others. This Reaſon we find alleadged by ſuch Divines as have been of chief credit in the Church of Chriſt, namely. Mr. <hi>Calvin, Chemnitius, Lavater.</hi> Dr. <hi>Fulke,</hi> and others. So to them that ſay Images may ſtand in Churches as helps to ſtir up Devotion, and to put Men in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of good things; It is anſwered (by <hi>Peter Martyr, Gualier, Lavater, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus, Polanus,</hi> and others) that the Lord himſelf hath appointed means enough to do that; and that no means may be uſed to that end, but ſuch as he hath Ordained. So the Churches of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Flanders</hi> in their Obſervations upon the harmony of Confeſſions gives this Reaſon againſt all <hi>Myſtical Ceremonies,</hi> that they are parts of the Holy Doctrine, and Dr. <hi>Andrews</hi> alleadgeth this for the firſt Root of all Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Idolatry, that men thought they would never have
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:56725:39"/>
admonitions and helps enough to ſtir them up to VVorſhip God, yet God <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> had given four means, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Word writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,</hi> the <hi>Word Preached, the Sacraments,</hi> and the <hi>great Book of the Creatures.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <q>This gives unto Ceremonies a chief part of the Nature of Sacraments, when they are appointed to teach or Admoniſh us by their Signification. This is affirmed and given as a reaſon againſt Significant Ceremonies, by <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> the Churches of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi> in their Obſervations upon the harmony of Confeſſions, <hi>Calvin, Martyr, Beza, Sadcel, Danaeus, Zepperus, Polanus,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Jewel,</hi> Dr. <hi>Humfry,</hi> and others.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <q>In the time of the Law, (when God ſaw it good to teach his Church by ſignificant Ceremonies) none might be brought into, or received in the Worſhip of God, but ſuch only as the Lord himſelf did inſtitute. This reaſon is uſed againſt the Popiſh Ceremonies by <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>alvin, Junius, Lubbertus,</hi> and others.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <q>It is much leſs lawful for man to bring ſignificant Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies into Gods Worſhip now, than it was Under the Law. For God hath abrogated his own, not only thoſe that were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to prefigure Chriſt, but ſuch alſo as ſerved by their ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification to teach moral Duties, ſo as now (without great Sin) none of them can be continued in the Church, no not for ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Of this Judgment were the Fathers in the Councel of <hi>Nice</hi> and <hi>Auſtin, Martyr, Bullinger, Lavater, Hoſpinian, Piſcator, Cooper,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Weſtphaling,</hi> and others.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>And if thoſe Ceremonies that God himſelf ordained to teach his Church by their ſignification may not now be uſed, much leſs may thoſe which man hath deviſed. This Reaſon our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines hold to be ſtrong againſt Popiſh Ceremonies, namely <hi>Calvin, Bullinger, Hoſpinian, Arcularius, Virell,</hi> Dr. <hi>Bilſon,</hi> Dr. <hi>Rainolds,</hi> Dr. <hi>Willet, and others. Yea,</hi> this is one main Difference which God hath put between the State of that Church under the Law, and this under the Goſpel, that he thought good to teach that by other myſtical Ceremonies, beſides the ordinary Sacraments, and not this. And of this Judgment is <hi>Calvin, Bullenger, Chemnitius, Danaeus, Hoſpinian, Arucularius,</hi> our book of <hi>Homilies,</hi> Dr. <hi>Humfrey,</hi> Dr. <hi>Rainolds,</hi> Dr. <hi>Willet,</hi> and others. All which Divines do teach that to bring inſignificant Ceremonies into the Church of Chriſt is plain Judaiſm. Beſides this, 'tis a ſpecial part of that <hi>Chriſtian Liberty</hi> which Chriſt
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:56725:40"/>
hath purchaſed for us by his death, and that which all Chriſtians are bound to ſtand for: that the Service we are to do unto God now, is not myſtical, Ceremonial, and Carnal (as it was then) but plain and ſpiritual. And of this Judgment were the Divines within the Territories of <hi>Hamborough)</hi> in an Epiſtle they wrote to <hi>Mèlancthon)</hi> and <hi>Virel, Piſcator,</hi> Dr. <hi>Rainolds,</hi> and others.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <q>This will open a Gap to <hi>Images, Oyl, Lights, and Spittle, Cream,</hi> and all <hi>other Popiſh Ceremonies,</hi> eſpecially if they ſhall be judged as fit to Teach and Admoniſh by their ſignification, as theſe which we retain. And indeed this is a chief Reaſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by both Papiſts and Lutherans juſtifie the Uſe of Images; and whereby <hi>Bellarmine</hi> commendeth all other their Ceremonies, that <hi>they are fit to teach and put men in remembrance of good things.</hi> The Popiſh Cuſtome of the Prieſts ſprinkling men with Holy Water, and uſing with all theſe words, <hi>Remember thy Baptiſm,</hi> (as their manner was in ſome Countries can with no reaſon be held for Unlawful, if ſuch ſignificant Ceremonies as ours are to be defended. <hi>With ſuch Reſpects and Relations, Remembrances and Apprehenſions</hi> (ſaith Dr. <hi>Fulke)</hi> all Idolatry and falſe Worſhip may be defended.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <q>VVe are further confirmed in this our Argument by the Judgment of the Godly Learned, who, (beſides the Teſtimony they have given to every ſeveral proof we have brought for it) do alſo ſpeak directly with us in this General. <hi>That no Myſtical and ſignificant Ceremony deviſed by Man, and appropriated to Gods Service may be retained in the Church of Chriſt.</hi> Of this judgment is the Church of <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> the Churches of <hi>France,</hi> and the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> in their Obſervations upon the Harmony of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> Mr. <hi>Beza,</hi> Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> and others. Yea, Dr. <hi>Whitgift</hi> himſelf profeſſeth, that <hi>he did not like that any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript Apparel ſhould be uſed in Gods Service</hi> for <hi>Signification.</hi> And no good reaſon can be given why the Church may not as well enjoyn a preſcript Apparel for ſignification, as any other Ceremony.</q>
               </p>
               <p>To all which I'le add one Argumentative Conſideration which the <hi>Church of England</hi> doth afford us, which is given in their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Ceremonies before the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> as a reaſon why they did put away any of thoſe many Ceremonies, with which the Church was burthen'd, which reaſon is diſtinct from that of their <hi>Multitudes,</hi> and 'tis taken from their <hi>ſignificancy,</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:56725:40"/>
and the <hi>likeneſs they had with thoſe in uſe among the Jewes,</hi> on which account they were not ſuited to the Goſpel Diſpenſation. After mention is made of the great exceſs and Multitude of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies in the dayes of Popery, they add, <q>And beſides this, Chriſt's Goſpel is not a Ceremonial Law (as much of <hi>Moſes</hi> Law was) but it is a Religion to ſerve God not in Bondage of the <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure,</hi> [i. e. <hi>ſignificant Ceremony]</hi> or Shadow, but in the <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of the Spirit.</q> As if it had been ſaid a great part of Goſpel Liberty conſiſts in being freed from thoſe ſignificant Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, which are not <hi>now</hi> of Gods appointment, Theſe words do ſeem to ſuggeſt that one reaſon of the aboliſhing the ſignificant Ceremonies of the Papiſts was becauſe they being ſignificant, were ſo like unto the Jewiſh Service, and ſo different from the Goſpel State, and ſuch as have been ſo much abus'd to Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that 'twas not eaſie to retain the Ceremony, and abandon the Superſtition.</p>
               <p>This being the Senſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſeeing the Ceremonies retained are of the <hi>ſame ſignificant,</hi> or Jewiſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, with thoſe aboliſhed, that have been as much abus'd to Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, as others, and have no other Foundation than Mans VVit and VVill for their ſupport, why were not <hi>theſe,</hi> that are left, rejected for the ſame reaſon, <hi>thoſe</hi> ſtill retained by the Papiſts have been. If you'l argue from the ſignificancy, the likeneſs that is between Popiſh Ceremonies, and the Jewiſh; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reject 'em, ſeeing the Engliſh are of the ſame kind, is not the Argument as ſtrong againſt them. Is not a Surplice as like the Jewiſh Garment, as ſome of the Popiſh Rights are to the Jewiſh Ceremonies; why then ſhall the one be aboliſhed, becauſe of that <hi>likeneſs,</hi> and the other kept, or, if their being abus'd to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, and the Difficulty of ſeparating the Superſtitious abuſe from the uſeing 'em be ſufficient to aboliſh the Rites of <hi>Salt,</hi> and <hi>Spittle,</hi> Lights, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> why not as ſufficient for the aboliſhing the <hi>Surplice,</hi> the <hi>Sign</hi> of the <hi>Croſs in Baptiſm. Kneeling at the Lords Supper, Bowing at the name of Jeſus:</hi> Have not all theſe been as much abus'd to Superſtition, and ſtill are as any of the reſt, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally conſidering what Diviſions they have made in the Church, why not then aboliſh'd? Or if it be a ſin to conform to the Popiſh Rites, How a Duty to Conform to theſe that of the ſame kind with 'em? Or, if theſe without Sin may be appropriated to Gods VVorſhip by Proteſtants, which may not the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> where they
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:56725:41"/>
have Authority by their Impoſitions, impoſe 'em on the people as in <hi>France,</hi> &amp;c. and appropriate 'em to God's VVorſhip?</p>
               <p>Methinks Mr. <hi>Greenham</hi> expreſſeth himſelf very full on this particular in his Anſwer unto the <hi>Biſhops of Ely,</hi> as 'tis in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter.</hi> 
                  <q>If your VViſdom think (ſays he) that I deceive my ſelf in my Suppoſition, for that in <hi>Lutheraniſm</hi> more and worſe abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes be maintained, I anſwer, (that Conſubſtantiation excepted) they be all <hi>ejuſdem generis</hi> of the like kind.</q> [This he ſpeaks of the Ceremonies of the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> who keep up <hi>Images,</hi> compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring 'em with our Ceremonies] ſeeing they are not retained <q>
                     <hi>ad Cultum Dei,</hi> to the VVorſhip of God, but as they ſay, <hi>Ad Aedificationem, Decorum, et Ordinem Eccleſiae</hi> to Edification, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and differ only from us <hi>ſecundum Majus, &amp; Minus,</hi> as great things and leſs, Therefore as more and worſe Ceremonies are <hi>leſs</hi> to be tolerated, ſo no more are the fewer, or leſſer evils to be allowed, and as you and other good men have great Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences in the Multitude of Ceremonies I beſeech you to think, that I, and others may have ſome Conſciences in the fewer ſort, when they be of the <hi>like nature</hi> with others.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Seeing what has been ſaid doth ſufficiently prove the unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Ceremonies in the judgment of many a Diſſenter, they are afraid to Comply with (or joyn with any in) the uſe of thoſe Ceremonies. They are fully convinc'd, they ſhould ſin if they did, the which they durſt not do, leaſt they provoke God to jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie.</p>
               <p>There are in the VVritings of the <hi>Old Non-Conformiſts</hi> ſuch a multitude of weighty Arguments againſt the Lawfulneſs of the Ceremonies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that a giving the Reader all would take up a very large Volume, but 'tis not my buſineſs to inſiſt on all that may be offer'd, I'le therefore cloſe with this one Argument.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="argument">
               <head>
                  <hi>Argument</hi> VI.</head>
               <p>Notwithſtanding the great Cry that has been made about the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Service,</hi> and the reaſonableneſs of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming unto it, for that reaſon, ſome Diſſenters refuſe to joyn in the uſe of it, becauſe ſuch a practice is not agreeable to the <hi>beſt Antiquity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They think that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were beſt acquainted with the Mind and VVit of Jeſus Chriſt, and that the <hi>Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:56725:41"/>
in the <hi>Firſt, Second</hi> and <hi>Third Centuries</hi> kept more exactly to the Rule of Chriſt than thoſe, who lived in the <hi>Fourth, Fifth, Sixth,</hi> or <hi>Seventh, &amp;c.</hi> whence the Antiquity the Diſſenter pleads for is that which is <hi>moſt Ancient,</hi> and <hi>moſt pure,</hi> unto which pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern ſuch as will aim at a thorough Reformation, muſt attempt the reducing all things in matters of Religion.</p>
               <p>'Tis generally agreed by all Proteſtants, that in the Apoſtolical and moſt Primitive Dayes of the Goſpel all things were moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly conformed to the VVill of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and that the nearer any keep to his Rule, the better. A Deviating from the <hi>Primitive practice</hi> has been but the beginning of all thoſe many corruptions that have infeſted the Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Seeing this is a truth acknowledged by moſt, let us enquire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>Antiquity of ſuch Liturgies</hi> as this in uſe among us, and after the <hi>time when</hi> Liturgies were firſt impoſed, and from <hi>whom</hi> and <hi>when</hi> the preſent <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liturgy had its riſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. From what has been already ſuggeſted, 'tis manifeſt <hi>That there were no ſtinted Liturgies impos'd on any Paſtors of particular Churches,</hi> the <hi>Firſt Four Hundred years after Chriſt.</hi> The which may be be further confirm'd out of what Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> in the <hi>Second part of the Hiſtory of the Reformation</hi> doth acknowledge, who, ſpeaking of Liturgies, doth ſay, <q>That they were not made the Subject of any publick Conſultation till St. <hi>Auſtins</hi> time; when in their Dealings with Hereticks, they found they took advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages from ſome of the Prayers, that were in ſome Churches. Upon this, he tells us, it was order'd, that there ſhould be <hi>no Prayers</hi> uſed in the Church, but upon common Advice. After that the <hi>Liturgie</hi> came to be more carefully confidered. <hi>Formerly</hi> the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of God was <hi>a pure,</hi> and <hi>ſimple thing,</hi> and ſo it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued till Superſtition had ſo infected the Church, that thoſe Formes were thought too naked, unleſs they were put under more Artificial Rules, and dreſſed up with much Ceremony, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> So far Dr. <hi>Burnet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About this time, which was in the <hi>Fourth Century</hi> St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> compos'd his Service Book, which was the firſt that gained any confiderable Reputation in the VVorld. The Spurious Liturgies that are aſcribed unto the Apoſtles are ſuch, as have enough in 'em to convince the <hi>Reader,</hi> that they were not ſo ancient as is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. After this time the Paſtors, or Biſhops of Churches were very buſie in compoſing Prayers, in making Additions to
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:56725:42"/>
what was done by ſuch as went before 'em. But no Liturgie as yet impos'd on any Churches, Every Paſtor, tho' he communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated the prayers he had compoſed for his own uſe unto others (The which he did only for the ſatisfaction of his Brethren that they might be aſſur'd, there was nothing of Error in 'em) yet none impos'd. 'Tis very probable that St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>'s Liturgie in Divers places finding Acceptance was much in uſe: But 'tis moſt certain, that until <hi>Pope Adrian</hi> the firſt, who liv'd in the <hi>Eighth Century</hi> there was no general Impoſition of any Liturgie.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Petries</hi> Church Hiſtory 'tis ſtoryed. <q>That about the later end of the <hi>Eighth Century,</hi> there was a great contention for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the <hi>Maſs of Pope Gregory</hi> into the Churches, firſt by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Pope <hi>Adrian,</hi> and then of <hi>Charles</hi> the Great; ſome Churches had one Directory, and ſome another, who would not change, VVhen the <hi>Pope</hi> ſaw ſo great Oppoſition (and it may be underſtood, that it was not ſmall, when the Pope was put to ſuch a ſhift) he ſaid he would refer it to the VVill of God, whither he would by any viſible ſign approve the Maſs of <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> or <hi>Ambroſe:</hi> ſo theſe two Books were laid together upon the Altar in St. <hi>Peters</hi> Church, and he cal'd upon God which of the Two he approved. The Doors were ſhut all Night, and the next Morning, when they were return'd into the Church, the Book of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> was found lying as it was laid down, and the other was all torn and diſperſed through the Church. The Pope maketh the Comment (if we will belive <hi>Jacob de Voragine in Vita Gregorij)</hi> That the <hi>Maſs</hi> of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſhould be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touch'd, and the <hi>Maſs</hi> of <hi>Gregory</hi> ſhould be uſed through the VVorld, and ſo he did Authorize and Command that it ſhould be uſed in all Churches, and Chappels. But many did expound that ſign the contrary way, and would not receive it, till <hi>Charles</hi> did command all Biſhops and Prieſts to uſe it through his Dominions, he cauſed the <hi>Maſs of Ambroſe</hi> to be burned and threw many Prieſts into Priſon, who refuſed to accept the new Maſs [or <hi>Pope Gregories Liturgy]</hi> The Church of <hi>Millaine</hi> would not change. <hi>Walifred Strabo</hi> (who lived about the year 900) teſtifieth in his Book <hi>de Exordijs rerum</hi> cap. 25. That in his time the Roman Maſs was not univerſally in all Churches, but almoſt (ſaith he) in all the Churches of the Latines, and no <hi>Benedictine</hi> Monks did read it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> Thus <hi>Adrian</hi> the Pope, and <hi>Charles</hi> the Emperour were the firſt hot Zealots for <hi>Gregories
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:56725:42"/>
Liturgy,</hi> who were much more fond of it, than <hi>Gregory</hi> himſel<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was, for <hi>Gregory</hi> did as much deteſt the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Impoſition,</hi> as he did zealouſly reject the <hi>Title</hi> of an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Biſhop,</hi> whence he was not fond of impoſing it on us in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis very certain that the Chriſtian Religion did many an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years flouriſh in <hi>this Kingdom</hi> before 'twas troubled with a <hi>Romiſh Liturgie,</hi> which came not hither till about the year 600, and then rejected by the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Chriſtians, who ſeverely ſuffer'd for their refuſing to comply with the prelatick Impoſitions of that proud Monk <hi>Auſtine,</hi> who, ſtirring up the King of <hi>Kent</hi> to fight againſt the Chriſtians, thereby to bring 'em, if poſſible, to a complyance with his Ceremonies, was the cauſe of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of above a Thouſand Godly Monks, beſides the many others who were cruelly ſlain at that time. The which <hi>Auſtin</hi> moſt wretchedly did, tho' he never receiv'd any ſuch advice from <hi>Gregory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An account of Pope <hi>Gregories</hi> Moderation we have in Dr: <hi>Burnet,</hi> who gives us alſo a ſhort Hiſtory of the Riſe and Progreſs of Ceremonies thus. <q>
                     <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great was the firſt, that took much care to make the Church Muſick very regular, and he did alſo put the Liturgies in another Method, than had been former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed. Yet he had no <hi>ſuch fondneſs of his own Compoſures.</hi> But left it to <hi>Auſtine</hi> the Monk, whom he ſent over into <hi>England,</hi> when he conſulted him in it, either to uſe the <hi>Roman,</hi> or the <hi>French</hi> Rituals, or any other, as he ſhould find they were moſt likely to edifie the people. [But] After this there were great variations; for as any Prelate came to be Canonized, or held in high eſteem by the people; ſome private <hi>Collects,</hi> or particular Forms, that he had uſed, were practiſed in his, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps as his Fame, ſpread in the Neighbouring Dioceſs.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the Liturgie as it's firſt <hi>riſe</hi> was in <hi>Auſtine</hi>'s time, or thereabout, which was occaſioned by the Errors that then did infeſt the Churches, at which time the Miniſters would vent their Errors in their very Prayers, even ſo by degrees it received re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Additions, ſome part brought in at one time, and ſome at another. So ſays Dr. <hi>Burnet.</hi> 
                  <q>In every Age there were <hi>nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Additions</hi> made, and all Writers allmoſt in the Eighth and Ninth Centuries employed their Fancies to find out <hi>Myſtical Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifications,</hi> for every Rite, that was then uſed; and ſo as a new Rite was added, it was no hard matter to add ſome Myſtery to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:56725:43"/>
it. This had made the Office ſwell out of meaſure, and there was a great variety of them, <hi>Miſſals, Breviaries, Rituals, Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificals, Portoiſes, Pies, Graduals, Antiphorals, Pſalteries, Hours,</hi> and a great many more.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Out of theſe was the <hi>Engliſh Service</hi> taken, which as it had no higher Riſe than that of <hi>Gregorie</hi>'s or at moſt <hi>Ambroſe</hi>'s Liturgy, in like manner it was a <hi>Compoſition of time,</hi> the Remaining parts having different Fathers, ſome hundred years younger than the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>This I'le evince particularly out of <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> who (as his Intereſt prompted him) made diligent ſearch after the Antiquity of the ſeveral parts of the <hi>Romiſh Service Book.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The Verſicle, <hi>Glory to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Ghoſt</hi> was as <hi>Alcuinus</hi> thought Compoſed by St. <hi>Hierome</hi> at the requeſt of Pope <hi>Damaſus,</hi> But as <hi>Walfrid Strabo,</hi> 'twas compoſed by the <hi>Nycene Council</hi> ſometime before <hi>Hierome,</hi> it may be to ſhew their Deteſtation to the <hi>Arrian</hi> Hereſie, which was ſome hundred years after Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Kyrie Eleiſon</hi> (i. e.) <hi>Lord have mercy on us,</hi> is fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuppoſed to be us'd ever ſince the Apoſtles days, becauſe 'tis found in St. <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>feigned Liturgy,</hi> but <hi>Bellarmine</hi> cannot ſay that 'twas us'd in the <hi>Roman Liturgy</hi> Two Hundred years before <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great who liv'd about the year 600.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Dominus Vobiſcum,</hi> or the <hi>Lord be with you,</hi> An ancient Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutation, us'd by Believers in the Old Teſtament times, about which <hi>Petrus Damianus</hi> wrote a Book with this Title, <hi>Dominus vobiſcum.</hi> Tho' this was an ancient Salutation in uſe among old Believers, when they met one another, yet we have no evidence, that 'twas brought into the Liturgie as a part of ſolemn and ſet Worſhip until the firſt Council at <hi>Bracca,</hi> Can. 21. enjoyn'd it the Biſhops and Prieſts.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The <hi>Collects,</hi> which <hi>were the ſhort Prayers</hi> of ſeveral <hi>Popes</hi> and others Cannoniz'd for Saints, were brought into the Liturgy by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> almoſt 600 years after Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The <hi>Te Deum Laudamus,</hi> or that <hi>Hymn</hi> which begins thus. We praiſe thee O God, tho' it be not found in the Sacred Scriptures, yet 'twas (ſaith <hi>Bellarmine)</hi> given the Church by <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration</hi> at the <hi>Baptiſm</hi> of St. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> at which time St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> and St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> did <hi>extempore,</hi> and alternately to the Aſtoniſhment of the people ſing this Hymne, as <hi>Dacius Epiſcopus Mediolanenſis</hi> reports.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:56725:43"/>
6. After the <hi>Leſſons,</hi> the <hi>Reſponſes,</hi> which are ſo call'd, ſaies <hi>Rabanus,</hi> becauſe one who begins is anſwer'd by the reſt, were firſt invented by the <hi>Italian Churches,</hi> was not within ſeveral hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years after Chriſt.</p>
               <p>By theſe Intimations concerning the Antiquity of ſome parts of the Engliſh Service 'tis evident, That as all ſtinted Liturgies com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the moſt primitive practices are <hi>new,</hi> ſo our <hi>Liturgie,</hi> which was taken out of <hi>Gregories,</hi> A Liturgie not ſo ancient, as that of <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and which in proceſs of time was ſtrangely alter'd is much more <hi>new,</hi> unto which the Diſſenters cannot firmly adhere, if they will as they think they ought, make the <hi>moſt Primitive Practice</hi> the pattern and Rule of theirs.</p>
               <p>What need any other Impoſitions on the Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, or on the people <hi>now,</hi> than were on 'em the firſt 300 years? And why ſhall we be wiſer than our firſt Fore-Fathers? Is it not a duty to have a juſt reſpect to Antiquity? Why not then to that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity that comes neareſt unto the Apoſtles days? Whatever ſome may think, there are many among the Diſſenters, who are fully perſwaded that untill all things in Religion be reduc'd to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Conſtitution eſtabliſhed by the Lord Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, adher'd unto by thoſe who for ſome hundred years followed 'em, the Church of God will never flouriſh.</p>
               <p>This is the Rule they muſt walk by, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or Sin againſt God, to avoid which Sin, they refuſe to joyn with the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in her Liturgie, that is ſo <hi>beſide</hi> the practice of the Primitive Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>Let theſe few of the many Arguments, which the Diſſenters have offered againſt the <hi>lawfulneſs of the Engliſh Liturgy</hi> ſatisfie the Reader, On this I have the more fully inſiſted to the end thoſe <hi>Sober Conformiſts,</hi> who it may be have not conſidered the Reaſons why the Diſſenters cannot conform to the Engliſh Liturgie may ſee thas 'tis not <hi>Honnour,</hi> nor <hi>Fancy,</hi> but <hi>Conſcience,</hi> that is the ground of their Non-Conformity.</p>
               <p>I'm very Confident, that a great part of the Diſſenters (I ſpeak not of all becauſe I know 'em not) would with all their Hearts Conform to all is requir'd of 'em by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> could they do it with a ſafe Conſcience, and ſurely, ſuch among the Conformiſts, who will conſider theſe Reaſonings of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, and who do not meaſure the Conſciences of other Men by the Light and Latitude of their own, cannot but conclude,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:56725:44"/>
that <hi>there are ſome Nonconformiſts who cannot with a ſafe conſcience conform,</hi> but ſhould they do it, 'twould be againſt <hi>the plain convic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of conſciences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As 'tis not <hi>humour</hi> nor <hi>fancy</hi> that occaſions their Diſſent from the Church, ſo 'tis more than <hi>meer ſcruple of conſcience.</hi> Theſe Diſſenters are under <hi>ſtrong convictions</hi> of Conſcience, that they ſin, if they conform; This is certainly the caſe of many, who are as fully perſwaded, that the Conformiſts do err, as the Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt can be that they do ſo.</p>
               <p>This being their caſe, the queſtion is, <hi>whether</hi> notwithſtanding theſe <hi>plain convictions</hi> of Conſcience, they muſt conform, and <hi>act contrary to their convictions? Whether they may ſafely ſin againſt God, to the end they may render the Obedience required by man?</hi> It hath been heretofore aſſerted by all ſorts of Chriſtians, whether Proteſtant or Papiſt. 1. That <hi>God muſt be obeyed rather than man;</hi> And, 2. <hi>That no authority is ſufficient to oblige any to act contrary to the plain convictions of Conſcience.</hi> Yea <hi>Medina</hi> himſelf doth aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, that a man muſt rather obey an <hi>erroneous</hi> Conſcience, than the command of any Prelate, that is contradictory thereunto.</p>
               <p>Suppoſing theſe Diſſenters do err, yet they muſt not act contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unto an erroneous Conſcience, the whole that can be juſtly deſir'd is, that they uſe all regular means to depoſe and ſhake off the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of Conſcience, which muſt be done by a ſincere ſeeking God for more light, that they may come to the knowledge of the truth, and by a diligent and impartial enquiry into the true State of the controverſie; Moreover, there muſt be if poſſible, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting the writings of the Learned on both ſides, or a converſing with 'em, with a readyneſs to weigh all things with deliberation, and a reſolution to embrace the truth, where ever 'tis found; But if after all their old convictions are rather ſtrengthned than other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, they muſt beware they act not contrary to their Conſcience. They muſt not reſign up their reaſon, their Conſcience, nor their Religion unto the pleaſure of the greateſt Potentate on Earth. <hi>This</hi> I take to be the Doctrine of all <hi>ſound Proteſtants of the Church of England,</hi> yea I can, when there ſhall be an occaſion, prove it to be ſo by a Collection of the ſeveral Arguments of the Learned Drs. of the Church, which they have urg'd for the confirmation of this truth, in the oppoſition they make to the <hi>blind obedience</hi> of the Papiſt. Whence I inferr.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That theſe Diſſenters in refuſing to joyn with the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:56725:44"/>
in the Liturgy, do but diſcharge their duty unto God.</hi> Their not joyning with the Church is not the ſin of <hi>Schiſm; Schiſm</hi> is aſſerted by Proteſtants to be a <hi>cauſleſs ſeparation,</hi> whence if there be a good cauſe why they ſeparate, 'tis not cauſeleſs, and can there be a better cauſe than the avoiding ſin? They ſeparate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſhould ſin if they did not ſeparate.</p>
               <p>But though this be enough to clear the Diſſenter, who is fully convinc'd of the unlawfulneſs of thoſe Termes of Communion that are impoſed on the people, yet 'tis not enough to juſtifie the ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of thoſe, who do not only think it lawfull, but <hi>expedient</hi> to joyn with the Church of <hi>England</hi> in their Prayers and Ceremonies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who if they will ſeparate from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and juſtifie their ſeparation, they muſt argue from other Topicks, for certainly the peace of the Church, and the authority of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, cannot but engage a people to do what is both lawfull and expedient.</p>
               <p>Theſe therefore (I think) deny, that they ſeparate from the Communion of the Church. Although they worſhip God in Meetings, locally diſtant from the Pariſh Church, yet their Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are but as Chappels of Eaſe, and the Preachers but as Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates to the Pariſh Churches.</p>
               <p>That the Epiſcopal Party may effectually demonſtrate a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Aſſembly <hi>locally diſtant</hi> from the Pariſh Church to be Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, they muſt prove.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That the people of this Aſſembly were once actually Members of the Pariſh Churches.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>That theſe people do ordinarily ſeparate themſelves from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Communion of their Pariſh Churches.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>That their ſeparation is cauſleſs.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Firſt, They muſt prove, <hi>that the people of this Aſſembly, that is locally diſtant from the Pariſh Church, were</hi> once <hi>Members of the Pariſh Church,</hi> that they were under an obligation of holding ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Communion with their Pariſhes.</p>
               <p n="1">1. All <hi>External Communion</hi> muſt be in Pariſh Aſſemblys, or ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Congregational Churches; For a Dioceſan, Provincial or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Aſſembly of all the Members of thoſe Societies for Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Communion, is, on the account of the multitude of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, impoſſible, 'tis impoſſible they ſhould meet in one and the ſame Aſſembly, and hold Communion with each other in Prayers, in the Word, and in the Sacrament; Their External Communion
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:56725:45"/>
in Prayers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> muſt be in leſſer Aſſemblies, or not at all.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Thoſe who are under any Obligations of holding external Communion with this, or the other Pariſh muſt be Members of this or the other Pariſh Church. Such as are not Members of this or the other Pariſh Church, cannot be ſaid to ſeparate from it, tho' they meet in places <hi>locally diſtant,</hi> becauſe they not being Members of the Pariſh Church, are not under any Obligation of holding external Communion with <hi>that</hi> Pariſh, <hi>A Man</hi> (ſaies Dr. <hi>Stilling fleet) is not ſaid to ſeparate from every Church, where he forbears or ceaſes to have Communion, but only from that Church with which he is obliged to hold Communion, and yet withdraws from it,</hi> This ſufficiently evinces, That unleſs the Conformiſts can prove that the Diſſenters were <hi>oblig'd</hi> to hold Communion, as Members of the <hi>Pariſh Churches,</hi> they cannot prove a Separation. To ſeparate from a Church doth ſuppoſe, that perſon to have been once of that Church.</p>
               <p>But the Quaerie is, how the Conformiſts will prove all the Diſſenters to be Members of ſome particular Pariſh Church? Will they ſay that they were all made Members of ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Pariſh Church by their <hi>Baptiſme?</hi> That cannot be, becauſe by Baptiſm we are only made Members of the Catholick Church. Doth our being born <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men, and our Inhabiting in ſuch a Pariſh make us Members of the Pariſh Church? No, for there are no Grounds in Scripture for this, Our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, nor his Apoſtles did not leave any Intimations concerning ſuch a Rule, neither can any precept, but what is fetch from God's word, faſten any ſuch Obligation on the Conſcience, that whoever lives within ſuch a precinct muſt be a Member of ſuch a Church, How then muſt it be? The Anſwer of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and the Primitive Chriſtians for the firſt 300 years, and of moſt Proteſtants, is full for this, which is, <hi>That it muſt be by the peoples conſent.</hi> For as the people are inveſted with a Right to choſe their own Paſtor and the Church with which they would hold Communion. Even ſo they cannot be Members nor under any Obligation of holding Ordinary Communion with this, or the other particular Church without their own <hi>conſent.</hi> Conſent is as abſolutely neceſſary to the conſtituting a particular Pariſh Church, as a National, which conſent may be diſcovered not only <hi>Expreſly,</hi> but alſo <hi>implicitly,</hi> which is when a people do ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly joyn with ſome particular Church in all Ordinances, as many
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:56725:45"/>
Pariſhioners, who, by their Ordinary holding Communion with the Pariſh Church in all Ordinances, do <hi>practically,</hi> and <hi>interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatively</hi> (though not expreſly) diſcover their conſent to be of that Church, whereby (I think) they are under an Obligation to conſtant Communion with that Pariſh Church ſo long as they find it lawful: Tho' theſe may <hi>Occaſionally</hi> hold Communion elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, yet their ordinary, and conſtant Communion muſt be with their Pariſh Church. For which reaſon, if they do ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily forbear, or ceaſe to have Communion with their Pariſh-Church, it may be juſtly ſaid, that they do ſeparate from it.</p>
               <p>But there are many an Inhabitant in moſt Pariſhes, who, as they were not made Members of the Pariſh Church by <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> nor can be by meer <hi>Cohabitation,</hi> even ſo they never were by their own <hi>Conſent,</hi> either <hi>expreſly,</hi> or <hi>interpretatively.</hi> They never held Communion with the Church of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>all Ordinances,</hi> were never confirm'd by the Biſhops, nor ever did participate of the Lord's Supper, and therefore I think it cannot be truly ſaid, That they <hi>Separate.</hi> How can they ceaſe that Communion which they never had? For which reaſon to prove theſe <hi>Schiſmatical Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiſts,</hi> who never ſeparated from the Church, ſeems an Impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility. Surely their exerciſe of that Right, and Power, with which they are inveſted as Chriſtians in choſing their own Paſtor, cannot be an Act <hi>Schiſmatical.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this 'tis manifeſt, That thoſe who never expreſly nor im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitly conſenting to hold communion with any Pariſh-Church in all Ordinances were never actually obliged to hold Communion with ſuch particular Pariſhes, and conſequently their forbearing ſuch Communion or their Aſſembling in places diſtant from the Pariſh Church cannot be a Separation, and if not a Separation, it cannot be a Schiſm.</p>
               <p>Thus the Reader may eaſily perceive how neceſſary 'tis, that the Conformiſts prove, that thoſe Diſſenters, who now meet in Aſſemblies <hi>locally diſtant</hi> from the Pariſh Churches, were once Members and under an Obligation of holding external Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the Pariſh Churches, if they will prove 'em <hi>Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> Furthermore they muſt prove.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That this <hi>people do</hi> ordinarily Separate <hi>themſelves from the external Communion of their Pariſh Church.</hi> For ſeeing the Sin of Schiſm conſiſts in <hi>cauſeleſs Separation,</hi> there muſt be a <hi>Separation,</hi> or there can be no <hi>cauſeleſs Separation,</hi> (that is) there can be no
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:56725:46"/>
Schiſm, but how the Conformiſt can prove a Separation any otherwiſe than by inſiſting on the people's, not holding Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the <hi>ſame manner,</hi> or <hi>ſame place</hi> with the Church, is difficult to ſuppoſe. And if they take either of their ways without the Addition of ſome other Conſideration, they muſt either make many of their own Meetings <hi>Separate,</hi> which are in places local<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſtant from the Pariſh Church, where their Modes of Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration are different, or clear many Diſſenters from the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of Separation, what do they think of ſuch Meetings in which the Common Prayer is read, are they Separate and Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical? But after they have prov'd both theſe, they cannot prove <hi>all Diſſenters</hi> Schiſmatical, unleſs they can alſo evince.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That the Separation is <hi>Cauſeleſs</hi> and <hi>Sinful,</hi> But how they can prove that thoſe who, if they ſeparate, do ſo on no other Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, than that they may <hi>forſake</hi> Sin is a point worthy of Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</p>
               <p>If there be any ſinful Impoſition made the term of Communion, 'tis ſufficient to juſtifie the Separation of thoſe, who withdraw themſelves from the external Communion of that Church. If a Church that is ſound in the Doctrine of Religion, though it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts an Idolatrous Worſhip, yet if it make the leaſt Sin the Term of Communion, whereby the people cannnot have Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with that Church but by a deliberate committing that Sin, Separation from the Communion of this Church is juſtifiable. For whatever ſome may ſuggeſt, we muſt not commit the leaſt Sin that good may come thereof.</p>
               <p>To inſiſt then ſo much on the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of the Church, as if it were a Good for the Obtaining which we might venture on a little Sin, is a Notion of a very dangerous Tendency, giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too great Countenance to a Doctrine of the Papiſts, whereby they juſtifie all their Villanies. A <hi>Little evil</hi> (ſay they) may be done for the Obtaining a great Good, for inſtance. The Salvation of the many Souls in Three Kingdoms is a great, a very great Good, the Killing One, Two, or Three Hereticks in order thereunto, at moſt is but a little evil which may be done for ſo great a good. Moreover this juſtifies all their <hi>Officious</hi> Lying and Equivocating, they tell a Lye that ſome great good may come thereof. But this is ſo contrary to the pure Nature of a Holy God, and his Holy, Good, and Juſt Command, that whoever will indulge himſelf in a practical embraceing ſuch a Notion, doth but prepare the greater Damnation for his own Soul.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:56725:46"/>
God is a great God, and the leaſt Sin being an Offence to his Dread Majeſty, cannot knowingly with deliberation and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance be committed, but the perſon that does it, expoſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to Divine Indignation; who ever <hi>breaketh the leaſt of theſe my Commands, ſays Chriſt.</hi> Matth. 5. 19. is in danger of looſing Heaven, for, <hi>though a man keep the whole Law,</hi> and <hi>yet offend</hi> in <hi>one point,</hi> he is <hi>guilty of all. James</hi> 2. 10. We muſt not ſpeak nor act wickedly for God, he is not glorified by Mans lye, and therefore <hi>Wo unto them that will do evil that good may come thereof. Rom.</hi> 3. 8. If the leaſt ſin be made the <hi>Term</hi> of Communion, no Conſideration of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> or of <hi>Obedience</hi> to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate can excuſe thoſe from guilt, that will venture on that ſin. Whence 'tis evident,</p>
               <p>That all thoſe who by the Reaſons inſiſted on in this Treatiſe are fully convinc'd, That <hi>ſomewhat ſinful is impoſed as a Term of Communion with the Church of England,</hi> they do but diſcharge their Duty, and keep a good Conſcience in ſeparating, and yet by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration do not accuſe the Church, as if ſhe had been no true Church, or as if Salvation could not by others be had in it. A Church that is ſound in the Faith, that 'tis a true Church in a <hi>Theological</hi> Senſe, being lyable to Error, may, even while Sound in the great things of Religion, impoſe ſome <hi>Error,</hi> as a <hi>Term</hi> of Communion, from which thoſe, who are convinc'd of the Sin, muſt ſeparate. A ſound Church in the great things, may <hi>err</hi> in leſſer matters, and may Impoſe Aſſent and Conſent unto that <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,</hi> as a <hi>Term</hi> of Communion, with the which theſe Diſſenters durſt not comply, but ſeeing they cannot have Communion on eaſier Terms, muſt ſeparate.</p>
               <p>There is a great Difference between the Errors or Corruptions of a Church which are made <hi>Terms</hi> of Communion, and thoſe which are <hi>not.</hi> 'Tis not to be queſtion'd, but that a man may joyn with a Church that is leſs pure than another, even with a Church that hath ſeveral Spots in it (or he muſt joyn with none) and may be under an Obligation of continuing with that Church, although he may go elſewhere and be better edifyed, otherwiſe there being <hi>variety of Gifts,</hi> thoſe who are more eminent than the reſt among the Miniſtery, muſt have moſt of the people round, when other honeſt, though not ſo able; Preachers have <hi>few,</hi> or <hi>none.</hi> However if they make the <hi>leaſt Spot,</hi> or <hi>Impurity</hi> a <hi>Term of Communion,</hi> he dares not comply. As long as he may
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:56725:47"/>
may continue Communion without being made a partaker of the impurities, (as in many inſtances he may) he muſt not ſeparate, but when they impoſe their corruptions as Termes of Communion, ſo that he cannot have Communion but by complying with the corruption, he muſt not ſin for the ſake of Communion, nor on any other conſideration whatſoever.</p>
               <p>But ſeeing they cannot hold Communion with the Pariſh-Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; The next great quaerie is, <hi>what they muſt do, whether live without ſome Ordinances all the dayes of their Life,</hi> or <hi>Aſſemble themſelves together for Communion in all Ordinances, in ſuch a way as they are fully convinc'd is agreable to the Sacred Scriptures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That they muſt not conſtantly neglect any Ordinance of God, nor the publick attendance on his worſhip, ſomewhere is ſo clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reveal'd in the word of God, that whoever is not ſo far in love with <hi>Quakeriſm,</hi> as to neglect the Teſtimony of God's written Word, cannot but acknowledge it; That the Lord Jeſus who has inſtituted a Miniſtry, and made it the peculiar work of ſome men in ſpecial to preach the Word, not only for <hi>converſion of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> but for the <hi>ediſication of the converted,</hi> for the help and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of whom there is inſtituted not the Ordinance of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> alone, but that of the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> which is deſign'd for the ſtrength and encreaſe of Grace in Chriſtians, I ſay this Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, who hath ſo graciouſly inſtituted a Miniſtry and Ordinances, hath made it the duty of Chriſtians to aſſemble themſelves toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to the end they may be made partakers of the Bleſſings of his Inſtitutions and Ordinances; And ſuch is the Relation between Miniſter and People, that is, between a Goſpel Miniſter, and an orderly Chriſtian Aſſembly, that the one cannot be without the other, neither can the one ordinarily perform ſome Relational Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but in an Aſſembly with the other, and therefore muſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble themſelves together, 'tis their duty.</p>
               <p>I cannot at preſent enlarge on this head, and therefore as to this I can only add, that the ſenſe of all Proteſtants generally is, that all Chriſtians ought to aſſemble themſelves together for publick worſhip; <hi>Viz.</hi> for Prayer, the Word and Sacraments, and that 'tis the duty of a Paſtor to take heed to himſelf, and the Flock over which he is made over-ſeer, and that 'tis the peoples duty to attend <hi>Ordinarily</hi> on the Miniſtry of their own Paſtor.</p>
               <p>The great <hi>difference</hi> between the Church of <hi>England</hi> and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, is not ſo much about the peoples duty of aſſembling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:56725:47"/>
together for publique worſhip, as about the place where, and the Miniſter with whom. The <hi>Church of England</hi> ſayes, it muſt be in the Pariſh Church with the Miniſter of the Pariſh, but the <hi>Diſſenter</hi> aſſerts, that every Chriſtian is inveſted with a right to chooſe his own Paſtor, and that therefore he muſt go where he finds the worſhip to be in a way moſt agreable to God's Holy word, but when he is once fix'd, he is under thoſe Obligations of Duty unto his Paſtor, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> do ſay, a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioner is unto the Miniſter of the Pariſh. But ſeeing on theſe things I cannot <hi>now</hi> enlarge, I will conclude with an humble and affectionate requeſt to all good Chriſtians, whether <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> or <hi>Diſſenter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I beſeech you to conſider, that conſcience is a tender thing, its wounds unſupportable, frequently accompanied with ſuch horror as is very like unto the pains and torments of the damned; No man therefore muſt act contrary to the plain convictions thereof. What man ſoever does, what he is convinc'd in Conſcience is a ſin, does greatly diſhonour and provoke Almighty God. All care muſt be taken to obtain the knowledge of the truth, and gain a freedom from error, but there muſt not be an acting againſt the plain convictions of conſcience, though erroneous.</p>
               <p>On this I inſiſt as a ſound part of the Proteſtant Doctrine, ſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuouſly defended againſt the many feeble aſſaults of the Papiſt, by ſeveral worthies of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> And really this is a Rule all good Chriſtians muſt walk by, in doing which, ſeeing there are almoſt as many <hi>different perſwaſions</hi> of conſcience about ſome leſſer things, as there are conſidering mindes, there will be as <hi>many different practices</hi> where there are different Sentiments about matters of practice, there the practice will be different, for which reaſon, the ſtrong muſt take heed that they deſpiſe not the weak, and the weak look to it that they judge not the ſtrong; For whether we conform, or conform not, if we do what we do conſcientiouſly to the Lord, we ſhall be accepted of him.</p>
               <p>I verily believe that many do think themſelves bound in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to conform, the which they would not do to gain a world, if they did think it a ſin, and 'tis as true, that many among the Diſſenters are as conſcientiouſly Non-conformiſts, and would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally have conform'd, did they not think that ſo conforming they ſhould ſin againſt God. Both theſe muſt be tenderly regarded by ſuch as will walk by the Chriſtian Rule; A Non-conformiſts cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:56725:48"/>
a conformiſt as one that acts againſt his conſcience is unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and a Conformiſt's cenſuring all Diſſenters as Hypocrites, looking on their conſcience to be but fancy, their Religion to be faction, is no leſs unchriſtian than the former. But to be more particular, my humble deſire is,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That thoſe who are of the Communion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> would continue it ſo long as they can with a ſafe conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Let not every little diſſatisfaction with ſome men drive you off from thoſe wayes you have nothing, beſide the miſcarriage of ſome men of that profeſſion, to object againſt, 'tis true, your duty is to mind the glory of God in the edification of your own Soul, and if your Pariſh Miniſter be one whoſe incapacity for the Miniſterial work is ſuch, as not to anſwer the end of the Miniſtry, you muſt look out for a better, and be where you may have more than the ſhadow of a Miniſter, even one who is competently qualified for the workes; But do this in a way as little offenſive to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as your conſcience will permit. Why will you ſeparate from that Communion, where you may be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin, eſpecially ſeeing by doing ſo you do what you cannot ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie? But if you cannot continue your Communion without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying with ſin, you muſt rather withdraw than ſin.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That ſuch as are not actually of any Communion, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> neither joyn'd with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> nor with the Diſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, of which fort there are many, eſpecially among the younger people, would remember that they have, <hi>as Chriſtians,</hi> a <hi>right to chooſe their own Paſtor,</hi> in the exerciſe of which right, 'tis their duty to have a ſpecial regard to the Glory of God, the good of their own Soul, and the peace of the Church, and therefore if you may have all theſe ends anſwer'd by joyning your ſelves to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and you can with a ſafe Conſcience do it, you do well in joyning with that Church, but if you can't with a ſafe Conſcience joyn with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but can with the Non-conformiſts, you muſt apply your ſelves to thoſe of the Non-conformiſts who do in your judgments keep moſt exactly to the rule of the Goſpel. You muſt regard God's Glory as your ultimate end, the Salvation of your Soul as an end ſubordinate, and God's word as your Rule, by which in purſuance of theſe great ends, you muſt walk. Study therefore ſeriouſly the <hi>Rule,</hi> and be ſure you do not knowingly and with deliberation deviate there from.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:56725:48"/>
3. My third requeſt is to ſuch as are joyn'd with the <hi>Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts,</hi> that you Cenſure not thoſe who continue their Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> Are you Conſcientious in your way, So ought you to eſteem them to be in their way? Would not you have them conſider you as Hypocrites, or fanciful Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouriſts, neither do you judge them to be ſuch, what, though thoſe Reaſons I have Collected out of the Writings of the Old Nonconformiſts, may faſten powerful Convictions on your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, yet they may not be of any ſuch weight in the eſteem of others. Tho' I have produc'd them to the end the Conformiſt may be mov'd to look on you as conſcientious perſons, yet do you not abuſe it, as if all Conformiſts were as much Convinc'd by 'em as you your ſelves are, and therefore muſt be eſteem'd to act contrary to their Conſciences in conforming. Take heed of ſuch cenſuring.</p>
               <p>Finally my humble deſire is, That ſuch as are of the conforming Clergie would conſider, that the above mention'd Arguments may be (as indeed with many they are) of great Force, and that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Conformiſt may be able eaſily to anſwer 'em; Yet Thouſands among the Diſſenters can not ſhake off the Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they receive from ſuch Arguments. Oh then be not too ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere in your cenſure! But conſider that theſe Diſſenters cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form but by wounding their Conſciences, be therefore very tender how you impoſe on 'em, but do your utmoſt both for a <hi>Comprehenſion,</hi> and <hi>Indulgence</hi> of thoſe ſound Proteſtants, who walk conſcientiouſly.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb facs="tcp:56725:49"/>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:56725:49"/>
            <head>The LETTERS.</head>
            <p>BY an impartial peruſal of theſe following <hi>Letters,</hi> the <hi>Reader</hi> may eaſily perceive the <hi>difference</hi> there was between ſome <hi>great States</hi> men in <hi>Queen Elizabeth's</hi> time, and ſome of the <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy,</hi> and that when the <hi>Clergy</hi> were for a ſevere perſecuting Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Diſſenters, the <hi>Councill,</hi> and in ſpecial the Lord <hi>Burleigh,</hi> that wonder of his age (though a Son of the Church of <hi>England)</hi> endeavour'd the relief of the <hi>Non-conformists.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Letters</hi> were firſt taken from <hi>Arch-Biſhop Whitgift</hi>'s own Copy, as may appear from the Title prefix'd to the Letter, thus, <hi>My Lord Treaſurer</hi>'s <hi>Letter unto me,</hi> and <hi>my anſwer to the Lord Treaſurer.</hi> There are ſome great perſons among the Clergy, who have ſeen 'em in Manuſcript.</p>
            <div n="1" type="letter">
               <head>Numb. 1.</head>
               <p>THere is a Letter written to the Biſhop for the execution of her Majeſties Proclamation for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity ſet forth in the book, and other injunctions, pen'd (as is ſuppos'd) by Sir <hi>Thomas Smith;</hi> The which I'll not fully tranſcribe. There is one clauſe only that is for my purpoſe, which is concerning the meetings of the Clergy, which were firſt ordained to keep all Churches in the Dioceſs, in an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niform and Godly Order, which <hi>now is commonly ſaid</hi> (the <hi>more is the pity) to be only uſed of you [i. e.</hi> the Biſhop and his Clergy,] <hi>and your Officers to get money,</hi> or <hi>for ſome other purpoſes;</hi> This paſſage ſhewes the corruption of the Clergy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="letter">
               <head>Numb. 2.</head>
               <head>
                  <hi>A Letter written by the</hi> Lord Treaſurer Cecil <hi>to</hi> Arch-biſhop Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gift, <hi>in anſwer to one received from the</hi> Arch-biſhop.</head>
               <p>MAY it pleaſe your Grace; I perceive that the <hi>Biſhop of Rocheſter</hi> through your perſwaſion is contented to be removed to <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> whereof I am glad, whereby the <hi>Dean of Weſtminſter</hi> may be plac'd, as your <hi>Grace</hi> may think fit, and I do deſire her Majeſty will new place all the Biſhops in the void room, whereof I am very mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and deſirous for the benefit of the Church, <hi>wiſhing that the Church
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:56725:50"/>
may take that good thereby,</hi> that <hi>it hath need of,</hi> for ſurely <hi>your Grace muſt pardon me, I rather wiſh it, than look,</hi> or <hi>much hope for</hi> it; I ſee ſuch <hi>Worldlyneſs</hi> in <hi>many that were otherwiſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected before they came to Cathedral Churches,</hi> that I <hi>fear the places alter the men,</hi> but herein I condemn not all: but <hi>few</hi> there be that do better, being <hi>Biſhops</hi> (in the void roomes whereof I am very mindfull,) than being <hi>Preachers they did;</hi> I am bold thus to ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my mind of Biſhops to an Arch biſhop, but I clear my ſelf, I mean nothing in any conceit to your <hi>Grace,</hi> for though of late I <hi>have vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in my poor opinion,</hi> in that by <hi>your order, poor ſimple men</hi> have rather been <hi>ſought for by inquiſition to be found Offenders,</hi> than upon <hi>their facts condemned,</hi> yet ſurely I do not for all this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from your Grace in Amity and Love, but I do reverence your Learning and Integrity, and wiſh that the <hi>Spirit of gentleneſs</hi> may win, rather than <hi>ſeverity;</hi> But therefore enough of the miſbehavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of <hi>Browning,</hi> towards the <hi>Maſter of Trinity Colledg;</hi> I am ſorry to hear as I do, eſteeming him meeter for <hi>Bethlehem</hi> than for that Colledg. The Queen's Majeſty asked me, what I thought of <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers</hi> to be the Miniſter of the <hi>Temple,</hi> whereunto I anſwered, that at the requeſt of <hi>Dr. Alney</hi> in his ſickneſs, and of a number of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Gentlemen of the <hi>Temple,</hi> I had yeilded my Allowance of him to that place, ſo as he will ſhew himſelf <hi>Conformable</hi> to the <hi>order of the Church,</hi> whereunto I was inform'd, that he would ſo be; But <hi>her Majeſty</hi> told me that your <hi>Grace</hi> did not ſo allow of him, which I ſaid might be for ſomething ſuppos'd to be written by him, Titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>de Diſciplina Eccleſiaſtica,</hi> whereupon her <hi>Majeſty</hi> command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me to write to your <hi>Grace,</hi> to know your opinion, which I pray your Grace to ſignifie unto her, as God ſhall move ye, ſurely it were great pity, that any impediment ſhould be occaſion to the contrary, for he is well learn'd, very honeſt, and well lov'd, and allow'd of the generality of that houſe. Mr. <hi>Bond</hi> told me, that your <hi>Grace</hi> liked well of him, and ſo do I alſo, as of one well learn'd, and honeſt, but (as I told him) if he came not to the place with ſome applauſe of the Company, he ſhall be weary thereof, and I commended him to her Majeſty, if <hi>Travers</hi> ſhould not, but her Majesty thinketh him not fit for that place, becauſe of his infirmity. Thus I end, wiſhing your <hi>Grace</hi> Aſſiſtance of God's Spirit to govern your charge unblameably</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Graces to command
<hi>William Burleigh.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>From the Court at</hi> Oatlands, <date>Sept. <hi>17. 1584.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="letter">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:56725:50"/>
               <head>Numb. 3.</head>
               <head>
                  <hi>A part of a Letter ſent unto the</hi> Arch-biſhop <hi>of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>and</hi> Biſhop of London, <hi>from her Majeſties</hi> Councill <hi>about</hi> September <hi>20. 1584.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter our hearty commendations to both your Lordſhips, although we have heard of late times ſundry complaints out of divers countries of this Realm, of ſome proceedings againſt a great number of Eccleſiaſtical Perſons, ſome Parſons of Churches, ſome Vicars, ſome Curates, but all <hi>Preachers,</hi> whereby ſome were deprived of their livings, ſome ſuſpended from their Miniſtry, and preaching, yet we have forborn to enter into any particular examination of ſuch complaints, thinking, that howſoever inferior Officers, as <hi>Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, Commiſſaries, Arch-Deacons,</hi> and ſuch like, whoſe Offices are of <hi>more value</hi> and <hi>profit by ſuch kind of proceedings,</hi> might in ſuch ſort proceed againſt the Miniſters of the Church, yet your Lordſhip the <hi>Arch-Biſhop</hi> of that Province of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> have beſide your general authority, ſome particular intereſt in the preſent juriſdiction of ſundry <hi>Biſhopricks</hi> vacant, and you alſo the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> both for your own authority in your Dioceſs, and as head Commiſſioner Eccleſiaſtical would have a Paſtoral regard over the particular Officers, to <hi>ſtay,</hi> and <hi>temperate them in their haſty proceedings</hi> againſt the <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and eſpecially againſt ſuch as do <hi>carneſtly profeſs,</hi> and <hi>inſtruct the people</hi> againſt the dangerous Sects of. <hi>Papiſtry;</hi> but yet of late, hearing of the <hi>lamentable eſtate of the Church</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> that is, of a great number of zealous and learned Preachers, they are ſuſpended from their cures, the vacancy of the place for the moſt part without any Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry or Preaching, Prayers and Sacraments, and in ſome places of certain appointed to thoſe void roomes, being perſons neither of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor of good names, and in other places of that County, a great number of perſons occupying the cures, being notoriouſly <hi>unfit,</hi> moſt for lack of learning, many charg'd or chargable with great and enormions faults, as <hi>drunkenneſs, filthineſs of Life, Gameſters at Cardes, hunting of Alehouſes,</hi> and ſuch like, againſt whom we hear not <hi>of any proceedings,</hi> but that they are <hi>quietly ſuffered to the ſlander of the Church,</hi> to the offence of good people, yea to the famiſhing of them for lack of good teaching, and thereby dangerous
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:56725:51"/>
to the ſubverting of many weaklins from their duties <hi>to God,</hi> and the <hi>Queens Majeſty,</hi> by <hi>ſecret Jeſuites,</hi> and <hi>counterfeit Papiſts,</hi> and having thus in a general ſort heard out of many partes of the like of this lamentable Eſtate of the Church, yet to the intent, we ſhould not be deceived in the generality of the reports we ſought to be inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="letter">
               <head>Numb. 4.</head>
               <head>
                  <hi>A Letter from the</hi> Lord Treaſurer <hi>to the</hi> Arch-biſhop. <hi>July 5. 1584.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT may pleaſe your <hi>Grace,</hi> I am ſorry to trouble you ſo often as I do, but I am more troubled my ſelf, not only with many private Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſundry Miniſters, recommended for perſons of <hi>credit,</hi> for <hi>peaceable perſons</hi> in their Miniſtry, and yet by complaints to your <hi>Grace,</hi> and other your Collegues in commiſſion, <hi>greatly troubled,</hi> but alſo I am daily now charged by <hi>Councellors</hi> and <hi>publique per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> to neglect my duty in <hi>not ſtaying theſe your Graces</hi> proceedings, ſo <hi>vehement,</hi> and ſo general againſt <hi>Miniſters</hi> and <hi>Preachers,</hi> as the <hi>Papiſts thereby are greatly encouraged,</hi> all <hi>evil diſpoſed perſons</hi> and <hi>ſubjects animated,</hi> and <hi>thereby the Queen's Majeſties ſafety endangered;</hi> with theſe kinds of Arguments I am daily aſſailed, againſt which I anſwer, that I think your <hi>Grace</hi> doth nothing, but being duely examined, tendeth to the maintenance of the Religion now Eſtabliſhed, and to avoid <hi>Schiſm</hi> in <hi>the Church,</hi> I alſo have for example ſhewd your papers ſent to me, how fully the Church is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd with Preachers, and how <hi>ſmall a number</hi> there are that do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for their <hi>ſingularity,</hi> but theſe occaſions do not ſatisfie all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, neither do I ſeek to ſatisfie all perſons, but with <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Truth.</hi> But now my <hi>good Lord,</hi> by chance I have come to the ſight of an <hi>Inſtrument</hi> of <hi>24 Articles</hi> of great <hi>length</hi> and <hi>curioſity,</hi> formed in a <hi>Romiſh Stile,</hi> to examine all manner of Miniſters in this time without <hi>diſtinction of perſons,</hi> which Articles are Entituled <hi>apud Lambeth, May 1584</hi> to be executed <hi>ex officio mero,</hi> &amp;c. and upon this occaſion I have ſeen them. I did recommend unto your Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces favour <hi>two Miniſters</hi> Curates of <hi>Cambridge-ſhire</hi> to be favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably heard, and your <hi>Grace</hi> wrote to me, that they were <hi>contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſeditious,</hi> and <hi>perſons vagrant,</hi> to maintain this controverſie, wherewith I <hi>charg'd them ſharply,</hi> and they both deny'd theſe char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and requir'd to be <hi>tryed,</hi> and ſo to receive puniſhment, I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that your <hi>Grace</hi> would ſo charge them, and then I ſhould ſee afterwards, what they ſhould deſerve, and advis'd them to reſort
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:56725:51"/>
to your <hi>Grace,</hi> comforting them that they ſhould find favourable proceedings, and ſo I hoped upon my former commendations the rather. What may be ſaid to them I know not, nor whether they have been ſo faulty as your Grace have been inform'd, neither do I mean to treat for to favour ſuch men, for pardon, I may ſpeak upon their amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but now they coming to me, I asked how your <hi>Grace</hi> proceeded with them, they ſay, they are commanded to be examined by the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and I asked them whereof, they ſaid of a great <hi>number of Articles,</hi> but they could have no copies of them, I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, that they might anſwer to the truth, they ſaid, that they were ſo many in number, and ſo diverſe, that they were afraid to anſwer to them, for fear of captious interpretation, upon this I ſent for the <hi>Regiſter,</hi> who brought me the <hi>Articles,</hi> which I have read, and find ſo <hi>curiouſly penn'd,</hi> ſo <hi>full</hi> of <hi>branches</hi> and <hi>circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and I think, the <hi>Inquiſitors of</hi> Spain <hi>uſe not ſo many queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> to <hi>comprehend,</hi> and <hi>to trap their preyes.</hi> I know your <hi>Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,</hi> can defend theſe with all their particles, but ſurely under your <hi>Graces correction,</hi> this <hi>Juridical</hi> and <hi>Canonical ſifting of poor Miniſters is not to edifie</hi> and <hi>reform,</hi> and in charity I think they ought not to anſwer to all theſe nice points, except they were very noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Offenders in <hi>Papiſtry</hi> or <hi>Hereſie.</hi> Now good my <hi>Lord,</hi> bear with my ſcribling, I <hi>write with the Teſtimony of a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi> I deſire the peace of the Church, I deſire concord and unity in the exerciſe of our Religion, I fear no ſenſual wilfull recuſant, but I conclude that according to my ſimple judgment, <hi>this kind of proceeding is too much ſavouring</hi> the Romiſh Inquiſition, and <hi>is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a device to ſeek for Oſſenders, than to reform any;</hi> This was not that charitable instruction that I thought was intended. If theſe poor Miniſters ſhould in ſome few points have any ſcrupulous concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions meet to be removed, this is not a <hi>charitable way</hi> to ſend them to anſwer to your common Regiſter upon ſo many Articles at one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, without commodity of inſtruction by your <hi>Regiſter,</hi> whoſe office is only to receive their anſwers, by which the parties are first ſubject to condemnation, before they be taught their errors; It may be that I ſay that <hi>Canoniſts</hi> may maintain this proceeding by Rules of their Lawes, but though <hi>omnia lice<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, omnia non expediunt.</hi> I pray your <hi>Grace</hi> bear this (one, perchance a fault) <hi>that I have willed them</hi> not <hi>to anſwer theſe Articles, except their Conſciences may ſuffer them.</hi> And yet I have ſharply admoniſhed them, that if they be diſturbers in their Churches, they muſt be corrected, and yet upon
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:56725:52"/>
your <hi>Graces</hi> anſwer to me, <hi>ne ſutor ultra erepidam,</hi> neither will I put <hi>falcem in alterius meſſem.</hi> My paper teaches me to make an end.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Graces at command
<hi>William Burleigh.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
                  <p>Your Grace muſt pardon my haſty ſcribling, for I have done this <hi>raptim,</hi> and without correction.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="letter">
               <head>Numb. 5.</head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> Treaſurer's reply <hi>to an anſwer of the</hi> Arch-biſhop's <hi>unto the former Letter.</hi> July <hi>17. 1584.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Have received your Graces loving Letter, anſwering Speeches (as I think) delivered by your Chaplain <hi>Dr. Coſſins,</hi> and I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you are <hi>ſharply mov'd</hi> to blame me, and clear your ſelf, I know I have many faults, but I hope I have not given ſuch cauſe of offence, as your Letter expreſſeth, I deny nothing that your Grace thinketh meet to proceed in with theſe whom you call factious, and therefore there is no controverſie betwixt you and me expreſſed in your Letter. The <hi>controverſie is paſſ'd in your Grace's Letter in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> and ſo I do reſt ſatisfied, your Grace promiſed me to deal (I ſay,) only with ſuch as violate order, and to charge them therewith, which I allow well thereof; <hi>But your</hi> Grace <hi>not charging men with ſuch faults, ſeeketh by examination to urge them to accuſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> and then I think <hi>you'l puniſh them.</hi> I think your Graces proceedings is, (I will not ſay <hi>rigorous</hi> nor <hi>captious)</hi> but I think it is <hi>ſcarce charitable.</hi> I have no leiſure to write more, and therefore I will end, for <hi>writing will but encreaſe offence,</hi> and I mean not to offend your Grace. I am content that your <hi>Grace,</hi> and my <hi>Lord of London</hi> where I hear <hi>Brown</hi> is, uſe him as your Wiſdomes ſhall think meet. If I had known his faults, I might be blam'd for write<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for him, but <hi>when by examination only it is to ſift him with 24 Articles I have cauſe to pity the poor man.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Graces as Friendly as any,
<hi>William Burleigh.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="letter">
               <head>Numb. 6.</head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> Arch-Biſhop's <hi>Anſwer to the</hi> Lord Treaſurer.</head>
               <p>MY ſingular <hi>good Lord;</hi> God knoweth how deſirous I have been from time to time to ſatisfie your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> in all things, and to have my doings approved to you, for which cauſe, ſince my coming to this place, I have done nothing of importance without your
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:56725:52"/>
advice, I have riſen early, and ſat up late, to write unto you ſuch objections and anſwers as on either ſide were uſed, I have not done the like to any man, and ſhall I now ſay that I have loſt my labour, or ſhall my juſt dealing with two of the moſt diſorder'd Miniſters in a whole <hi>Dioceſs</hi> (the obſtinacy and contempt of whom, eſpecially of one of them your ſelf would not bear in any ſubjected to your Authority) cauſe you <hi>ſo to</hi> think and ſpeak of my doings, yea and of my ſelf, no man living ſhould have made me beleive it. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>an old friend is better than a new,</hi> and I truſt your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> will not ſo light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caſt off your old friend, for any of thoſe <hi>new fangled factious Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> whoſe fruits are to make diviſions, whereſoever they come, and to ſeparate old and aſſured friends. <hi>Your Lordſhip</hi> ſeemeth to charge me with <hi>breach of promiſe,</hi> touching my manner of proceeding, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I am no way guilty, but I have alter'd my firſt courſe of depriving them for not ſubſcribing, only juſtifiable by law and common practice, both in the time of <hi>King Edward,</hi> and from the beginning of her <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties</hi> Reign. <hi>Your Lordſhip</hi> alſo objecteth that I took this courſe for the better maintenance of my <hi>book,</hi> &amp;c. mine enemies ſaid ſo indeed, but I truſt my friends have a better opinion in me; Why ſhould I ſeek for any confirmation of my book after years, or what ſhould I get there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by more than already? And yet if <hi>ſubſcription</hi> may confirm it; it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd long ago, by the ſubſcription of all the Clergy almoſt in <hi>England</hi> before my time, even of <hi>Branie</hi> alſo who ſeemeth now to be ſo wilful. Mine enemies and tongues of this ſlanderous and uncharitable Sect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, that I am revolted, become <hi>a Papiſt,</hi> and I know not what; But it proceedeth from their lewdneſs, not from any deſert of mine, and I diſdain to anſwer to ſuch notorious untruths, which the beſt of them dare not avouch to my face. Your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> ſeemeth further to burden me with <hi>wilfulneſs,</hi> I am ſure, that you are not ſo perſwaded of me, I will appeal to your own Conſcience, <hi>there is difference between wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>conſtancy,</hi> I have taken upon me the defence of the Religion, and Rights of this Church of England, to appeaſe the Sects of Schiſmes therein, to reduce all the Miniſters thereof to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity and due obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, <hi>herein I intend to be conſtant,</hi> and not to waver with every wind, the which alſo my place, my perſon, my duty, the law, her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and the goodneſs of the cauſe doth require of me, and wherein your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> and others all things conſidered, ought in duty to aſſiſt and countenance me. It is ſtrange that a man in my place dealing with ſo good warranties as I do, ſhould be ſo encounter'd, and for not yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhould be accounted <hi>wilful,</hi> but I muſt be contented, <hi>vincit, qui pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur,</hi>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:56725:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and if my friends herein forſake me, I truſt God will not, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the law, her Majeſty, who hath laid the charge on me, and are able to protect me; But of all other things it moſt greiveth me, that your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> ſhould ſay, that the <hi>two Miniſters</hi> fare the worſe becauſe your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> ſent them; Hath your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> ever had any cauſe ſo to think of me, it is needleſs for me to proteſt my heart and affections towards you above all other men, the world knoweth it, and I am aſſured that your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> nothing doubeth thereof, I have rather cauſe to complain to your Lordſhip of your ſelf, that upon ſo ſmall occaſion, and in the behalf of two ſuch, you will ſo hardly conceive of me, yea and as it were <hi>counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance perſons,</hi> ſo <hi>meanly qualified in ſo evil a cauſe againſt me your Lordſhip's ſo long tryed friend,</hi> and their ordinary, that hath not ſo been in times paſt, now it ſhould leaſt of all be, I may not ſuffer the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious contempt of any of them, eſpecially unleſs I will become <hi>Aeſop's block,</hi> well, becauſe I would be loath to omit any thing whereby your Lordſhip might be ſatisfied, I have ſent unto you certain reaſons to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the manner of my proceeding which I marvel ſhould be ſo much <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked</hi> in this cauſe, having been ſo long practis'd in the like, yea in the ſame, and never before this time found fault with, truly my Lord, I must proceed this way, or not at all, the reaſons I have ſet down in this paper, and I heartily pray your Lordſhip not to be carryed away either from the cauſe, or from my ſelf upon unjuſt ſurmiſes or clamours, leaſt you be ſome occaſion of that confuſion, which hereafter you would be ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for: For mine own part, I deſire no farther defence in theſe occaſions of your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> nor any other than juſtice and law will yield unto me. In my private affairs I know I ſtand in need of friends, eſpecially of your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> of whom I have made alwayes an aſſured account, but in theſe publick actions I ſee no cauſe why I ſhould ſeek for friends, ſeeing they to whom the care of the common weal is committed, ought out of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty therein to joyn with me, to conclude, I am your Lordſhips aſſured, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will I ever be perſwaded, but that you bear an hearty good will towards me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>So far</hi> Whitgift. <hi>If Dr.</hi> Burnet <hi>would undertake the carrying on the</hi> Hiſtory of Eccleſiaſtical Affairs <hi>all the time</hi> Q. Eliz. <hi>liv'd, and in order thereunto, might he be ſo happy as to obtain a ſight of all thoſe great things were then on the ſtage, the world would ſee how little they are owing unto</hi> Heylin <hi>for his Hiſtory, and alſo under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand how unjuſtly the Old Proteſtants call'd</hi> Puritanès, <hi>have been repreſented as factious.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:56725:53"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
